<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName archivearticle.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Exp Med</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Exp. Med</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of Experimental Medicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-1007</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1540-9538</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2192096</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">95310866</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">7540657</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>GD2 oligosaccharide: target for cytotoxic T lymphocytes</article-title></title-group><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>1</day><month>7</month><year>1995</year></pub-date><volume>182</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><permissions><license license-type="openaccess"><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution&#x02013;Noncommercial&#x02013;Share Alike&#x02013;No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the publication date (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rupress.org/terms">http://www.rupress.org/terms</ext-link>). After six months it is available under a Creative Commons License (Attribution&#x02013;Noncommercial&#x02013;Share Alike 4.0 Unported license, as described at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Carbohydrate antigens rarely provide target epitopes for cytotoxic T lymphocytes (CTL). Disialoganglioside GD2 is a glycolipid expressed at high levels in human tumors and a small group of murine lymphomas (EL4, RBL5, RMA, RMA-S, A13, and BALBRVE). Immunization of C57B1/6 mice with irradiated EL4 cells stimulated a specific CTL response and protected these animals from engraftment of EL4 lymphoma. The CTL activity resided in the CD4-CD8+ population, was dependent on T cell receptor alpha/beta, and was not removed by anti-natural killer cell immunoabsorption, but was restricted to GD2 and H-2b bearing targets. CTL activity could be completely inhibited by GD2-oligosaccharide- specific monoclonal antibodies and their F(ab')2 fragments, but not by immunoglobulin G3 myelomas or antibodies against GD3 or GM2. Soluble GD2 did not inhibit specific tumor lysis. RMA-S lymphoma cells (GD2+H- 2b-TAP2 deficient) were resistant to GD2-specific CTL. Sialic acid- containing peptides eluted from EL4 lymphoma cells could (a) stabilize H-2 molecules on RMA-S cells and (b) sensitize them for GD2-specific CTL. Control peptides (derived from vesicular stomatitis virus nucleoprotein peptide and GD2-negative lymphomas) could also stabilize H-2 on RMA-S, but were resistant to GD2-specific CTL. These H-2-binding peptides could be purified by anti-GD2 affinity chromatography. We postulate a new class of naturally occurring epitopes for T cells where branched-chain oligosaccharides are linked to peptides with anchoring motifs for the major histocompatibility complex class I pocket. While analogous to the haptens trinitrophenyl and O-beta-linked acetyl- glucosamine, the potential implications of natural carbohydrates as antigenic epitopes for CTL in biology are considerable.</p></abstract></article-meta></front></article>