<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5524713</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28740238</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">5740</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-05740-z</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The resident pathobiont <italic>Staphylococcus xylosus</italic> in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>-deficient skin accelerates spontaneous skin inflammation</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Yeji</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Yong-Soo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Jin-Young</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Su-Hyun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>Yun-Yong</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Kweon</surname><given-names>Mi-Na</given-names></name><address><email>mnkweon@amc.seoul.kr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Mucosal Immunology Laboratory, Department of Convergence Medicine, University of Ulsan College of Medicine/Asan Medical Center, Seoul, Korea </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0842 2126</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.413967.e</institution-id><institution>ASAN Institute for Life Science, Asan Medical Center, </institution></institution-wrap>Seoul, Korea </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>7</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>24</day><month>7</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>6348</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>4</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>1</day><month>6</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2017</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">I&#x003ba;B&#x003b6;, which is encoded by the <italic>Nfkbiz</italic> gene, is a member of the nuclear I&#x003ba;B family of proteins that act as transcriptional regulators via association with NF-&#x003ba;B. <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>-deficient (<italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup>) mice develop spontaneous dermatitis; however, the underlying mechanism has yet to be elucidated. In our study, we found higher skin pathology scores and more serum IgE antibodies and trans-epidermal water loss in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> than in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>-sufficient (<italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup>) mice. There was also greater expansion of IFN-&#x003b3;-, IL-17A-, and IL-22-secreting CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells and of IL-17A-secreting &#x003b3;&#x003b4;<sup>+</sup> T cells in the skin of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice than in with <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> mice. Pyrosequencing analysis showed decreased diversity of resident bacteria and markedly expanded <italic>Staphylococcus (S.) xylosus</italic> in the skin of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice. Oral administration of antibiotics including cephalexin and enrofloxacin ameliorated skin inflammation. Topical application of <italic>S. xylosus</italic> also resulted in the expansion of IL-17A-secreting CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells along with high levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines and chemokines in the skin of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice. The expansion of commensal <italic>S. xylosus</italic> may be one cause of skin dysbiosis in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice and suggests that the <italic>Nfkbiz</italic> gene may play a regulatory role in the microbiota-skin immunity axis.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2017</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">The skin acts as an important physical barrier that is directly exposed to numerous pathogens in the environment. It maintains a symbiotic relationship with various commensal microorganisms that inhabit it<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. Changes in microbial composition have been found in many skin diseases including atopic dermatitis (AD) and psoriasis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. For instance, microbiome analysis in patients with AD revealed that the proportion of <italic>Staphylococcus (S.) aureus</italic> that increased during disease flares correlated with disease severity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. <italic>S. aureus</italic> was also isolated from skin lesions of STAT3-deficient mice and of ADAM17-deficient mice with spontaneous dermatitis, and antibiotic treatments were essential to control the disease progression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. <italic>S. xylosus</italic> is a coagulase-negative gram-positive <italic>staphylococcal</italic> species and a common skin commensal bacterium of humans and other mammals<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Some cases of <italic>S. xylosus</italic> infection, including erythema nodosum<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>, pyelonephritis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>, and corneal infections<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup> occur in humans. In laboratory mice, <italic>S. xylosus</italic> has been associated with spontaneous dermatitis in both NOS2<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup> and athymic nude mice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup> and with conjunctivitis in NADPH oxidase<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>, implying that <italic>S. xylosus</italic> is an opportunistic pathogen. Although microorganisms are not the only inducers of skin disease, it seems likely that microbial alteration and the predominance of specific resident bacteria directly affect dermatitis severity.</p><p id="Par3">As gut microbes are associated with gut immunity, commensal microbiota in the skin also play a pivotal role in local immunity to maintain homeostasis both in a steady state and during infection<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. When the skin of germ-free mice was colonized with <italic>S. epidermidis</italic> and compared with that of conventional mice, the germ-free mice had fewer resident-effector T cells than the conventional mice and developed protective T-cell responses against the <italic>Leishmania major</italic> parasite<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. In addition, <italic>S. epidermidis</italic>-induced IL-17A<sup>+</sup>CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells enhanced innate barrier immunity and ameliorated pathogen infection<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. However, when the expansion and aberration of commensal microbiota with pathogenic potential occurred under specific circumstances, such as infection and injury, it could disturb immune system homeostasis and worsen inflammation. Previous studies revealed that staphylococcal enterotoxin B or alpha-toxin derived by <italic>S. aureus</italic> induced IL-17A secretion, leading to the abnormal proliferation of keratinocytes and recruitment of inflammatory cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. Notably, patients with severe skin signs showed more <italic>S. aureus</italic> specific-IgE antibodies (Abs) than those with mild symptoms<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. Because of the complex interplay among commensal microbes, immunity, and environmental factors in the skin mucosa, the underlying mechanisms have yet to be elucidated.</p><p id="Par4">I&#x003ba;B&#x003b6;, encoded by the <italic>Nfkbiz</italic> gene, is a member of the nuclear I&#x003ba;B family of proteins that act as transcriptional regulators via association with NF-&#x003ba;B. Several previous studies revealed a critical role of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b6; signaling in the regulation of immune responses<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. I&#x003ba;B&#x003b6;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice showed severe skin irritation in the face, neck, and periocular regions and several signs of Sj&#x000f6;gren&#x02019;s syndrome<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. I&#x003ba;B&#x003b6; interacts with NF-&#x003ba;B and is associated with both positive and negative regulation of NF-kB transcriptional activity. Like other I&#x003ba;B proteins, it has inhibitory effects on the transcription of inflammatory genes regulated by NF-kB, such as TNF-&#x003b1;, but it can also induce pro-inflammatory cytokines, such as IL-6 and IL-12p40<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. I&#x003ba;B&#x003b6; also plays an important role in adaptive immunity by regulating Th17 development<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Although IL-6 and IL-17A production was significantly reduced in I&#x003ba;B&#x003b6;-deficient cells <italic>in vitro</italic>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>, highly elevated levels of these cytokines were detected <italic>in vivo</italic>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. It is known that I&#x003ba;B&#x003b6; deficiency in hematopoietic cells is not the major cause of spontaneous inflammation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. The specific depletion of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b6; in lymphocytes or myeloid cells does not induce inflammation in the conjunctiva and ocular skin, although enhanced apoptosis in I&#x003ba;B&#x003b6;-deficient epithelial cells is involved in the onset of Sj&#x000f6;gren&#x02019;s syndrome-like autoimmune disease in I&#x003ba;B&#x003b6;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. It is not clear how the immune system is overactivated by depletion of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b6;.</p><p id="Par5">In this study, we demonstrated that <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>-deficient (<italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup>) mice with atopic-like dermatitis have elevated serum IgE Abs and drastically increased numbers of IL-17A-secreting CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells in skin. Microbiome analysis showed the predominant expansion of <italic>Staphylococcus</italic> sequences, particularly <italic>S</italic>. <italic>xylosus</italic>, and a significant decrease in the diversity of commensal bacteria. Antibiotics completely eliminated dermatitis symptoms, implying specific taxonomic alterations associated with the induction of hyper-immune responses in the skin. Of note, the inoculation of <italic>S</italic>. <italic>xylosus</italic> in the skin of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> and their heterozygous littermates (<italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup>) resulted in the expansion of IL-17A production from CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title><italic>Nfkbiz</italic><sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice developed spontaneous skin inflammation</title><p id="Par6">To clarify the mechanism underlying the development of dermatitis in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice, we first confirmed the disease progression in our facility. As reported by others<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>, we established that erosions and hair loss that were exhibited throughout the ocular region beginning about age 4 weeks in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice then extended to the whole body (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1A</xref>). In these mice, disease incidence and clinical score were also significantly increased from about age 4 weeks in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1B</xref>). The levels of transepidermal water loss (TEWL), which show abnormal skin barrier function, and of serum IgE Ab, which has a positive correlation with the severity of atopic dermatitis and psoriasis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>, was higher in the <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice than in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>-sufficient (<italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup>) mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1C</xref>). In addition, the levels of various pro-inflammatory cytokines (i.e., IL-1&#x003b2;, IFN-&#x003b3;, TNF-&#x003b1;, IL-6, IL-17A, and IL-22) and chemokines (i.e., MCP-1, MIP-1&#x003b1;, RANTES, and KC) were significantly increased in the serum of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice when compared with <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1D</xref>). There were marked increases in the numbers of CD11b<sup>+</sup> or CD207<sup>+</sup> or CD11c<sup>+</sup> cells and CD4<sup>+</sup> or CD8&#x003b1;<sup>+</sup> cells infiltrating into the epidermis and dermis of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice as determined by confocal microscopy analysis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1E</xref>). We conducted an intense analysis and found no significant phenotype differences in the innate lymphoid cell subsets isolated from <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> and <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice (data not shown). Once we confirmed the development of dermatitis in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice, we performed further experiments.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Spontaneous skin inflammation develops in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice. (<bold>A</bold>) Representative skin phenotype and histology of skin biopsy from <italic>Nfkbz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> and <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice at age 10 weeks. Scale bar&#x02009;=&#x02009;50&#x02009;&#x000b5;m. (<bold>B</bold>) Disease incidence and progression of dermatitis in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> and <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;20). Dermatitis incidence (score&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;3) is shown as a percentage. (<bold>C</bold>) Trans-epidermal water loss (TEWL) and serum IgE antibody levels in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> and <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice. (<bold>D</bold>) Cytokines and chemokine levels in a skin homogenate. (<bold>E</bold>) Confocal microscopy of skin biopsies from <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> and <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice. Scale bar&#x02009;=&#x02009;50&#x02009;&#x003bc;m. Data are representative of three independent experiments. All data are mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;s.e.m. *<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, **<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_5740_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e761"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>IL-17A- and IL-22-secreting skin-resident T cells increased in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic><sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice</title><p id="Par7">To determine the cell types involved in dermatitis in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice, we analyzed immune cells in the skin via flow cytometry. The skin-resident dendritic cells (DCs) include Langerhans cells (LCs) in the epidermis and DCs in the dermis (dDCs), which can be divided into various subsets<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. Absolute numbers of MHCII<sup>+</sup>CD11c<sup>+</sup> cells were highly elevated in the epidermis and dermis of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice in comparison with those in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1A</xref>). Among four DC subsets in skin, the relative percentages of CD103<sup>+</sup> dDCs (CD11b<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup>CD207<sup>&#x02212;</sup>CD103<sup>+</sup>) were increased while CD207<sup>+</sup> dDCs (CD11b<sup>+</sup>CD207<sup>+</sup>CD103<sup>+</sup>) were decreased in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice when compared with <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2A</xref>). No significant changes of relative percentages were found in LCs (CD11b<sup>+</sup>CD207<sup>+</sup>CD103<sup>&#x02212;</sup>) and CD11b<sup>+</sup> dDCs (CD11b<sup>+</sup>CD207<sup>&#x02212;</sup>CD103<sup>&#x02212;</sup>) between <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> and <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2A</xref>). We next addressed skin-resident T-cell subsets and found that &#x003b3;&#x003b4;<sup>high</sup> T cells with few CD4 and CD8 T cells were present in the skin of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> mice, but <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice with AD had massive infiltration of CD4, CD8, and &#x003b3;&#x003b4;<sup>mid</sup> T cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2B</xref>). Interestingly, accumulated CD4, CD8, and &#x003b3;&#x003b4;<sup>mid</sup> skin-resident T cells obtained from <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice predominantly produced IL-17A and IL-22 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2C</xref>). When these findings are considered together, CD103<sup>+</sup> dDCs and IL-17A- and IL-22-secreting skin-resident T cells may be associated with skin inflammation in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>IL-17A- and IL-22-secreting T cells infiltrate into skin of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice. Flow cytometry analysis of (<bold>A</bold>) DC subsets in CD45<sup>+</sup>MHCII<sup>+</sup>CD11c<sup>+</sup> cells and (<bold>B</bold>) T cells in skin of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> and <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice. (<bold>C</bold>) IL-17A and IL-22 production from each cell subset after gating CD45-positive skin cells. Data are representative of three independent experiments. *<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, **<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_5740_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e981"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title><italic>Nfkbiz</italic>-deficient skin exhibited decreased diversity of the bacterial community and an increase in <italic>S. xylosus</italic></title><p id="Par8">Numerous studies have shown that dysbiosis of the skin microbiome is associated with development of AD and psoriasis in human patients and in animal models<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. Hence, we next addressed the skin microbiota to determine whether the resident microbiota is also related to the development of dermatitis in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice. When quantity of bacterial 16S rRNA was assessed by PCR, there was a significantly higher bacterial burden in the skin homogenates of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice than from <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3A</xref>). Further pyrosequencing analysis using skin tissue homogenates revealed that <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> and <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice have segregated microbiota composition (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3B</xref>) and that <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice have less diversity and species richness in than <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3C</xref>). The <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice had decreased levels of <italic>Pseudomonas</italic>, <italic>Acinetobacter</italic>, <italic>Gemella</italic>, <italic>Ochrobactrum</italic>, and <italic>Rhodococcus</italic> genera (data not shown) but high abundance of <italic>S. xylosus</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3D</xref>). To further confirm the expansion of <italic>S. xylosus</italic> under disease conditions, we next cultured skin swabs from <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> and <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice on mannitol salt agar (MSA), a medium selective for <italic>Staphylococcus</italic>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>. Consistent with the pyrosequencing data, numerous yellow colonies on MSA, mostly identified as <italic>S. xylosus</italic> by 16S rRNA sequencing, were obtained from skin swab culture of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3E</xref>). In addition, elevated numbers of <italic>Staphylococcus</italic> colonies were detected with increasing age (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3F</xref>), which correlated with the clinical score of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1B</xref>). Overall, decreased bacterial diversity with the striking expansion of <italic>S. xylosus</italic> occurred in the skin of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice with dermatitis.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Increased bacterial burden and decreased bacterial diversity in skin of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice. (<bold>A</bold>) Relative expression of 16&#x02009;s rDNA universal bacteria in skin of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> and <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice. (<bold>B</bold>) Principal coordinate analysis of unweighted and weighted UniFrac distances between samples from skin of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> and <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice. (<bold>C</bold>) Shannon index, observed operational taxonomic units (OTUs), and phylogenetic diversity (PD) whole tree of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> and <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice. (<bold>D</bold>) Composition of skin bacterial communities in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> and <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice at phylum level (&#x0003e;1% of total 16S rRNA sequences) with additional speciation of <italic>Corynebacterium</italic> and <italic>Staphylococcus</italic> genera. Each bar represents relative abundance in one mouse. Results are representative of two experiments (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;4&#x02013;6 per group). (<bold>E</bold> and <bold>F</bold>) Quantification of <italic>Staphylococcus</italic> species from skin swabs of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> and <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice performed using mannitol salt agar (MSA). Data are mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;s.e.m. (<bold>A</bold> and <bold>F</bold>). *<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, **<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01.&#x000a0;n.d., not detected.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_5740_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e1263"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Antibiotic treatment ameliorated dermatitis in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic><sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice</title><p id="Par9">To clarify the direct role of resident microbiota in controlling symbiosis in the skin, we next applied antibiotics to <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice. Oral administration of antibiotics including cephalexin and enrofloxacin for 4 weeks significantly ameliorated the skin inflammation in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice, during which time the disease score of untreated mice worsened (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4A</xref>). To support this amelioration of skin inflammation, we found significantly lower levels of TEWL and IgE Abs in the antibiotic-treated <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice than in the untreated <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4B</xref>). We also observed a decline in <italic>Staphylococcus</italic> species in the skin, indicating that the antibiotics effectively suppressed <italic>S. xylosus</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4B</xref>). The oral administration of antibiotics suppressed the levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines (i.e., IL-1&#x003b2;, TNF-&#x003b1;, IL-6, IL-17A, and IL-22) and chemokines (i.e., MCP-1, MIP-1&#x003b1;, RNATES, and KC) in the skin (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4C</xref>). In this regard, the numbers of infiltrated DCs and T cells were significantly diminished in the skin tissue of antibiotic-treated <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice (Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4D</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1B</xref>).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Antibiotic (ABX) treatment eliminates skin inflammation. (<bold>A</bold>) Representative skin phenotype and histology of skin biopsy from untreated (water alone) and ABX-treated <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice at age 6 weeks. Scale bar&#x02009;=&#x02009;50&#x02009;&#x003bc;m. (<bold>B</bold>) TEWL, serum IgE levels, and colony-forming units (CFU) of <italic>Staphylococcus</italic> species. (<bold>C</bold>) Cytokine and chemokine levels in skin homogenate. (<bold>D</bold>) Confocal microscopy of skin biopsies. Scale bar&#x02009;=&#x02009;50&#x02009;&#x003bc;m. Data are representative of three independent experiments. All data are mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;s.e.m. *<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, **<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_5740_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e1368"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par10">We further explored DC and T-cell subsets associated with skin inflammation induced by resident bacteria. Among the DC subsets, only CD103<sup>+</sup> dDC subsets were significantly reduced by antibiotic treatments (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5A</xref>). The oral administration of antibiotics diminished total recovered numbers of CD4, CD8, and &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T cells and the percentages of those cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5B</xref>). Interestingly, IL-17A-secreting CD4, CD8, and &#x003b3;&#x003b4;T cells were significantly reduced by antibiotic treatments (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5C</xref>). Consistent with the ELISA data shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4C</xref>, antibiotic treatments were not associated with IFN-&#x003b3; secretion by CD4<sup>+</sup> and CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). Collectively, these data suggest that the dominant expansion of <italic>S. xylosus</italic>, which inhabits the skin of mammals as a commensal bacterium, is one factor that contributes to the onset of skin inflammation in the absence of the <italic>Nfkbiz</italic> gene. Moreover, IL-17A and IL-22 are strongly related to the expansion of <italic>S. xylosus</italic>.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Infiltrated IL-17A- and IL-22-secreting T cells are reduced in skin of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice after ABX treatment. Flow cytometry analysis of (<bold>A</bold>) DCs in CD45<sup>+</sup>MHCII<sup>+</sup>CD11c<sup>+</sup> cells and (<bold>B</bold>) T cells in CD45<sup>+</sup> cells isolated from skin of water- and ABX-treated <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice at age 6 weeks. (<bold>C</bold>) IL-17A and IL-22 production by CD45<sup>+</sup> cells in skin. Data are representative of three independent experiments. *<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, **<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_5740_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e1459"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Antibiotic treatment reduced gene expression related to skin inflammation of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic><sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice</title><p id="Par11">To investigate which genes are involved in the regulation of skin inflammation induced by resident bacteria in the absence of the <italic>Nfkbiz</italic> gene, we compared the gene expression profiles in the skin tissues of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> mice, <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice, and antibiotic-treated <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice. The expression levels of 694 and 368 genes were higher and lower (i.e., changed&#x02009;&#x02265;&#x02009;2-fold) in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice than in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3A</xref>) and in antibiotic-treated <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice than in untreated <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6A</xref>), respectively. As expected, the gene expression levels of pro-inflammatory cytokines (i.e., IL-17A, IFN-&#x003b3;, TNF, and IL-18) were higher in the skin of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice than in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> mice. The expression of the S100a9 gene, which is a marker of inflammation, was also significantly increased in the inflamed skin of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3A</xref>). In contrast, the gene expression level of ectodysplasin A (Eda), which contributes to human and murine skin repair<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>, was lower in the skin of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice than in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3A</xref>). Furthermore, IL-17A target genes (i.e., S100a9, S100a8, CAMP, and LCN2) were remarkably upregulated in the skin of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice with dermatitis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3A</xref>). We next created and analyzed a hit gene network predicted by Ingenuity Pathway Analysis (IPA) software. Activation of the NF-kB signal pathway in the skin of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice was as predicted by the IPA software (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3B</xref>). Notably, the depletion of resident microbiota by antibiotic treatment resulted in the reduction of gene expression related to inflammation (i.e., S100a8, S100a9 and Tnfrsf9), but the activation of gene expression was associated with skin repair (i.e., Eda and Eda receptor) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6A</xref>). Th17 cell-associated genes, (i.e., S100a8, CAMP, BATF, IL-23A, LCN2, and HIF-1&#x003b1;) highly expressed in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice with dermatitis, were downregulated after antibiotic treatments (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6A</xref>). By analysis with the IPA software, downregulation of the NF-kB signal pathway was predicted in the skin of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice in the absence of resident microbiota after antibiotic treatment, in comparison with that in untreated <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6B</xref>). Overall, these results support our conclusion that unusual expansion of the resident microbiota may be a key factor in the development of skin inflammation.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>ABX treatment reduces gene expression related to inflammation in skin of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice. (<bold>A</bold>) Microarray analysis of skin from water- and ABX-treated <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;3 per group). Genes with significantly changed expression (fold change&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;1.0 and <italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) after ABX treatment clustered in a heat map. (<bold>B</bold>) A gene interaction network, associated with the amelioration of spontaneous dermatitis in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice, identified by Ingenuity Pathway Analysis software. Solid lines indicate direct interaction; dashed lines indicate indirect interaction.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_5740_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e1650"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Differentiation of Th17 cells in the skin after topical application of <italic>S. xylosus</italic></title><p id="Par12">The amelioration of skin inflammation resulting from the administration of antibiotics prompted us to investigate whether the topical application of <italic>S. xylosus</italic> induces skin inflammation in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice. We pretreated <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> and <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice with antibiotics for 2 weeks to reduce resident commensals and topically applied <italic>S. xylosus</italic> to the back skin for 2 weeks. Topical inoculation resulted in the persistent colonization of <italic>S. xylosus</italic> on the skin of both <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> and <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice after antibiotic treatment (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S4</xref>). The frequency of LCs and dDCs in the skin was not altered by <italic>S. xylosus</italic> inoculation (data not shown). Of interest, the topical application of <italic>S. xylosus</italic> induced the accumulation of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells in the skin and markedly enhanced the production of IL-17A in the skin of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> and <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice (Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7A</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5A</xref>). There were many more IL-17A-secreting CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells in the skin of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice than in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> mice. The numbers of IL-22-secreting CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells were only slightly increased by <italic>S. xylosus</italic> application, which did not reach statistical significance (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7A</xref>). As expected, there was no significant induction of IL-17A-secreting CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells when heat-killed <italic>S. xylosus</italic> was applied topically onto <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> and <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice (Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7A</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5A</xref>). Furthermore, we observed significant increases of pro-inflammatory cytokines (i.e., IL-1&#x003b2;, IFN-&#x003b3;, TNF-&#x003b1;, and IL-17A) and chemokines (i.e., MCP-1, MIP-1&#x003b1;, RANTES, and KC) in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> skin after inoculation of <italic>S. xylosus</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7B</xref>), which also elevated the levels of IL-1&#x003b2;, TNF-&#x003b1;, MCP-1, MIP-1&#x003b1;, and RANTES in the skin of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>+/&#x02212;</sup> mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S5B</xref>). When these findings are considered together, a single commensal bacterial species (i.e., <italic>S. xylosus</italic>) in the skin has the potential to lead to the differentiation of IL-17A-secreting CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells and to elicit various pro-inflammatory cytokines and chemokines, which may be involved in the onset of skin inflammation.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Topical application of <italic>S. xylosus</italic> leads to differentiation of Th17 cells in skin of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice. (<bold>A</bold>) Flow cytometry analysis of IL-17A and IL-22 production in CD4<sup>+</sup> cells from skin of PBS, heat-killed <italic>S. xylosus&#x000a0;(HK-S.x)</italic>, or <italic>S. xylosus(S.x)</italic>-inoculated <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice. (<bold>B</bold>) Cytokine and chemokine levels in skin homogenate. Data are representative of three independent experiments. Data are mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;s.e.m. *<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, **<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_5740_Fig7_HTML" id="d29e1857"/></fig>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par13">In this study, we showed that spontaneous dermatitis developed in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice along with expansion of IL-17A- and IL-22-secreting CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells. Pyrosequencing analysis indicated significantly decreased bacterial diversity and drastically expanded pathobiont <italic>S. xylosus</italic> in the skin of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice. Antibiotic treatment relieved the dermatitis in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice, accompanied by decreased numbers of IL-17A- and IL-22-secreting CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells. The introduction of <italic>S. xylosus</italic> to the skin of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice resulted in the predominant expansion of IL-17A-secreting CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells. These results demonstrate that the expansion of pathobiont <italic>S. xylosus</italic> under <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>-deficient conditions may be a cause of skin dysbiosis and may be mediated by pathogenic IL-17A-secreting CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells.</p><p id="Par14">Previous studies described humans with AD and psoriasis that exhibited general pattern dysbiosis in the skin. These subjects had decreased bacterial diversity and altered predominant bacterial species<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. In this study, we found a similar dysbiotic patterns in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice with spontaneous dermatitis. Specifically, <italic>S. xylosus</italic> accounted for more than 80% of the resident bacteria in the skin of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice. <italic>S. xylosus</italic> is a commensal bacterium that inhabits the skin of mammals and occasionally humans<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>, and its ability to cause opportunistic infections has been reported<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. We found a correlation between the expansion of <italic>S. xylosus</italic> and the severity of inflammation in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice, a finding that is supported by a recent study describing the dominant expansion of <italic>S. aureus</italic> among patients with more severe AD<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. Moreover, the fact that antibiotics specific to <italic>S. xylosus</italic> resulted in the complete suppression of dermatitis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup> supports the notion that the dysbiosis provoked by the predominance of <italic>S. xylosus</italic> is closely related to skin inflammation.</p><p id="Par15">AD has been considered an allergic Th2-mediated disease due to the high levels of IgE Ab<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>; however, others suggest that AD is more heterogeneous, given the contributions of other T cells such as Th17 and Th22<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>. Among several subsets of AD, intrinsic AD and Asian AD patients preferentially exhibit the activation of Th17 and Th22 cytokines<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. These patients show features typical of persons with psoriasis, such as parakeratosis and epidermal hyperplasia<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. Although the numbers of Th17 and Th22 cells were found to be increased systemically and in the skin of AD patients, the roles of IL-17A and IL-22 in the pathogenesis of this disease remain unclear. In this context, another recent study addressed the possibility that IL-17A acts as an inducer for Th2-type immune responses in murine AD models<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. On the other hand, IL-22 is known to promote keratinocyte proliferation. IL-23 produced by keratinocytes in response to endogenous TLR4 ligands polarized skin DCs to stimulate the IL-22 response<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. In our study, we found that IL-17A and IL-22, more than any other cytokines, were significantly reduced in response to the administration of antibiotics (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5C</xref>) and that <italic>S. xylosus</italic> inoculation onto <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice led to elevated IL-17A and IL-22 cytokines in skin homogenates (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7A</xref>). In this context, others demonstrated that the onset of skin inflammation in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> is independent of the Th2 response by showing that dermatitis still developed in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup>Stat6<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup>. We further observed that IFN-&#x003b3; remained elevated even after antibiotic treatment and improvement of skin inflammation (Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4C</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>). These lines of evidence suggest that Th17 and Th22 cells rather than Th1 cells may be directly involved in the development of skin inflammation in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice.</p><p id="Par16">Our results indicate that the topical association of <italic>S. xylosus</italic> elevates chemokine secretion in the skin (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7B</xref>). Others showed that MCP-1 and MIP-1&#x003b1; participate in both immediate and delayed skin reactions and trigger the recruitment of local T cells, macrophages, and granulocytes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. Transgenic mice overexpressing MCP-1 in the epidermis also exhibit a dramatic increase of MHCII<sup>+</sup> cells in the dermis and show augmentation of the contact hypersensitivity reaction<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>. We speculate that the expansion of <italic>S. xylosus</italic> first stimulates chemokine secretion by keratinocytes and/or fibroblasts, which may be involved in the recruitment of innate immune cells in the skin that are indispensable in the onset of skin inflammation. In support of this possibility, the inoculation of <italic>S. xylosus</italic> also increased migratory DCs (CD11c<sup>+</sup> MHCII<sup>hi</sup>) in skin-draining lymph nodes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S6</xref>). Other studies indicate that MCP-1 is also responsible for the recruitment of Th17 cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>, while IL-17A stimulates fibroblasts to produce MCP-1 and RANTES<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>. Overall, these results imply that the expansion of a single pathobiont such as <italic>S. xylosus</italic> provokes inflammation in local mucosal tissues through the induction of chemokines and Th17 and Th22 responses.</p><p id="Par17">In <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice with severe dermatitis, we found a marked increase in CD103<sup>+</sup> dDCs, which are rare in normal skin (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2A</xref>). This subset was significantly reduced after antibiotic treatment (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5A</xref>). However, topical inoculation of <italic>S. xylosus</italic> was unable to drive the recruitment of CD103<sup>+</sup> dDCs in the skin (data not shown). Others found that CD103<sup>+</sup> DCs in non-lymphoid tissues are functionally specialized in the cross-presentation of antigens to CD8<sup>+</sup> cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>. CD207<sup>+</sup> dDCs, often referred to as CD103<sup>+</sup> DCs in the skin, induce CD8<sup>+</sup> T-cell and Th1-cell responses<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>. However, there have been no reports of CD103<sup>+</sup> dDCs in skin of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice with dermatitis, though its presence in steady-state skin-draining lymph nodes is known<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>. Further studies on CD103<sup>+</sup> dDC function are needed to assess their role in Th17 differentiation during <italic>S. xylosus</italic> infection.</p><p id="Par18">I&#x003ba;B&#x003b6;, encoded by the <italic>Nfkbiz</italic> gene, is a transcription factor known to promote IL-17A production. For instance, I&#x003ba;B&#x003b6;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice show resistance to diseases with enhanced Th17 responses, including experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis (EAE) and psoriasis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>. However, in this study, we observed robust Th17 responses as well as expression of IL-17A signature genes (i.e., S100a8, S100a9, CAMP, and LCN2) in the skin of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice with spontaneous dermatitis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). We assume that, unlike ROR&#x003b3;t, I&#x003ba;B&#x003b6; is not a master regulator for Th17 cells. It could thus function as a Th17 cell-specific transcription factor in cooperation with ROR nuclear factors. The overexpression of ROR nuclear factors drove IL-17A production in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> T cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. In our study, we detected the upregulation of other transcription factors that contribute to Th17 differentiation, such as BATF, which remodels chromatin to enable the access of transcription factors to Th17-specific loci<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>; Hif-1&#x003b1;, which can directly increase ROR&#x003b3;t expression and drive IL-17A expression with ROR&#x003b3;t<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>; and IL-23A, which is essential for the induction of pathogenic Th17 cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup> in the skin of <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice with dermatitis (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). These results provide support for a molecular mechanism of an enhanced Th17 response in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice.</p><p id="Par19">In conclusion, our findings demonstrate that <italic>S. xylosus</italic> is an important pathobiont that accelerates dermatitis in <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>-deficient mice. We also found that a single commensal bacterium can modulate innate and acquired immune responses in the skin. Although the commensal microbiota maintains a symbiotic relationship with the host immune system and plays a beneficial role in the host under steady-state conditions, it can provoke and trigger inflammation under <italic>Nfkbiz</italic>-deficient conditions. These results suggest that the <italic>Nfkbiz</italic> gene has a potential regulatory role in the microbiota-skin immunity axis.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec11"><title>Ethics statement</title><p id="Par20">All animal experiments were approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of Asan Biomedical Research Center (Approval No. PN 2014-12-063) and the studies were carried out in accordance with the approved guidelines and regulations. All experiments were performed under anesthesia with a mixture of ketamine (100&#x02009;mg/kg) and xylazine (20&#x02009;mg/kg), and all efforts were made to minimize suffering.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Mice</title><p id="Par21">
<italic>Nfkbiz</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice were provided by Prof. Shizuo Akira (IFReC, Osaka University, Japan). All mice were maintained under specific pathogen-free conditions in the animal facility at Asan Biomedical Research Center (Seoul, Korea), where they received sterilized food and water <italic>ad libitum</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Clinical score</title><p id="Par22">Pathological phenotypes of mice were scored according to the criteria as described previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>, with slight modification: (1) swelling of the eyelid; (2) periocular skin erosion and eyes with discharge that were difficult to open; (3) inflammation reaching the skin of the ear and part of the skin on the body; (4) erosion and loss of hair in the whole body; and (5) severe erosion and loss of hair in the whole face and body.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Preparation of mononuclear cells from skin</title><p id="Par23">Mouse trunk skin was shaved, peeled off, and placed epidermal side down in a Petri dish. Subcutaneous fat tissue and blood vessels were scrapped off with a Scalpel (Feather, Osaka, Japan). Skin tissue was then incubated with 0.25% trypsin (Gibco, Waltham, MA) at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 2&#x02009;h. Epidermal cells were separated from the dermis by mechanical separation and vigorously agitated in RPMI 1640 (Gibco) containing 10% FBS (Gibco) at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 10&#x02009;min. The dermis was then minced with scissors and further treated with 2.5&#x02009;mg/ml collagenase IV (Sigma Aldrich, St. Louis, MO) and 0.2&#x02009;mg/ml DNase (Roche) at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C with stirring. After 1&#x02009;h, digestion was stopped by the addition of 10&#x02009;mM EDTA. Epidermal and dermal cell suspensions were filtered and enriched for immune cells using a 40&#x02013;75% Percoll density gradient (GE Healthcare, Buckinghamshire, UK).</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Flow cytometry analysis and antibodies</title><p id="Par24">For cytokine analysis, cell suspensions were cultured in RPMI 1640 medium supplemented with 10% FBS and 1% penicillin and streptomycin (Gibco) with 50 ng/ml PMA (Sigma Aldrich) and 1&#x02009;&#x003bc;g/ml ionomycin (Sigma Aldrich) in the presence of Brefeldin A (BD Biosciences, Franklin Lakes, NJ) overnight at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. Cells were stained with Live/Dead Cell Stain kit (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA) and surface markers after treatment with purified anti-mouse CD16/32 Ab (BD Biosciences). Fixation and permeabilization were performed with BD Cytofix/Cytoperm (BD Biosciences), followed by intracellular cytokine staining. The following Abs from BD Biosciences, eBioscience (Santa Clara, CA), or BioLegend (San Diego, CA) were used for analysis: anti-CD45 (30-F11), anti-CD4 (RM4&#x02013;5), anti-CD8&#x003b1; (53&#x02013;6.7), anti-TCR&#x003b3;&#x003b4; (GL3), anti-IFN-&#x003b3; (XMG1.2), anti-IL-4 (11B11), anti-IL-17A (TC11-18H10), anti-IL-22 (IL-22JOP), anti-MHC II (M5/114.15.2), anti-CD207 (4C7), anti-CD11b (M1/70), anti-CD11c (HL3), and anti-CD103 (2E7). Cell acquisition was performed on a BD Biosciences FACSCanto II flow cytometer and data were analyzed using FlowJo software (Tree Star, Ashland, OR).</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>16s rRNA gene pyrosequencing analysis</title><p id="Par25">Genomic DNA was extracted from skin tissue using the NucleoSpin Soil kit (Macherey-Nagel, D&#x000fc;ren, Germany). PCR amplification was performed using primers targeting the segment from the V1 to V3 regions of the 16S rRNA gene with extracted gDNA. For bacterial amplifications, we used barcoded primers of 9&#x02009;F (5&#x02032;-CCTATCCCCTGTGTGCCTTGGCAGTC-TCAG-AC-AGAGTTTGATCMTGGCTCAG-3&#x02032;; the underlined sequence indicates the target region primer) and 541&#x02009;R (5&#x02032;-CCATCTCATCCCTGCGTGTCTCCGAC-TCAG-X-AC-ATTACCGCGGCTGCTGG-3&#x02032;; X indicates the unique barcode for each subject). The amplifications were performed under the following conditions: initial denaturation at 95&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 5&#x02009;min, followed by 30 cycles of denaturation at 95&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x02009;sec, primer annealing at 55&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x02009;sec, and extension at 72&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x02009;sec, with final elongation at 72&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 5&#x02009;min. The amplified products were purified with the QIAquick PCR purification kit (Qiagen, Valencia, CA). Equal concentrations of purified products were pooled together and short fragments (non-target products) were removed with an AMPure bead kit (Agencourt Bioscience, Beverly, MA). The quality and product size were assessed on a Bioanalyzer 2100 (Agilent, Palo Alto, CA) using a DNA 7500 chip. Mixed amplicon sequencing was performed by emulsion PCR and then deposited on picotiter plates. The sequencing was carried out at Chunlab (Seoul, Republic of Korea) on a GS Junior Sequencing System (Roche, Branford, CT), in accordance with the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Microarray analysis</title><p id="Par26">RNA from skin tissues was isolated with TRIzol (Invitrogen) reagent. RNA labeling and hybridization were performed by using the Agilent one-color microarray-based gene expression analysis kit (Agilent Technology, Santa Clara, CA). In brief, total RNA (200&#x02009;ng) from each sample was linearly amplified and labeled with Cy3-dCTP. The labeled cRNAs were purified by RNAeasy mini kit (Qiagen). Each labeled cRNA (600&#x02009;ng) was fragmented by adding blocking agent and fragmentation buffer, and then heated at 60&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 30&#x02009;min. Finally GE hybridization buffer was added to dilute the labeled cRNA. Hybridization solution was dispensed into the gasket slide and assembled with the Agilent SurePrint G3 Mouse GE 8X60&#x02009;K kit. The slides were incubated for 17&#x02009;h at 65&#x02009;&#x000b0;C in an Agilent hybridization oven and then washed. The hybridized array was immediately scanned with an Agilent Microarray Scanner D.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>IPA (Ingenuity Pathway Analysis)</title><p id="Par27">IPA (Ingenuity Systems, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ingenuity.com">http://www.ingenuity.com</ext-link>) was used for gene network analysis, which was carried out to identify the most significant gene sets associated with disease process and molecular and cellular functions in significantly altered genes (described in the Figs&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). The significance of over-represented gene sets was estimated by the right-tailed Fisher&#x02019;s exact test. Gene network analysis was carried out by using a global molecular network developed from information contained in the Ingenuity Knowledge Base. Identified gene networks were ranked according to scores provided by IPA.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Antibiotic treatment</title><p id="Par28">Mice were treated with 0.5&#x02009;mg/ml cephalexin and enrofloxacin (Sigma Aldrich) in drinking water.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Bacterial isolation and inoculation onto mice</title><p id="Par29">To isolate <italic>S. xylosus</italic> from skin, swabs from the shaved back skin of mice (1&#x02009;cm<sup>2</sup> or the infection area) were placed in PBS and cultured on MSA (BD Biosciences). The colonies from the plates were sequenced by Macrogen (Seoul, Republic of Korea). <italic>S. xylosus</italic> was cultured in mannitol salt broth (BD Biosciences) at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C overnight in a shaking incubator. Bacteria were enumerated by assessing the colony-forming units (CFUs) using a standard plate count method and by measuring optical density at 600&#x02009;nm. For the topical inoculation of bacteria, a bacterial suspension (10<sup>9</sup> CFUs) in PBS was topically applied to the shaved back skin of mice using a sterile cotton swab. Bacteria were applied every other day.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Histological analysis and immunofluorescence microscopy</title><p id="Par30">After sacrifice, mouse back skin was fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde, embedded in paraffin, and stained with hematoxylin-eosin. Microscopic images were obtained (BX53; Olympus Optical, Tokyo, Japan). For immunofluorescence microscopy, skin tissues were frozen, embedded in OCT compound, sectioned, and fixed with &#x02212;20&#x02009;&#x000b0;C acetone for 5&#x02009;min. Slides were blocked with PBS containing 1% BSA for 1&#x02009;h at room temperature and stained with anti-CD8&#x003b1; (53&#x02013;6.7), anti-CD4 (RM4-5), anti-CD11b (M1/70), anti-CD207 (4C7), and anti-CD11c (HL3) Abs (BD Biosciences) overnight at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. Tissues were washed and stained with 4&#x02032;,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI; BD Pharmingen) for 2&#x02009;min at room temperature, followed by mounting with PermaFluor mountant (Thermo, Waltham, MA). Images were captured on an LSM 710 confocal microscope (Carl Zeiss, Oberkochen, Germany).</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>IgE and cytokine analysis</title><p id="Par31">Serum total IgE Ab level was determined using mouse IgE ELISA kit (BD Biosciences). Supernatant was collected after skin tissues were weighed and homogenized with Tris-EDTA buffer (10&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl and 1&#x02009;mM EDTA, pH 7.4, 0.05% sodium azide, 1% Tween-80, protease inhibitor cocktail) and centrifuged at 11,000&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;g for 10&#x02009;min at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C. Cytokines and chemokines from tissue homogenates were measured by a ProcartaPlex Multiplex immunoassay kit (eBioscience), in accordance with the manufacturer&#x02019;s instructions.</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Trans-epidermal water loss</title><p id="Par32">TEWL was measured by VapoMeter SWL4001JT (Delfin, Kuopio, Finland).</p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Statistics</title><p id="Par33">GraphPad Prism software (GraphPad, La Jolla, CA) was used for statistical analysis. Significant differences between two groups were analyzed with two-tailed unpaired <italic>t</italic>-test. Multiple groups were analyzed by two-way ANOVA followed by Bonferroni&#x02019;s <italic>post hoc</italic> test (*<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05; **<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec25"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2017_5740_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplemental Information&#x000a0;</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Electronic supplementary material</bold></p><p>
<bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at doi:10.1038/s41598-017-05740-z
</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Publisher's note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Prof. Jin-Woo Bae and Dr. Min-Soo Kim for their advice and evaluation of the metagenomic analysis. This work was supported by the National Research Foundation of Korea (NRF-2017R1A2B3002132) and the Korean Healthcare Technology R&#x00026;D Project, Ministry for Health, Welfare and Family Affairs of Korea (HI13C0016).</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>Y.K. performed all experiments and data analysis and wrote the manuscript; Y.L. and J.Y. helped to design experiments, analyze data, and review the manuscript; S.L. helped in data collection and analysis; Y.P. assisted in data analysis, interpretation and manuscript review; M.K. contributed to the conception and design of the study and supervised the study.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing Interests</title><p id="Par34">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belkaid</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Segre</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dialogue between skin microbiota and immunity</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2014</year><volume>346</volume><fpage>954</fpage><lpage>959</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1260144</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25414304?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25414304</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Temporal shifts in the skin microbiome associated with disease flares and treatment in children with atopic dermatitis</article-title><source>Genome Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>850</fpage><lpage>859</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/gr.131029.111</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22310478?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22310478</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marcus</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Demmler</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudolph</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bacterial colonization of psoriasis plaques. Is it relevant?</article-title><source>Dermatol Reports</source><year>2011</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>e14</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4081/dr.2011.e14</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25386266?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25386266</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Freeman, A. F. &#x00026; Holland, S. M. The hyper-IgE syndromes. <italic>Immunol Allergy Clin North Am</italic><bold>28</bold>, 277&#x02013;291 viii (2008).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kobayashi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Dysbiosis and <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> colonization drives inflammation in atopic dermatitis</article-title><source>Immunity</source><year>2015</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>756</fpage><lpage>766</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2015.03.014</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25902485?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25902485</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dordet-Frisoni</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genomic diversity in <italic>Staphylococcus xylosus</italic></article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2007</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>7199</fpage><lpage>7209</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.01629-07</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17890333?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17890333</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giordano</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Erythema nodosum associated with <italic>Staphylococcus xylosus</italic> septicemia</article-title><source>J Microbiol Immunol Infect</source><year>2016</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>134</fpage><lpage>137</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmii.2012.10.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23266237?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23266237</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tselenis-Kotsowilis</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Koliomichalis</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Papavassiliou</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Acute pyelonephritis caused by <italic>Staphylococcus xylosus</italic></article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>1982</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>593</fpage><lpage>594</lpage><?supplied-pmid 7130375?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7130375</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Makki</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Phenotypic and genotypic characterization of coagulase negative staphylococci (CoNS) other than <italic>Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic> isolated from ocular infections</article-title><source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source><year>2011</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>9018</fpage><lpage>9022</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1167/iovs.11-7777</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22025577?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22025577</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Won</surname><given-names>YS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Identification of Staphylococcus xylosus isolated from C57BL/6J-Nos2(tm1Lau) mice with dermatitis</article-title><source>Microbiol Immunol</source><year>2002</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>629</fpage><lpage>632</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1348-0421.2002.tb02744.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12437030?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12437030</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Russo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Invernizzi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gobbi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Radaelli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diffuse scaling dermatitis in an athymic nude mouse</article-title><source>Vet Pathol</source><year>2013</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>722</fpage><lpage>726</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0300985812463408</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23064880?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23064880</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gozalo</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Spontaneous Staphylococcus xylosus infection in mice deficient in NADPH oxidase and comparison with other laboratory mouse strains</article-title><source>J Am Assoc Lab Anim Sci</source><year>2010</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>480</fpage><lpage>486</lpage><?supplied-pmid 20819397?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20819397</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belkaid</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tamoutounour</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The influence of skin microorganisms on cutaneous immunity</article-title><source>Nat Rev Immunol</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>353</fpage><lpage>366</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nri.2016.48</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27231051?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27231051</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Compartmentalized control of skin immunity by resident commensals</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2012</year><volume>337</volume><fpage>1115</fpage><lpage>1119</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1225152</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22837383?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22837383</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naik</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Commensal-dendritic-cell interaction specifies a unique protective skin immune signature</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2015</year><volume>520</volume><fpage>104</fpage><lpage>108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature14052</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25539086?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25539086</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eyerich</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>IL-17 in atopic eczema: linking allergen-specific adaptive and microbial-triggered innate immune response</article-title><source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source><year>2009</year><volume>123</volume><fpage>59</fpage><lpage>66 e54</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaci.2008.10.031</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19056110?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19056110</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Niebuhr</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Staphylococcal alpha-toxin is a strong inducer of interleukin-17 in humans</article-title><source>Infect Immun</source><year>2011</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>1615</fpage><lpage>1622</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.00958-10</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21245272?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21245272</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reginald</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Immunoglobulin E antibody reactivity to bacterial antigens in atopic dermatitis patients</article-title><source>Clin Exp Allergy</source><year>2011</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>357</fpage><lpage>369</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2222.2010.03655.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21155910?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21155910</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>I&#x003ba;B&#x003b6; regulates Th17 development by cooperating with ROR nuclear receptors</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2010</year><volume>464</volume><fpage>1381</fpage><lpage>1385</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature08922</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20383124?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20383124</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karlsen</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Borregaard</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Cowland</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induction of neutrophil gelatinase-associated lipocalin expression by co-stimulation with interleukin-17 and tumor necrosis factor-a is controlled by I&#x003ba;B&#x003b6; but neither by C/EBP-b nor C/EBP-d</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2010</year><volume>285</volume><fpage>14088</fpage><lpage>14100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M109.017129</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20220144?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20220144</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>MaruYama</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Control of IFN-g production and regulatory function by the inducible nuclear protein I&#x003ba;B&#x003b6; in T cells</article-title><source>J Leukoc Biol</source><year>2015</year><volume>98</volume><fpage>385</fpage><lpage>393</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1189/jlb.2A0814-384R</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26019294?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26019294</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamazaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gene-specific requirement of a nuclear protein, I&#x003ba;B&#x003b6;, for promoter association of inflammatory transcription regulators</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2008</year><volume>283</volume><fpage>32404</fpage><lpage>32411</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M802148200</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18824552?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18824552</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Regulation of Toll/IL-1-receptor-mediated gene expression by the inducible nuclear protein I&#x003ba;B&#x003b6;</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2004</year><volume>430</volume><fpage>218</fpage><lpage>222</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature02738</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15241416?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15241416</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okuma</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Enhanced apoptosis by disruption of the STAT3- I&#x003ba;B&#x003b6; signaling pathway in epithelial cells induces Sjogren&#x02019;s syndrome-like autoimmune disease</article-title><source>Immunity</source><year>2013</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>450</fpage><lpage>460</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2012.11.016</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23453632?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23453632</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Motoyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Positive and negative regulation of NF-kB-mediated transcription by I&#x003ba;B&#x003b6;, an inducible nuclear protein</article-title><source>J Biol Chem</source><year>2005</year><volume>280</volume><fpage>7444</fpage><lpage>7451</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M412738200</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15618216?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15618216</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ueta</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Stat6-independent tissue inflammation occurs selectively on the ocular surface and perioral skin of I&#x003ba;B&#x003b6;<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> mice</article-title><source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source><year>2008</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>3387</fpage><lpage>3394</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1167/iovs.08-1691</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18441309?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18441309</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Paparo</surname><given-names>SB</given-names></name><name><surname>Guaragna</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Albanesi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>High IgE levels in patients affected by psoriasis: review of the literature and personal observations</article-title><source>Clin Ter</source><year>2014</year><volume>165</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><?supplied-pmid 24770810?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24770810</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laske</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Niggemann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Does the severity of atopic dermatitis correlate with serum IgE levels?</article-title><source>Pediatr Allergy Immunol</source><year>2004</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>86</fpage><lpage>88</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.0905-6157.2003.00106.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14998387?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14998387</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Disentangling the complexity of the skin dendritic cell network</article-title><source>Immunol Cell Biol</source><year>2010</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>366</fpage><lpage>375</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/icb.2010.34</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20231850?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20231850</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shittu</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolawole</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and molecular characterization of mannitol salt positive, coagulase-negative <italic>staphylococci</italic> from nasal samples of medical personnel and students</article-title><source>J Med Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>55</volume><fpage>317</fpage><lpage>324</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/jmm.0.46072-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16476796?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16476796</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garcin</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ectodysplasin A pathway contributes to human and murine skin repair</article-title><source>J Invest Dermatol</source><year>2016</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>1022</fpage><lpage>1030</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jid.2015.09.002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26829034?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26829034</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alekseyenko</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Community differentiation of the cutaneous microbiota in psoriasis</article-title><source>Microbiome</source><year>2013</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>31</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2049-2618-1-31</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24451201?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24451201</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nagase</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Isolation and species distribution of <italic>Staphylococci</italic> from animal and human skin</article-title><source>J Vet Med Sci</source><year>2002</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1292/jvms.64.245</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11999444?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11999444</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Totte</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Prevalence and odds of <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> carriage in atopic dermatitis: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>Br J Dermatol</source><year>2016</year><volume>175</volume><fpage>687</fpage><lpage>695</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/bjd.14566</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26994362?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26994362</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bochniarz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wawron</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Szczubial</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Production of slime by coagulase-negative staphylococci (CNS) isolated from clinical and subclinical mastitis in cows</article-title><source>Pol J Vet Sci</source><year>2014</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>447</fpage><lpage>452</lpage><?supplied-pmid 25286652?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25286652</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zamankhan Malayeri</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jamshidi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Zahraei Salehi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification and antimicrobial susceptibility patterns of bacteria causing otitis externa in dogs</article-title><source>Vet Res Commun</source><year>2010</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>435</fpage><lpage>444</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11259-010-9417-y</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20526674?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20526674</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Brandt, E. B. &#x00026; Sivaprasad, U. Th2 cytokines and atopic dermatitis. <italic>J Clin Cell Immunol</italic><bold>2</bold> (2011).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gittler</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Progressive activation of Th2/Th22 cytokines and selective epidermal proteins characterizes acute and chronic atopic dermatitis</article-title><source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source><year>2012</year><volume>130</volume><fpage>1344</fpage><lpage>1354</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaci.2012.07.012</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22951056?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22951056</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koga</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Possible pathogenic role of Th17 cells for atopic dermatitis</article-title><source>J Invest Dermatol</source><year>2008</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>2625</fpage><lpage>2630</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/jid.2008.111</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18432274?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18432274</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suarez-Farinas</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Intrinsic atopic dermatitis shows similar Th2 and higher Th17 immune activation compared with extrinsic atopic dermatitis</article-title><source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source><year>2013</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>361</fpage><lpage>370</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaci.2013.04.046</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23777851?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23777851</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Asian atopic dermatitis phenotype combines features of atopic dermatitis and psoriasis with increased Th17 polarization</article-title><source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source><year>2015</year><volume>136</volume><fpage>1254</fpage><lpage>1264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaci.2015.08.015</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26428954?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26428954</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakajima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>IL-17A as an inducer for Th2 immune responses in murine atopic dermatitis models</article-title><source>J Invest Dermatol</source><year>2014</year><volume>134</volume><fpage>2122</fpage><lpage>2130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/jid.2014.51</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24480880?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24480880</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yoon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>IL-23 induced in keratinocytes by endogenous TLR4 ligands polarizes dendritic cells to drive IL-22 responses to skin immunization</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><year>2016</year><volume>213</volume><fpage>2147</fpage><lpage>2166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20150376</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27551155?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27551155</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gaga</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Skin reactivity and local cell recruitment in human atopic and nonatopic subjects by CCL2/MCP-1 and CCL3/MIP-1a</article-title><source>Allergy</source><year>2008</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>703</fpage><lpage>711</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1398-9995.2007.01578.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18070228?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18070228</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>IR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kupper</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Keratinocyte-derived monocyte chemoattractant protein 1 (MCP-1): analysis in a transgenic model demonstrates MCP-1 can recruit dendritic and Langerhans cells to skin</article-title><source>J Invest Dermatol</source><year>1995</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>635</fpage><lpage>643</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1523-1747.ep12324061</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7594634?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7594634</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pelletier</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evidence for a cross-talk between human neutrophils and Th17 cells</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2010</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>335</fpage><lpage>343</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2009-04-216085</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19890092?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19890092</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brembilla</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Th17 cells favor inflammatory responses while inhibiting type I collagen deposition by dermal fibroblasts: differential effects in healthy and systemic sclerosis fibroblasts</article-title><source>Arthritis Res Ther</source><year>2013</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>R151</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/ar4334</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24289089?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24289089</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>IL-17A promotes RANTES expression, but not IL-16, in orbital fibroblasts via CD40-CD40L combination in thyroid-associated ophthalmopathy</article-title><source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source><year>2016</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>6123</fpage><lpage>6133</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1167/iovs.16-20199</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27832278?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27832278</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ginhoux</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The origin and development of nonlymphoid tissue CD103<sup>+</sup> DCs</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><year>2009</year><volume>206</volume><fpage>3115</fpage><lpage>3130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20091756</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20008528?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20008528</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Igyarto</surname><given-names>BZ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Skin-resident murine dendritic cell subsets promote distinct and opposing antigen-specific T helper cell responses</article-title><source>Immunity</source><year>2011</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>260</fpage><lpage>272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2011.06.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21782478?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21782478</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henri</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CD207<sup>+</sup>CD103<sup>+</sup> dermal dendritic cells cross-present keratinocyte-derived antigens irrespective of the presence of Langerhans cells</article-title><source>J Exp Med</source><year>2010</year><volume>207</volume><fpage>189</fpage><lpage>206</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20091964</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20038600?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20038600</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johansen</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>I&#x003ba;B&#x003b6; is a key driver in the development of psoriasis</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>2015</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>E5825</fpage><lpage>5833</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1509971112</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26460049?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26460049</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ciofani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A validated regulatory network for Th17 cell specification</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2012</year><volume>151</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>303</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2012.09.016</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23021777?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23021777</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dang</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Control of Th17/Treg balance by hypoxia-inducible factor 1</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2011</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>772</fpage><lpage>784</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2011.07.033</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21871655?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21871655</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Induction and molecular signature of pathogenic Th17 cells</article-title><source>Nat Immunol</source><year>2012</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>991</fpage><lpage>999</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni.2416</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22961052?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22961052</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>