<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Nat Commun</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Nat Commun</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Nature Communications</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2041-1723</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5615048</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">768</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-017-00768-1</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Priming of lineage-specifying genes by Bcl11b is required for lineage choice in post-selection thymocytes</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kojo</surname><given-names>Satoshi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>Hirokazu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2801-2463</contrib-id><name><surname>Endo</surname><given-names>Takaho A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Muroi</surname><given-names>Sawako</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Ye</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>Wooseok</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Tenno</surname><given-names>Mari</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kakugawa</surname><given-names>Kiyokazu</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Naoe</surname><given-names>Yoshinori</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nair</surname><given-names>Krutula</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Moro</surname><given-names>Kazuyo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Katsuragi</surname><given-names>Yoshinori</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kanai</surname><given-names>Akinori</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Inaba</surname><given-names>Toshiya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Egawa</surname><given-names>Takeshi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Venkatesh</surname><given-names>Byrappa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff8">8</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Minoda</surname><given-names>Aki</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kominami</surname><given-names>Ryo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Taniuchi</surname><given-names>Ichiro</given-names></name><address><email>ichiro.taniuchi@riken.jp</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Laboratory for Transcriptional Regulation, RIKEN Center for Integrative Medical Sciences (IMS), 1-7-22 Suehiro-cho, Tsurumi-ku, Yokohama 230-0045 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Laboratory for Integrative Genomics, RIKEN Center for Integrative Medical Sciences (IMS), 1-7-22 Suehiro-cho, Tsurumi-ku, Yokohama 230-0045 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Division of Genomic Technologies, RIKEN Center for Life Science Technologies (CLST), 1-7-22 Suehiro-cho, Tsurumi-ku, Yokohama 230-0045 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Laboratory for Innate Immune Systems, RIKEN Center for Integrative Medical Sciences (IMS), 1-7-22 Suehiro-cho, Tsurumi-ku, Yokohama 230-0045 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0671 5144</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.260975.f</institution-id><institution>Division of Molecular Biology, Department of Molecular Genetics, Graduate School of Medical and Dental Sciences, </institution><institution>Niigata University, </institution></institution-wrap>Niigata, 951-8510 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 8711 3200</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.257022.0</institution-id><institution>Department of Molecular Oncology, Research Institute for Radiation Biology and Medicine, </institution><institution>Hiroshima University, </institution></institution-wrap>1-2-3, Kasumi, Minami-ku, Hiroshima 734-8553 Japan </aff><aff id="Aff7"><label>7</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2355 7002</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.4367.6</institution-id><institution>Department of Pathology and Immunology, School of Medicine, </institution><institution>Washington University School of Medicine, </institution></institution-wrap>660 S Euclid, Saint Louis, 63110 MO USA </aff><aff id="Aff8"><label>8</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0637 0221</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.185448.4</institution-id><institution>Institute of Molecular and Cell Biology, Agency for Science, </institution><institution>Technology and Research, </institution></institution-wrap>Biopolis, 138673 Singapore </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>9</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>26</day><month>9</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><elocation-id>702</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>1</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>27</day><month>7</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2017</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">T-lineage committed precursor thymocytes are screened by a fate-determination process mediated via T cell receptor (TCR) signals for differentiation into distinct lineages. However, it remains unclear whether any antecedent event is required to couple TCR signals with the transcriptional program governing lineage decisions. Here we show that Bcl11b, known as a T-lineage commitment factor, is essential for proper expression of ThPOK and Runx3, central regulators for the CD4-helper/CD8-cytotoxic lineage choice. Loss of Bcl11b results in random expression of these factors and, thereby, lineage scrambling that is disconnected from TCR restriction by MHC. Initial <italic>Thpok</italic> repression by Bcl11b prior to the pre-selection stage is independent of a known silencer for <italic>Thpok</italic>, and requires the last zinc-finger motif in Bcl11b protein, which by contrast is dispensable for T-lineage commitment. Collectively, our findings shed new light on the function of Bcl11b in priming lineage-specifying genes to integrate TCR signals into subsequent transcriptional regulatory mechanisms.</p></abstract><abstract id="Abs2" abstract-type="web-summary"><p id="Par2">CD4 and CD8 T cells develop in the thymus with their transcription programs controlled by ThPOK and Runx3, respectively. Here the authors show that a pre-commitment event modulated by the transcription factor, Bcl11b, is required for the proper expression of ThPOK and Runx3 and correct CD4/CD8 lineage commitment.</p></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2017</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par3">Early thymocyte progenitors (ETPs) retain their developmental potential to become non-T- lymphoid cells, but, upon exposure to the thymic microenvironment, the ETP expression program is dramatically altered to commit them to the T-lymphoid lineage<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. Previous studies demonstrated that a final T-lymphoid lineage commitment occurs at a developmental checkpoint during the transition from the CD4<sup>&#x02212;</sup>CD8<sup>&#x02212;</sup> double negative (DN)2a to the DN2b stage, where expression of the transcription factor Bcl11b is induced<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. Bcl11b-deficiency results in a developmental arrest of early T cell progenitors at the DN2a stage along with a concomitant acquisition of myeloid-lineage/natural killer (NK) cell gene signatures<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. Bcl11b thus serves as a T-lineage commitment factor that eliminates developmental potential to non-T lymphoid cells at the DN2 checkpoint<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. Beside its function during early thymocyte development, Bcl11b continues to be expressed during T lymphocyte differentiation<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup> and modulates the development of many lymphoid subsets, including natural killer T (NKT)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>, regulatory T (Treg)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup> and type2 innate lymphoid (ILC2) cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">After commitment to the T-lineage, another checkpoint, known as &#x003b2;-selection, selectively expands DN3 cells that successfully express functional TCR&#x003b2; chain after V(D)J recombination of the <italic>Tcrb</italic> locus. Thymocytes that have passed &#x003b2;-selection become &#x003b1;&#x003b2;T-lineage-restricted CD4<sup>+</sup>CD8<sup>+</sup> double positive (DP) precursor thymocytes, which express complete &#x003b1;&#x003b2;TCR complexes for the first time during T cell development. DP precursors are then subjected to additional positive and negative selections that enrich precursors with TCRs recognizing antigen-MHC complexes with intermediate affinity but eliminate precursors expressing self-reactive TCRs, respectively<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. Positively selected thymocytes differentiate into distinct T cell subsets with distinct functionalities via the activation of specific developmental programs. For instance, positive selection signaled via TCR engagement by MHC class-II (MHC-II) and class-I (MHC-I) guides precursors to differentiate into CD4<sup>+</sup>CD8<sup>&#x02212;</sup> helper or CD4<sup>&#x02212;</sup>CD8<sup>+</sup> cytotoxic T cells through the induction of key transcription factors, ThPOK and Runx3, respectively<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. Thus, DP precursors must be ready to integrate TCR signals, translating them into the appropriate developmental program. However, an important gap in our understanding of these processes is how TCR signals are coupled to mechanisms that control the expression of lineage-specifying genes, and it remains unclear whether preceding events are required for this coupling.</p><p id="Par5">One such lineage-specifying transcription factor, Zbtb7b, also known as T-helper-inducing POZ/Krueppel<sup>&#x02212;</sup> like factor (ThPOK), is a member of the BTB-POZ zinc-finger transcription factor family<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup> and is encoded by <italic>Zbtb7b</italic>, hereafter referred to as the <italic>Thpok</italic> gene. Previous genetic studies for &#x02018;gain and loss&#x02019; of ThPOK function demonstrated that its presence or absence in post-selection thymocytes is a major determinant of the CD4-helper (ThPOK<sup>+</sup>) versus CD8-cytotoxic (ThPOK<sup>&#x02013;</sup>) lineage dichotomy<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. Consistent with these findings, expression of the <italic>Thpok</italic> gene is restricted to MHC-II selected thymocytes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup> in positively selected thymocytes. Accordingly, <italic>Thpok</italic> regulation has been recognized as an ideal model to study how TCR signals are coupled with the transcriptional program that establishes the identity of CD4<sup>+</sup> helper T cells. Such studies identified a transcriptional silencer in <italic>Thpok</italic>, hereafter denoted as <italic>Thpok</italic> silencer (<italic>Sth</italic>), which is an essential cis-acting element restricting <italic>Thpok</italic> expression to post-selection thymocytes in the helper lineage<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. In addition to <italic>Sth</italic>, there are at least three enhancers in the <italic>Thpok</italic> locus<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>. Among them, the thymic enhancer (<italic>TE</italic>), located upstream of the <italic>Sth</italic>, acts first to initiate <italic>Thpok</italic> expression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>, which is subsequently upregulated through the activity of a proximal enhancer (<italic>PE</italic>) locating 1.8&#x02009;kb downstream of the proximal P2-promoter<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. While factors that regulate <italic>Sth</italic> activity, such as Runx family proteins<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> and MAZR<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>, have been identified, the factors involved in the activation of <italic>TE</italic> and <italic>PE</italic> remain poorly characterized. Gata3<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup> and Tcf1/Lef1<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref></sup> regulate <italic>Thpok</italic> expression, but primarily do so by targeting other regulatory regions such as general T-lymphoid enhancer, the known third enhancer. In contrast to <italic>Thpok</italic> regulation, very little is known about transcription factors that orchestrate CD8<sup>+</sup> T cell-specific expression of <italic>Runx3</italic> from its distal P1-promoter<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. Signals emanating from the IL-7 cytokine receptor have been shown to activate <italic>Runx3</italic>
<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>; however, the intermediaries and their cis-regulatory targets in <italic>Runx3</italic> remain to be established<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par6">Here we report two mechanisms by which Bcl11b governs the transcriptional program dissecting helper versus cytotoxic lineage commitment: <italic>Sth</italic>-independent repression of <italic>Thpok</italic> in DN thymocytes and enhancer-dependent <italic>Runx3</italic> repression in CD4-lineage cells. Deletion of Bcl11b in thymocytes at post-&#x003b2;-selection stage causes chaotic <italic>Thpok</italic> and <italic>Runx3</italic> expression, inducing random differentiation of both MHC-I and MHC-II selected cells into the helper and cytotoxic subsets. Along with earlier requirement for Bcl11b prior to DP stage in later <italic>Foxp3</italic> activation, we conclude that lineage-specifying genes are &#x02018;primed&#x02019; by Bcl11b before or during transition to the DP stage to represent an essential event for coupling TCR signals to expression programs for differentiating into the appropriate T-effector subsets.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Bcl11b binds to the <italic>Thpok</italic> locus</title><p id="Par7">Based on our assumption that proteins bound to <italic>Thpok</italic> silencer (<italic>Sth</italic>) should mediate coupling of TCR signals during positive selection with release of <italic>Thpok</italic> expression, we attempted to purify protein complexes by in vitro capture with an oligo-nucleotide harboring core <italic>Sth</italic> sequences. Consistent with prior chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) assays<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>, Bcl11b protein was efficiently enriched by affinity purification with core <italic>Sth</italic> sequences, but to lesser extent with mutant <italic>Sth</italic> sequences (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1a</xref>). Bcl11b also associated with other known <italic>Sth</italic> binding proteins, Runx1 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1b</xref>). Furthermore, reduction of <italic>Bcll1b</italic> dosage to the half (<italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup>) in the <italic>Runx</italic> mutant mice, in which combined mutations of <italic>Runx1</italic> and <italic>Runx3</italic> genes attenuated <italic>Sth</italic>-mediated <italic>Thpok</italic> repression<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>, resulted in an increase of CD8<sup>+</sup> subset de-repressing a <italic>Thpok</italic>
<sup><italic>gfp</italic></sup> reporter<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1c</xref>), indicating genetic interaction between two factors in the regulation of <italic>Sth</italic> function. Our ChIP sequencing (ChIP-seq) assay of total thymocytes also detected that Bcl11b associated with <italic>Sth</italic> and proximal enhancer (<italic>PE</italic>) as well as intronic regions downstream from distal P1-promoter in the <italic>Thpok</italic> locus (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1d</xref>). Bcl11b also bound to an upstream regulatory element (URE)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup> in the <italic>Sfpi-1</italic> locus, which encodes a myeloid transcription factor, PU.1, and is a putative target of Bcl11b to eliminate myeloid potential during T-lineage commitment (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1d</xref>). A more global analysis revealed the Runx recognition motif (5&#x02032;-ACCPuCA-3&#x02032;) as the second-ranked sequence enriched at Bcl11b-bound regions in thymocytes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1e</xref>) and Runx bindings coincided with &#x02009;~&#x02009;85 % of Bcl11b-bound regions (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1e</xref>), which is consistent with previous observation using neuronal cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. However, Bcl11b binding to <italic>Sth</italic> was Runx-independent, as determined using primary CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells in which two Runx sites within the <italic>Sth</italic> were mutated by a knock-in on the <italic>Thpok</italic>
<sup><italic>gfp</italic></sup> reporter allele<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>, whereas ThPOK binding to the <italic>Thpok</italic> silencer requires Runx-binding (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1f</xref>). Our analytical ChIP assay in CD4<sup>+</sup> and CD8<sup>+</sup> T cell subset detected that Bcl11b binding at <italic>PE</italic> was greater in Thpok-expressing CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, while fivefold more Runx was bound to <italic>Sth</italic> in ThPOK-negative cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1g</xref>). These results suggest that Bcl11b directly regulates activity of <italic>Thpok</italic> locus through binding to the silencer and enhancer elements.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Binding of Bcl11b to regulatory regions in the <italic>Thpok</italic> gene. <bold>a</bold> DNA pull-down assay showing in vitro Bcl11b binding to wild-type (Wt) <italic>Thpok</italic> silencer (<italic>Sth</italic>) core sequences, but not efficiently to mutant (Mut.) sequences. One representative of two experiments. <bold>b</bold> Co-immune precipitation assay showing interaction of Bcl11b with Runx1. One representative of two experiments. <bold>c</bold> Flow cytometry showing an increase of CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells de-repressing Thpok-GFP upon reduction of <italic>Bcl11b</italic> dosage in <italic>Runx</italic> mutant mice. One representative of two independent experiments. <bold>d</bold> Bcl11b ChIP-seq tracks at the <italic>Thpok</italic>, <italic>Thpok</italic>
<sup><italic>gfp:&#x00394;TESPE</italic></sup>, and <italic>Sfpi1</italic> genes in total thymocytes along with Runx ChIP-seq (GSE90794) tracks at the <italic>Thpok</italic> gene (<italic>top</italic>) for reference. Gene structure, transcriptional orientation and conservations in mammals (Cons.) in the <italic>Thpok</italic> gene are indicated. Positions of <italic>Thpok</italic> silencer (<italic>Sth</italic>), two enhancers (<italic>TE</italic> and <italic>PE</italic>), distal P1-promoter (<italic>P1</italic>) and proximal enhancer (<italic>PE</italic>) in the <italic>Thpok</italic> gene, and upstream regulatory element (<italic>URE</italic>) in the <italic>Sfpi1</italic> gene are indicated as <italic>arrowheads</italic>. <bold>e</bold> Co-occupancy by Runx at Bcl11b-bound genome regions. Runx recognition site (5&#x02032;-ACCPuCA-3&#x02032;) was listed among the top two common sequences for Bcl11b-bound regions. <bold>f</bold> ChIP-PCR assay for binding of Runx, Bcl11b, and ThPOK to Wt and Runx site mutated (RSM) <italic>Sth</italic> regions in CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells from <italic>Thpok</italic>
<sup><italic>+/gfp:241-401RM</italic></sup> mice. Lanes 1, 2, and 3 are input, control IgG and antibody-against the indicated transcription factor, respectively. One representative of two independent experiments. <bold>g</bold> ChIP-qPCR analyses showing binding of Runx and Bcl11b to the <italic>Sth</italic> and <italic>PE</italic> in CD4<sup>+</sup> (white bars) and CD8<sup>+</sup> (gray bars) T cells. Combined data from three independent ChIP experiments is shown. **<italic>P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;</italic>0.01 (unpaired <italic>t</italic>-test)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2017_768_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e1001"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Impaired <italic>Thpok</italic> regulation in <italic>Bcl11b</italic> mutant mice</title><p id="Par8">Because there is a developmental arrest at the DN2a stage when Bcl11b function is completely lacking, it is necessary to utilize a <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>fl</italic></sup> allele to examine the function of Bcl11b during T cell development beyond the DN stage. We therefore attempted to generate our own <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>fl</italic></sup> allele. However, our first trial unexpectedly generated a mutant <italic>Bcl11b</italic> allele, hereafter referred as to a <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m</italic></sup>, which produced a truncated Bcl11b protein due to a frameshift mutation incorporated into the targeting vector during its construction (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a</xref> and Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1a&#x02212;c</xref>). Despite its loss of the final zinc-finger motif, truncated mutant Bcl11b protein could bind to the <italic>Sth</italic> and an intronic region in the <italic>Thpok</italic>, as well as to the URE in <italic>Sfpi-1</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2b</xref>). Similar to <italic>Bcl11b null</italic> animals (<italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</italic></sup>), homozygous <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m</italic></sup> mice died as neonates (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1d</xref>). However, in contrast to the null animals, which completely lack CD4<sup>+</sup>CD8<sup>+</sup> DP thymocytes and thereby have small thymus<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>, we noticed that total thymocyte number is only slightly reduced in <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m/m</italic></sup> neonates (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1e</xref>) and, more strikingly, the DP population was present in those mice (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1f</xref>). In addition, <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m/m</italic></sup> progenitors gave rise to ILC2 cells (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1g</xref>), a subset that does not develop from <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</italic></sup> progenitors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. These results indicated that the mutant <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m</italic></sup> is a hypomorphic allele, thereby hereafter its product is referred to as hypomorphic Bcl11b protein (Bcl11b<sup>HM</sup>).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>CD4-skewed development by impaired <italic>Thpok</italic> regulation from hypomorphic <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m/m</italic></sup> progenitors. <bold>a</bold> Expression of truncated Bcl11b protein in the neonatal thymus from the hypomorphic <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m</italic></sup> allele detected by an antibody recognizing the N- (<italic>left</italic>), but not the C- (<italic>right</italic>), terminus of Bcl11b. One representative of two experiments. <bold>b</bold> Summary of ChIP assay for binding of Wt (white bars) and hypomorphic (black bars) Bcl11b to indicated regions in total neonatal thymocytes. <bold>c</bold>&#x02212;<bold>e</bold> Flow cytometry analyzing the expression of CD4, CD8, and Thpok-GFP during T cell development in Rag1-deficient hosts <bold>c</bold> and irradiated MHC-II deficient hosts <bold>e</bold> reconstituted with fetal liver cells with the indicated genotypes. Data are representative of at least two independent experiments. Numbers in <italic>dot plots</italic> indicate the percentage of cells in each quadrant. Histograms showing CD40L expression 2 days after in vitro TCR stimulation of peripheral CD4<sup>+</sup>, CD8<sup>+</sup> and CD4<sup>&#x02212;</sup>CD8<sup>&#x02212;</sup> DN cells differentiated in Rag1-deficient mice from <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>+/+</italic></sup>and <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m/m</italic></sup> fetal liver cells <bold>d</bold>. Data are representative of two independent experiments</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2017_768_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e1223"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par9">We next investigated the T cell development of <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m/m</italic></sup> progenitors that also harbor a <italic>Thpok</italic>
<sup><italic>gfp</italic></sup> reporter allele. For this purpose, we transferred <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m/m</italic></sup>:<italic>Thpok</italic>
<sup><italic>+/gfp</italic></sup> or control <italic>Thpok</italic>
<sup><italic>+/gfp</italic></sup> fetal liver progenitors into T cell-deficient <italic>Rag1</italic>
<sup><italic>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</italic></sup> hosts, allowing differentiation of the progenitors to proceed for two months. As shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref>, Thpok-GFP expression was absent in pre-selection thymocytes (defined as CD24<sup>hi</sup>TCR&#x003b2;<sup>lo</sup>) from control cells. In sharp contrast, nearly all pre-selection thymocytes derived from the transferred <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m/m</italic></sup> progenitors expressed Thpok-GFP. While the two major T cell subsets, CD4<sup>+</sup> helper and CD8<sup>+</sup> cytotoxic, were differentiated from control <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>+/+</italic></sup> progenitors, <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m/m</italic></sup> progenitors gave rise to predominantly CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells with a helper-related signature (e.g., CD40L induction) in mature thymocyte and peripheral T cell populations (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c, d</xref>). To address whether a re-direction of MHC-I selected cells to the CD4<sup>+</sup> lineage contributed to this CD4-skewing, we generated chimeras using irradiated MHC-II deficient hosts expressing the Ly9.1 marker, in which only differentiation of MHC-I selected cells was supported. Strikingly, we continued to observe skewing of CD4 differentiation in Ly9.1<sup>&#x02212;</sup> donor-derived populations from <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m/m</italic></sup>, but not <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>+/+</italic></sup>, progenitors (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2e</xref>). The shift to CD4 dominant differentiation was not observed when <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m/m</italic></sup>
<italic>:Thpok</italic>
<sup><italic>gfp/gfp</italic></sup> progenitors lacking ThPOK expression were transferred (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref>). Along with de-repression of Thpok-GFP in remaining CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref>), we conclude that aberrant <italic>Thpok</italic> expression redirects MHC class I-selected <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m/m</italic></sup> thymocytes to the CD4<sup>+</sup> lineage. After these initial characterizations of the hypomorphic <italic>Bcll11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m</italic></sup> allele, we generated a true conditional mutant (<italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>fl</italic></sup>) allele and a mutant allele that retains the identical frameshift mutation to the <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m</italic></sup> allele but lacks the loxP sequence in its 3&#x02032;UTR, which we referred to as the <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>HM</italic></sup> allele (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1a</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Silencer-independent <italic>Thpok</italic> repression by Bcl11b</title><p id="Par10">To further investigate how <italic>Thpok</italic> expression was de-regulated in <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m/m</italic></sup> cells, we examined promoter usages. Prior studies have shown that <italic>Thpok</italic> is transcribed from distal P1- and proximal P2-promoters<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup>, however, P2-derived transcripts were detected specifically in T-lineage cells and require <italic>PE</italic> activity (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a, b</xref>). Given the loss of Thpok-GFP expression in peripheral T cells upon removal of both <italic>TE</italic> and <italic>PE</italic> (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2a</xref>), <italic>TE</italic> is likely to drive P1-promoter activity in T cells. In contrast, <italic>Thpok</italic> transcript in <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m/m</italic></sup> pre-selection thymocytes was transcribed only from the P1-promoter (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3c</xref>). To understand the underlying mechanisms for unusual P1-promoter activation without P2-promoter activation in <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m/m</italic></sup> thymocytes, we examined Thpok-GFP expression from the <italic>Thpok</italic>
<sup><italic>gfp:&#x00394;TESPE</italic></sup> reporter allele, in which all three T cell-specific regulatory elements, <italic>Sth</italic>, <italic>TE</italic>, and <italic>PE</italic>, were removed from the <italic>Thpok</italic>
<sup><italic>gfp</italic></sup> allele by sequential gene targeting (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d</xref>). In Bcl11b wild-type cells, <italic>Thpok</italic> expression from the enhancer-deficient <italic>Thpok</italic>
<sup><italic>gfp:&#x00394;TESPE</italic></sup> reporter allele was derived solely from the P1-promoter (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2b</xref>), and was detected only in cells after the post-selection stages (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d</xref>). In contrast, despite deletion of the <italic>Sth</italic> silencer, Thpok-GFP expression from the <italic>Thpok</italic>
<sup><italic>gfp:&#x00394;TESPE</italic></sup> reporter allele was initiated in <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m/m</italic></sup> thymocytes at DN3 stage and its expression level was increased during transition to DP stage (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3d</xref>). These data revealed the presence of undefined <italic>Sth</italic>-independent mechanism by which Bcl11b represses <italic>Thpok</italic> expression in DN3 as well as in DP thymocytes.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>
<italic>Sth</italic>-independent <italic>Thpok</italic> repression by Bcl11b in pre-selection DP thymocytes. <bold>a</bold> Quantitative RT-PCR showing amount of promoter-specific <italic>Thpok</italic> transcripts in splenic CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells and splenic B220<sup>+</sup> B lymphocytes. Summary of three measurements. <bold>b</bold> Quantitative RT-PCR for <italic>Thpok-gfp</italic> expression in CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells from mutant reporter alleles, <italic>Thpok</italic>
<sup><italic>gfp:&#x00394;TE</italic></sup> and <italic>Thpok</italic>
<sup><italic>gfp:&#x00394;PE</italic></sup>, lacking the thymic enhancer (<italic>TE</italic>) or proximal enhancer (<italic>PE</italic>), respectively. Levels of P1- and P2 promoter-specific transcripts relative to those from the control <italic>Thpok</italic>
<sup><italic>gfp</italic></sup> allele harboring intact enhancers is shown. One representative of two independent experiments. <bold>c</bold> Promoter-specific <italic>Thpok</italic> transcripts in <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m/m</italic></sup> pre-selection DP thymocytes and CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells relative to those in control CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells. Summary of three measurements. <bold>d</bold> Histograms showing Thpok-GFP expression from the <italic>Thpok</italic>
<sup><italic>gfp:&#x00394;TESPE</italic></sup> allele in the indicated cell subsets differentiated in Rag1-deficient recipients from control (<italic>dotted line</italic>) and <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m/m</italic></sup> (<italic>solid line</italic>) fetal liver cells. Expression pattern of <italic>Thpok</italic>
<sup><italic>gfp</italic></sup> is shown as reference (<italic>shaded</italic>). Schematic structure of the <italic>Thpok</italic>
<sup><italic>gfp:&#x00394;TESPE</italic></sup> allele is included (<italic>upper panel</italic>). One representative of two independent experiments. <bold>e</bold> ATAC-seq tracks at the <italic>Thpok</italic> locus in CD24<sup>hi</sup>TCR&#x003b2;<sup>lo</sup>CD4<sup>+</sup>CD8<sup>+</sup> pre-selection thymocytes of 6-week-old <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>+/+</italic></sup> mice, newborn <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>+/fl</italic></sup>
<italic>:Lck-cre</italic>, newborn <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>HM/fl</italic></sup>
<italic>:Lck-cre</italic> and newborn <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>HM/HM</italic></sup>
<italic>:Lck-cre</italic> mice. ATAC-seq results in immature B cells (GSM2123187) is shown as reference. DP thymocyte- and B lymphocyte-specific peaks are marked with <italic>blue</italic> and <italic>red arrowheads</italic>, respectively. Position of the P1 promoter is indicated with <italic>black arrowhead</italic>
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2017_768_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e1743"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par11">To further address activation status of <italic>Thpok</italic> locus in <italic>Bcl11b</italic> mutant cells, we examined chromatin accessibility in DP thymocytes prepared from a <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>HM/fl</italic></sup>
<italic>:Lck-Cre</italic> and <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>HM/HM</italic></sup>
<italic>:Lck-Cre</italic> mice by ATAC-seq<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>. Interestingly, the <italic>Thpok</italic> locus in <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>HM/HM</italic></sup> pre-selection thymocytes retained open chromatin signatures around the P1-promoter, resembling those seen in B&#x000a0;cells expressing P1-derived transcripts (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3e</xref>). ChIP-seq analyses for Bcl11b binding in thymocytes of <italic>Thpok</italic>
<sup><italic>gfp:&#x00394;TESPE/gfp:&#x00394;TESPE</italic></sup> mice detected association of Bcl11b at intronic regions nearby the P1-promoter (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1d</xref>), which retained accessibility in the <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>HM/HM</italic></sup> cells and whose sequences are evolutionally conserved (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1d</xref>). Similar open structure was observed in DP cells of <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>HM/fl</italic></sup>
<italic>:Lck</italic>-<italic>Cre</italic> mice. These observations indicate that truncation of Bcl11b C-terminal sequences interferes, most specifically, with normal patterns of <italic>Thpok</italic> expression at early thymocyte differentiation, reconfiguring its regulome to mimic expression patterns found in B&#x000a0;cells. However, RNA-seq did not detect significant elevation of B cell signature genes in <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m/m</italic></sup> pre-selection thymocytes (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3a, b</xref>), suggesting that Bcll1b might be involved in modulating chromatin accessibility at the restricted loci such as <italic>Thpok</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title><italic>Bcl11b</italic> is needed for lineage fidelity by MHC-restriction</title><p id="Par12">Contrary to CD4-skewing from <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m/m</italic></sup> progenitor, a previous study reported emergence of CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells following <italic>Bcl11b</italic> inactivation at the DP stage using a <italic>Cd4-Cre</italic> driver. We reasoned that the apparent discrepancy could result from a stage-specific requirement for Bcl11b in regulating <italic>Thpok</italic> gene. We therefore next examined effect of <italic>Bcl11b</italic> inactivation by <italic>Cd4-Cre</italic> driver on <italic>Thpok</italic> expression. Although Thpok-GFP was uniformly de-repressed in all <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m/m</italic></sup> pre-selection thymocytes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref>), expression of this reporter was variegated and detected in only half of the pre-selection thymocytes from <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>fl/fl</italic></sup>
<italic>:Cd4-Cre</italic> mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>). We also observed that CD4<sup>+</sup>CD8<sup>+</sup> and CD4<sup>&#x02212;</sup>CD8<sup>+</sup> subsets were present in mature thymocytes from <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>fl/fl</italic></sup>
<italic>:Cd4-Cre</italic> mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a, b</xref>). It is noteworthy that, after positive selection, levels of Thpok-GFP in CD4<sup>+</sup>CD8<sup>&#x02212;</sup> cells differentiated from <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m/m</italic></sup> progenitors or in <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>fl/fl</italic></sup>
<italic>:Cd4-Cre</italic> mice were lower than those in control counterparts (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2c</xref> and Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref> middle), a shift that was also reflected in attenuated <italic>P2-Thpok</italic> mRNA (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3c</xref>). Thus, loss of Bcl11b function disrupts not only <italic>Thpok</italic> repression, but also distinct mechanisms for its activation. These results suggests that, in a portion of pre-selection thymocytes in the <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>fl/fl</italic></sup>
<italic>:Cd4-Cre</italic> mice, the kinetics of <italic>Thpok</italic> de-repression are delayed compared to <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m/m</italic></sup> progenitors, which is combined later with low <italic>Thpok</italic> expression levels, allowing the cells to differentiate into CD4<sup>+</sup>CD8<sup>+</sup> and CD4<sup>&#x02212;</sup>CD8<sup>+</sup> subsets.<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Lineage scrambling resulting from inactivation of <italic>Bcl11b</italic> at the DP stage due to sporadic <italic>Thpok</italic> and <italic>Runx3</italic> expression. <bold>a</bold> Flow cytometry analyzing the expression of CD4, CD8, Thpok-GFP, and Runx3-tdTomato by various thymocyte subsets in mice with the indicated genotypes. The histogram in the middle showing Thpok-GFP expression in CD4<sup>+</sup>CD8<sup>&#x02212;</sup> mature thymocytes from control (<italic>open</italic>) and <italic>Bcl11b-deficient</italic> (<italic>shaded</italic>) cells. <bold>b</bold> Graph showing summary of percentage of each subset in mature (CD24<sup>&#x02212;</sup>TCR&#x003b2;<sup>hi</sup>) thymocytes population of mice with indicated genotype. <bold>c</bold> Flow cytometry analyzing the expression of CD4, CD8, Thpok-GFP and Runx3-tdTomato in lymph node T cells of mice with the indicated genotypes. One representative of at least independent mice. <bold>d</bold> Flow cytometry analyzing the expression of CD4, CD8, Thpok-GFP and Runx3-tdTomato in pre-selection DP thymocytes and lymph node T cells differentiated in Rag1-KO hosts from <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>+/+</italic></sup> and <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m/m</italic></sup> fetal livers harboring <italic>Thpok</italic>
<sup><italic>gfp</italic></sup> and <italic>Runx3</italic>
<sup><italic>tdTomato</italic></sup> reporter alleles. One representative of two independent experiments. <bold>e</bold>, <bold>f</bold> Representative flow cytometry <bold>e</bold> analyzing differentiation of MHC-I and MHC-II selected cells in MHC-II and MHC-I deficient (MHC-II<sup>0</sup> and MHC-I<sup>0</sup>) backgrounds, respectively, along with a graph <bold>f</bold> showing a statistical summary of the percentages and absolute numbers in each cell subset in CD24<sup>&#x02212;</sup>TCR&#x003b2;<sup>hi</sup> mature thymocytes population of control (white circles) and <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>fl/fl</italic></sup>
<italic>:Cd4-Cre</italic> (filled circles) mice. Partial re-directed differentiation occurred in both MHC-I and -II selected cells. *<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, **<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01, and ***<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001(unpaired <italic>t</italic>-test)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2017_768_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e2137"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par13">Since previous studies showed release of <italic>Runx3</italic> repression in CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells that differentiated under low levels of ThPOK<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>, we next examined <italic>Runx3</italic> expression using a <italic>Runx3-tdTomato</italic> reporter allele that monitors distal P1-promoter activity, which is CD8-linege specific and serves as a major source for Runx3 protein expression in T cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. Importantly, we found that most mature thymocytes from <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>fl/fl</italic></sup>
<italic>:Cd4-Cre</italic> mice co-expressed Runx3-tdTomato and Thpok-GFP, regardless of their CD4/CD8 expression profiles (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>), whereas expression of these genes was mutually exclusive between CD4<sup>+</sup>CD8<sup>&#x02212;</sup> and CD4<sup>&#x02212;</sup>CD8<sup>+</sup> cells from control mice. Contrary to a previous report showing <italic>Runx3</italic> de-repression in CD4<sup>+</sup>CD8<sup>+</sup> DP thymocytes of <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>fl/fl</italic></sup>
<italic>:Cd4-Cre</italic> mice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup>, Runx3-tdTomato was not detectably expressed in CD24<sup>hi</sup>TCR&#x003b2;<sup>lo</sup> pre-selection thymocytes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a</xref>). Co-expression of Thpok-GFP and Runx3-tdTomato was observed also in CD4<sup>+</sup>CD8<sup>&#x02212;</sup> and CD4<sup>&#x02212;</sup>CD8<sup>+</sup> cells in the peripheral T cell pool of <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>fl/fl</italic></sup>
<italic>:Cd4-Cre</italic> mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4c</xref>), as well as in CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells differentiated from <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m/m</italic></sup> progenitors (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4d</xref>). Thus, lineage-specific expression of two major factors, ThPOK and Runx3, which drive the CD4/CD8 lineage dichotomy, requires Bcl11b, or more specifically, Bcl11b function mediated by its C-terminal sequences.</p><p id="Par14">We next examined the MHC specificity of T cells differentiated in <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>fl/fl</italic></sup>
<italic>:Cd4-Cre</italic> mice by crossing with MHC-I or MHC-II deficient mice. In mature thymocytes and peripheral T cell populations, a significant proportion of both MHC-I- and MHC-II-specific cells in <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>fl/fl</italic></sup>
<italic>:Cd4-Cre</italic> mice expressed surface markers for the alternative lineage, CD8 and CD4, respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4e, f</xref>). We therefore conclude that a substantial number of both MHC-I and MHC-II selected thymocytes failed in their specification for the appropriate developmental pathway, presumably due to spurious expression of ThPOK and Runx3 following positive selection. Ultimately, the chaotic expression of these factors resulted in &#x0201c;lineage scrambling&#x0201d;, unlinking DP precursor thymocyte commitment from MHC specificity.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Functions of Bcl11b in <italic>Runx3</italic> regulation</title><p id="Par15">To understand how Bcl11b regulates <italic>Runx3</italic> expression, we examined whether genomic regions around the <italic>Runx3</italic> locus were occupied by Bcl11b, Runx, and ThPOK factors. In addition to the P1-promoter, Bcl11b and Runx bound at two regions (&#x02212;39 and &#x02212;21&#x02009;kb), which were also bound by ThPOK (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref>) that is essential for <italic>Runx3</italic> repression in CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. To examine potential of these regions as <italic>cis</italic>-regulatory elements for <italic>Runx3</italic> regulation, we removed the regions separately or in combination from the <italic>Runx3-tdTomato</italic> allele using CRISPR/Cas9 technology<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup> (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">4</xref>). Levels of Runx3-tdTomato expression in CD4<sup>&#x02212;</sup>CD8<sup>+</sup> SP thymocytes were reduced upon removal of either the &#x02212;39 or &#x02212;21&#x02009;kb region, but not a control region of similar length positioned at &#x02212;40&#x02009;kb region (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref>). Expression of the <italic>Runx3</italic> reporter was further attenuated following combined deletion of the &#x02212;39 and &#x02212;21&#x02009;kb regions. These observations indicated essential regulatory functions for these two regions in driving proper levels of <italic>Runx3</italic> expression in CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells. The residual expression when both regions were removed also indicated the presence of other enhancer(s) in the <italic>Runx3</italic> locus.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Roles of Bcl11b in ThPOK-mediated repression of <italic>Runx3</italic>. <bold>a</bold> Runx and Bcl11b ChIP-seq tracks at the <italic>Runx3</italic> locus using total thymocytes, along with a ThPOK ChIP-chip track using CD4 SP thymocytes. Schematic structure of mutant <italic>Runx3</italic>
<sup><italic>tdTomato</italic></sup> reporter alleles harboring several types of deletion (<italic>bottom panel</italic>, <italic>left</italic>). Histograms (<italic>bottom panel</italic>, <italic>right</italic>) showing Runx3-tdTomato expression in CD4<sup>&#x02212;</sup>CD8<sup>+</sup> thymocytes from indicated mutant alleles (<italic>solid line</italic>) and non-transgenic allele (<italic>dotted line</italic>). Data shown are representative of at least three independent mice. <bold>b</bold> Amount of <italic>Socs1</italic> and <italic>Socs3</italic> mRNA in CD4 SP thymocytes and CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells from mice of indicated genotypes. Summary of three independent experiments. Mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD **<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 (unpaired <italic>t</italic>-test). <bold>c</bold> ChIP-qPCR analyzing ThPOK binding to the <italic>Sth</italic> in <italic>Thpok</italic> and the &#x02212;39E and &#x02212;21E regions in the <italic>Runx3</italic> using chromatin from CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells of Wt (white bars) and <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>f/f</italic></sup>
<italic>:Cd4-Cre</italic> (gray bars) mice. Combined data of three independent ChIP experiments. Means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD. <bold>d</bold> Flow cytometry analyzing the effect of a <italic>Thpok</italic> transgene on <italic>Cd8</italic> and <italic>Runx3</italic> expression. <italic>Dot plots</italic> showing CD4/CD8 expression in splenic T cells. Histograms at the right show <italic>Runx3</italic>
<sup><italic>tdTomato</italic></sup> reporter expression in Wt (white) and <italic>Bcl11b-deficient</italic> (gray) CD4<sup>+</sup>CD8<sup>&#x02212;</sup> subset. One representative of three individual mice. <bold>e</bold> Histograms showing CD8 and Runx3-tdTomato expression in control CD4<sup>&#x02212;</sup>CD8<sup>+</sup>, Bcl11b-deficient CD4<sup>&#x02212;</sup>CD8<sup>+</sup> and CD4<sup>+</sup>CD8<sup>&#x02212;</sup> T cells after retroviral transduction of Wt (<italic>open</italic>) and the non-functional <italic>HD</italic> mutant ThPOK (<italic>shaded</italic>). One representative of two independent experiments</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2017_768_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e2520"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par16">SOCS family proteins were proposed to mediate ThPOK-dependent repression of <italic>Runx3</italic> following thymocyte positive selection<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. However, expression of <italic>Socs1</italic> and <italic>Socs3</italic> was not reduced in Bcl11b-deficient CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells expressing <italic>Runx3</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5b</xref>). In Bcl11b-deficient cells, ThPOK bindings to &#x02212;39 and &#x02212;21 enhancers were also observed, albeit to a lesser extent, presumably due to lower ThPOK expression levels (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5c</xref>). We then tested whether ectopic ThPOK expression restored <italic>Runx3</italic> repression in CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells. Although transgenic ThPOK prevented the development of CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells in <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>fl/fl</italic></sup>
<italic>:Cd4-Cre</italic> mice, Runx3-tdTomato was not repressed as much in CD4<sup>+</sup>CD8<sup>&#x02212;</sup> splenic T cells (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5d</xref>). Consistent with this observation, retroviral ThPOK transduction into peripheral CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells reduced Runx3-tdTomato expression in control cells, but not in Bcl11b-deficient cells, while CD8 expression was reduced in both cells, as reported previously<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5e</xref>). These results indicated that full <italic>Runx3</italic> repression by ThPOK required Bcl11b after ThPOK bound to Runx3 enhancers. In contrast, ThPOK could repress <italic>Cd8</italic> expression in the absence of Bcl11b.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Bcl11b regulates <italic>Thpok</italic> and <italic>Runx3</italic> expression</title><p id="Par17">To address at which developmental stages Bcl11b is necessary for appropriate <italic>Thpok</italic> and <italic>Runx3</italic> expression, we inactivated the <italic>Bcl11b</italic> gene during maturation of MHC-II selected cells using a <italic>Thpok-Cre</italic> driver<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref></sup>. While CD4 and CD8 expression on peripheral T cells remained unchanged in <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>fl/fl</italic></sup>
<italic>:Thpok-Cre</italic> mice, the expression of Thpok-GFP and Runx3-tdTomato in CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells was decreased or increased, respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6a, b</xref>). When <italic>Bcl11b</italic> was inactivated in differentiated CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells by retroviral Cre transduction, de-repression of Thpok-GFP was also observed (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6c</xref>). These findings indicated that Bcl11b was necessary to maintain lineage-specific expression of both <italic>Thpok</italic> and <italic>Runx3</italic> after primary commitment of post-selection thymocytes to CD4/CD8 lineages.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Bcl11b function requires its C-terminal zinc-finger motif. <bold>a</bold> Flow cytometry analyzing the expression of CD4, CD8, Thpok-GFP, and Runx3-tdTomato in peripheral T cells from <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>+/+</italic></sup>
<italic>:Thpok-Cre</italic> and <italic>Bcl1b</italic>
<sup><italic>fl/fl</italic></sup>
<italic>:Thpok-Cre</italic> mice harboring <italic>Thpok</italic>
<sup><italic>gfp</italic></sup> and <italic>Runx3</italic>
<sup><italic>tdTomato</italic></sup> reporter genes. Inactivation of <italic>Bcl11b</italic> during the maturation of CD4-lineage cells by a <italic>Thpok-Cre</italic> transgene resulted in impaired Thpok-GFP expression, as well as Runx3-tdTomato de-repression. <bold>b</bold> RT-qPCR analyses showing relative amounts of <italic>Thpok</italic> (black bars) and <italic>P1-Runx3</italic> (white bars) mRNA in splenic CD4<sup>+</sup>CD8<sup>&#x02212;</sup> T cells of <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>+/+</italic></sup>
<italic>:Thpok-Cre</italic> and <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>fl/fl</italic></sup>
<italic>:Thpok-Cre</italic> mice. Results in splenic CD4<sup>&#x02212;</sup>CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells of <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>+/+</italic></sup>:<italic>Thpok-Cre</italic> are shown as references. Data were summary of three experiments. Means&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SD *<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05 (unpaired <italic>t</italic>-test). <bold>c</bold> Histograms showing Thpok-GFP expression from CD4<sup>+</sup> and CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells of <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>+/+</italic></sup>
<italic>:Thpok</italic>
<sup><italic>+/gfp</italic></sup> (white bars) and <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>fl/fl</italic></sup>
<italic>:Thpok</italic>
<sup><italic>+/gfp</italic></sup> (gray bars) mice 4 days after retroviral Cre transduction. One representative of three experiments. <bold>d</bold> Histograms showing Runx3-tdTomato expression 3 days after retroviral transduction of Wt and hypomorphic (HM) Bcl11b into peripheral CD4<sup>+</sup>CD8<sup>&#x02212;</sup>
<italic>Runx3-tdTomato</italic>
<sup><italic>+</italic></sup> cells from <italic>Bcl1b</italic>
<sup><italic>fl/fl</italic></sup>
<italic>:Runx3</italic>
<sup><italic>+/tdTomato</italic></sup>
<italic>:Thpok-Cre</italic> mice. Expression of Runx3-tdTomato in activated control CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells (<italic>dotted line</italic>) after transduction with an empty vector (<italic>open</italic>) are shown as controls. <bold>e</bold> Histograms showing Runx3-tdTomato expression after retroviral transduction of mutant Bcl11b proteins lacking the C-terminal zinc-finger motif are shown as in <bold>d</bold>. The <italic>dotted line</italic> represents Runx3-tdTomato expression after transduction of Wt Bcl11b. One representative of at least two experiments <bold>d</bold>, <bold>e</bold>
</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2017_768_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e2868"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par18">We also tested the converse scenario, namely, whether retroviral Bcl11b transduction restored Runx3-tdTomato repression in differentiated CD4<sup>+</sup> cells of <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>fl/fl</italic></sup>
<italic>:Thpok-Cre</italic> mice. Levels of Runx3-tdTomato was reduced upon Bcl11b transduction compared with empty vector controls (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6d</xref>); however, transduction with a vector encoding the Bcl11b<sup>HM</sup> protein repressed Runx3-tdTomato to lesser extent than wild-type Bcl11b (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6d</xref>). To gain more insights into the domainal structure of Bcl11b, we tested the activities of other mutants generated by sequential deletion on its C-terminus (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">5</xref>). While a Bcl11b mutant retaining the final zinc-finger domain (Bcl11b-&#x00394;10) and wild-type Bcl11b equally repressed Runx3-tdTomato expression, other mutants lacking the zinc-finger structure showed weaker activity (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6e</xref>). These results not only confirmed that loss of the last zinc-finger motif, rather than acquisition of aberrant sequences, attenuated Bcl11b function in the Bcl11b<sup>HM</sup> protein, but the new data also indicated that the last zinc-finger motif is essential for Bcl11b function in preserving lineage-specific <italic>Runx3</italic> expression.</p><p id="Par19">In this regard, we compared structures of Bcl11 family proteins in other species. There are two zinc-finger clusters in Bcl11b, double zinc-fingers in its central region and triple zinc-fingers at its C-terminus. Comparative genomics analyses revealed that some species, such as the Ascidians (<italic>C</italic>. <italic>intestinalis</italic>) and Worm (<italic>C. elegans</italic>), lacked the middle zinc-finger motif in Bcl11 orthologues, whereas the triplet zinc-finger structure at the C-terminal was highly conserved during evolution (Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">6</xref>), suggesting that C-terminal triplet zinc-fingers could be involved in ancestral and conserved function of Bcl11 family proteins.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Stage-specific requirement for Bcl11b in <italic>Foxp3</italic> transcription</title><p id="Par20">Additional analyses of T cell development from <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m/m</italic></sup> progenitors detected a striking defect in the development of Foxp3<sup>+</sup> regulatory T cells (Treg) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7a</xref>). In line with this finding, we were unable to induce Foxp3 expression in the mutant CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells even under potent Treg differentiation conditions in vitro (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7b</xref>). Contrary to this finding, a previous study reported the emergence of Foxp3<sup>+</sup> Treg cells following <italic>Bcl11b</italic> inactivation at the DP stage using a <italic>Cd4-Cre</italic> driver<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. This apparent discrepancy could result from a direct and stage-specific requirement for Bcl11b in activating <italic>Foxp3</italic>, as we observed in Thpok regulation by Bcl11b. Recent work reported that the CNS3 region in the <italic>Foxp3</italic> gene is essential to initiate <italic>Foxp3</italic> activation by poising the <italic>Foxp3</italic> promoter in an active state prior to the DP stage<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>. Our ChIP-seq detected Bcl11b binding to CNS3 in total thymocytes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7c</xref>) and our ChIP-qPCR detected similar binding of both Bcl11b and Bcl11b<sup>HM</sup> proteins to CNS3 (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7d</xref>). Since we recently observed that binding of the genome organizer, SATB1, to CNS3 is essential for Foxp3<sup>+</sup> Treg development in the thymus<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>, we examined SATB1 association with CNS3 in <italic>Bcl11b</italic> mutant thymocytes. Consistent with development of Foxp3<sup>+</sup> cells, SATB1 binding to CNS3 was unaffected in total thymocytes from <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>fl/HM</italic></sup>
<italic>:Cd4-Cre</italic> mice. On the contrary, SATB1 recruitment was significantly decreased in those cells from <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>fl/HM</italic></sup>
<italic>:Lck-Cre</italic> mice (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7e</xref>). These results suggested that priming of the <italic>Foxp3</italic> locus by Bcl11b prior to the DP stage is essential for activation of <italic>Foxp3</italic> gene via promoting SATB1 recruitment to the CNS3 enhancer.<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Regulation of <italic>Foxp3</italic> expression by Bcl11b. <bold>a</bold> Expression of Foxp3 in CD4<sup>+</sup>CD8<sup>&#x02212;</sup> mature thymocytes differentiated in Rag1-KO hosts from <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>+/+</italic></sup> and <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m/m</italic></sup> fetal liver progenitors. A representative histogram (<italic>left</italic>) along with a summary of five independent hosts (<italic>right</italic>) are shown. ***<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001 (unpaired <italic>t</italic>-test). <bold>b</bold> Histogram showing Foxp3 induction from CD62L<sup>+</sup>CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells after in vitro culture under Treg differentiation condition. One representative of two experiments. <bold>c</bold> Bcl11b ChIP-seq tracks at the <italic>Foxp3</italic> gene in DP thymocytes. Gene structure, transcriptional orientation and position of conserved non-coding sequence (CNS) 3 are indicated. <bold>d</bold> Summary of ChIP-qPCR assay for binding of Wt (white bars) and hypomorphic (black bars) Bcl11b to CNS2 and CNS3 regions in the <italic>Foxp3</italic> locus in neonatal total thymocytes. <bold>e</bold> ChIP-qPCR for binding of SATB1 to the CNS3 enhancer in the <italic>Foxp3</italic> gene. Chromatin was collected from DP thymocyte precursors using mice with the indicated genotypes. Combined data from three independent ChIP experiments are shown. **<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.01 (unpaired <italic>t</italic>-test)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41467_2017_768_Fig7_HTML" id="d29e3121"/></fig>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par21">In this study, we demonstrate that a hypomorphic Bcl11b protein (Bcl11b<sup>HM</sup>), lacking only its final zinc-finger domain, supports T-lineage commitment and ILC2 development. In contrast, the hypomorphic <italic>Bcl11b</italic> mutation fails to control the expression of transcription factors, including ThPOK, Runx3, and Foxp3, which are important for specification of mature T lineages (CD4-helper, CD8-cytotoxic, and Treg, respectively). Importantly, our findings dissect the functional architecture of Bcll1b, revealing independent regions that are responsible for early T-lineage commitment versus transcriptional regulation of lineage-specifying genes during positive selection.</p><p id="Par22">The distinct effects on expression of <italic>Thpok</italic> and <italic>Foxp3</italic> genes of the germline hypomorphic mutation when compared with a DP stage-specific inactivation of its gene indicate that Bcl11b acts on these two genes at an early developmental stage, presumably at the DN to DP transition, to control appropriate expression of these lineage-specifying transcription factors at later stage. For <italic>Thpok</italic>, while a half of precursors still repressed <italic>Thpok</italic> gene after conditional loss of Bcl11b expression, hypomorphic Bcl11b mutation caused <italic>Thpok</italic> expression in all precursors that retains non-T cells like open chromatin structure around the P1-promoter. This observation indicates that early <italic>Thpok</italic> repression at the DN to DP transition by Bcl11b involves chromatin closing. Our results using the <italic>Thpok</italic>
<sup><italic>gfp:&#x00394;TESPE</italic></sup> mutant reporter allele lacking <italic>Sth</italic> silencer revealed that Bcl11b regulates such chromatin closing independently of the <italic>Sth</italic>, which is essential to silence <italic>Thpok</italic> expression at later stage specifically in cytotoxic T cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. Given that the <italic>Sth</italic> is sufficient to repress reporter transgenes driven by heterologous enhancer/promoter in DP thymocytes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref></sup> and is essential to prevent expression of the endogenous gene in Bcl11b-sufficient DP cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>, both <italic>Sth</italic>-independent and <italic>Sth</italic>-dependent pathways operate to repress <italic>Thpok</italic> in precursor DP thymocytes. Considering that ectopic ThPOK expression in DP precursor thymocytes not only disturbs helper/cytotoxic lineage choice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup> but also increases a risk for lymphomagenesis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>, it might be beneficial to have two independent mechanisms to secure no leaky ThPOK expression in DP precursors. It is noteworthy that <italic>Sth</italic>-independent <italic>Thpok</italic> repression was reversible, since Thpok-GFP expression from the <italic>Thpok</italic>
<sup><italic>gfp:&#x00394;TESPE</italic></sup> allele was induced in mature T cells, suggesting that irreversible epigenetic changes such as DNA methylation are unlikely to be involved in early <italic>Sth</italic>-independent <italic>Thpok</italic> repression by Bcl11b. Given that <italic>Sth</italic> could stably silence <italic>Thpok</italic> transcript, particularly from the P2-promoter, in CD8-lineage cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>, mechanisms of <italic>Sth</italic>-dependent and <italic>Sth</italic>-independent <italic>Thpok</italic> repression could be different.</p><p id="Par23">The precise involvement of Bcl11b in <italic>Sth</italic>-independent <italic>Thpok</italic> repression remains elusive. As detected by ChIP-seq, Bcl11b covers regions around the P1-promoter in an <italic>Sth</italic>-independent manner. Along with evolutional conservation in sequences of intronic region just downstream of the P1-promoter, there might exist uncharacterized regulatory element(s) that suppresses P1-promoter activity upon expression of Bcl11b. Binding of mutant Bcl11b<sup>HM</sup> protein to such intronic region suggest that the C-terminal zinc-finger motif in Bcl11b is necessary to close P1-promoter region after Bcl11b binding to putative regulatory element(s). Alternatively, Bcl11b may be involved indirectly in the <italic>Sth</italic>-independent <italic>Thpok</italic> repression through an uncharacterized intermediate factor, however, the similar gene expression profiles between wild-type and <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m/m</italic></sup> precursors disfavors this possibility.</p><p id="Par24">De-repression of <italic>Thpok</italic> in mature CD8<sup>+</sup> populations that emerge from <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>fl/fl</italic></sup>
<italic>:Cd4-Cre</italic> precursors suggests that Bcl11b is required also for <italic>Sth</italic>-mediated <italic>Thpok</italic> repression. Thus, Bcll1b regulates <italic>Thpok</italic> repression by both <italic>Sth</italic>-independent and <italic>Sth</italic>-dependent mechanisms. Based on our data, we presume that Bcl11b acts initially to inhibit P1-promoter activity in an <italic>Sth</italic>-independent manner. Either sequentially or simultaneously, Bcl11b primes three T cell specific regulatory regions, <italic>Sth</italic> and two enhancers, <italic>TE</italic> and <italic>PE</italic>. Upon such priming, <italic>Sth</italic> initiates to suppress <italic>TE</italic> and <italic>PE</italic> activity, thereby removal of <italic>Sth</italic> results in <italic>Thpok</italic> de-repression in Bcl11b-sufficent precursors in which <italic>TE</italic>/<italic>PE</italic> enhancers also becomes functional after Bcl11b-mediated priming. In this regard, an <italic>Sth</italic>-independent mechanism alone is likely to be insufficient for extinguishing <italic>TE</italic>/<italic>PE</italic> enhancer activities. Thus, we assume that pre-conditioning of T cell specific regulatory regions by Bcl11b is an essential process for dissecting TCR signals that arise from engagement by distinct MHCs, and for converting them into establishment of &#x0201c;on&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;off&#x0201d; <italic>Thpok</italic> expression status for inducing helper- or cytotoxic-fate via inactivation or maintaining <italic>Sth</italic> activity, respectively.</p><p id="Par25">Bcl11b similarly primes the <italic>Foxp3</italic> locus for later activation upon exposure to agonistic selection signals<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>. A recent study showed that the pioneering enhancer, CNS3<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>, confers a poised state to the <italic>Foxp3</italic> promoter in precursor cells in response to TCR stimuli<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. In the present study, we show that binding of SATB1 to CNS3 in precursors, an essential process for activation of <italic>Foxp3</italic> gene in the thymus<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>, requires Bcl11b-mediated priming before transition to the DP stage. Whether common Bcl11b-mediated mechanisms operate to prime the <italic>Thpok</italic> and <italic>Foxp3</italic> loci remains unclear; however, we establish that the C-terminal zinc-finger motif of Bcl11b is involved in both processes. Collectively, our results reveal a set of novel functions for the T-lineage commitment factor Bcl11b, which &#x0201c;pre-conditions&#x0201d; precursors for integration of environmental cues, specifically TCR signals, into a developmental program that dissects effector lineages and shapes the primary T cell pool.</p><p id="Par26">Another striking finding from our studies is that the lack of Bcl11b inhibits both the positive and negative regulatory regions near <italic>Thpok</italic>. One possible model to explain how Bcl11b controls multiple regulatory regions would be its function as a scaffold to facilitate communication between the distal elements and the <italic>Thpok</italic> promoters. Using insertion ChIP technology<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>, we recently observed that the <italic>Sth</italic> and <italic>PE</italic> regions were positioned in close proximity during differentiation into CD8-lineage cells (I.T. manuscript in preparation). Thus, it is possible that Bcl11b is involved in shaping promoter-regulatory elements communications on the <italic>Thpok</italic> locus.</p><p id="Par27">Contrary to <italic>Thpok</italic> regulation, Bcl11b is merely involved in repression of <italic>Runx3</italic> in CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. Prior studies invoked an indirect mechanism for <italic>Runx3</italic> repression by ThPOK via the induction of SOCS family proteins<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>. However, our finding that ThPOK associates with functional <italic>Runx3</italic> enhancers raises the possibility that ThPOK directly antagonizes enhancer function. Indeed, ThPOK bound to the enhancers even in Bcl11b-deficient cells that were de-repressing <italic>Runx3</italic> albeit normal level of <italic>Socs</italic> family gene expression. These data suggest that the antagonistic action of ThPOK against <italic>Runx3</italic> expression requires Bcl11b after its binding to the <italic>Runx3</italic> enhancers. It is conceivable that Bcl11b assists ThPOK in preventing the formation of looping between the enhancers and the P1-Runx3 promoter. Nevertheless, it will be important in future studies to examine whether lineage-specific chromatin structures are formed in <italic>Thpok</italic> and <italic>Runx3</italic> loci and whether Bcl11b regulates these topologies.</p><p id="Par28">The C<sub>2</sub>H<sub>2</sub> zinc-finger motif not only serves as a DNA binding domain that recognizes specific sequences, but also as a docking module for RNA and proteins<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>. We found that the Bcl11b<sup>HM</sup> protein retains its ability to associate with regulatory regions, indicating that its final zinc finger is dispensable for DNA binding. However, it remains possible that the other four zinc-fingers domains have compensatory functions in this regard. There are two zinc-fingers clusters in mammalian Bcl11 family proteins, double zinc-fingers in its central portion and a trio of zinc-fingers at its C-terminus. Although there are Bcl11-related proteins in lower species that lacks the central dual zinc-finger domain, a trio of zinc-fingers at the C-terminus is evolutionally well conserved. Our results indicate that this domain is essential for gene regulation, presumably through modulating topological structures. Bcl11a has been shown to play a key role in the switch from fetal &#x003b3;- to adult &#x003b2;-globin in human<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup>. It is conceivable that common Bcl11 family-dependent mechanisms play a key role in developmentally programmed switching of regulatory regions by modulating topological structures through the C-terminal triplet zinc-finger stretch. Isolation of interacting molecules with it will further elucidate regulatory mechanism by Bcl11 family.</p></sec><sec id="Sec11" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec12"><title>Mice</title><p id="Par29">
<italic>Runx1</italic>
<sup><italic>&#x00394;446</italic></sup> mice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>, <italic>Runx3</italic>
<sup><italic>fl</italic></sup> mice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup>, <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>+/&#x02212;</italic></sup> mice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>, <italic>Thpok</italic>
<sup><italic>gfp</italic></sup> mice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>, <italic>Thpok</italic>
<sup><italic>gfp:241-401RM</italic></sup> mice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup> and <italic>Thpok</italic> transgenic mice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> have been described. <italic>Lck-Cre</italic> mice, and <italic>Cd4-Cre</italic> mice were from Dr J. Takeda, and Dr C. Wilson, respectively. &#x003b2;2m-deficient mice (stock No:002070), Rag1-deficient mice (Stock No:002216) were from Jackson laboratory, and I-A&#x003b2; deficient mice and <italic>Il2rg</italic>
<sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup>:<italic>Rag1</italic>
<sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> were from Taconic. In order to generate a <italic>Thpok</italic>
<sup><italic>gfp:&#x00394;TESPE</italic></sup> allele, <italic>TE/Sth</italic> and <italic>PE</italic> regions were sequentially removed from the <italic>Thpok</italic>
<sup><italic>gfp</italic></sup> reporter allele by using homologous recombination in ES cells. In order to construct the target vector for <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>fl</italic></sup> allele, genomic fragment isolated from the phage library (Stratagene) was used as starting material. The neomycin-resistance gene (<italic>neo</italic>
<sup><italic>r</italic></sup>) flanked with two loxP sequences was cut out from <italic>pL2-Neo(2)</italic> vector and thymidine kinase (TK) gene was isolated from pNT vector. A 5&#x02032; short homology region was amplified by PCR and was ligated with the <italic>neo</italic>
<sup><italic>r</italic></sup> fragment, followed by sequential ligation to add 3&#x02032; homology region. The third loxP sequences placed in the 3&#x02032; untranslated region (UTR) were derived from synthetic oligo-nucleotide. The single nucleotide deletion that causes a frameshift mutation in the <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m</italic></sup> allele was accidentally incorporated into the target vector at some point during above sequential ligation steps. To construct a real target vector for <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>fl</italic></sup> mutation, correct exon 4 sequences were replaced in the <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m</italic></sup> target vector. A fragment that harbors the identical <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m</italic></sup> single nucleotide deletion but lacks the third loxP sequences was used to construct the target vector for <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>HM</italic></sup> allele. In order to generate <italic>Runx3</italic>
<sup><italic>tdTomato</italic></sup> reporter allele, we constructed the targeting vector by replacing YFP cDNA fragment with cDNA fragment encoding tdTomato fluorescent protein in pRx31-KIN cassette vector<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>, which was used to generate the <italic>Runx3</italic>
<sup><italic>YFP</italic></sup> allele<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. Those targeting vectors were transfected into M1 ES cells as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. ES clones underwent homologous recombination were identified by PCR with appropriate primers sets. In order to delete &#x02212;39&#x02009;kb and &#x02212;21&#x02009;kb genomic regions from the <italic>Runx3</italic>
<sup><italic>tdTomato</italic></sup> reporter allele by CRISPR/Cas9 technology<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>, we selected two single guide RNA (sgRNA) target sequences that flanks target genomic regions, which were shown in Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>. Custom sgRNA, in which CRISPR RNAs was fused to a normally trans-encoded tracrRNA, were transcribed from a T7 promoter in the <italic>pUC18</italic> vector by in vitro transcription with MEGAshortscript T7 kit (Life Technologies, AM1354) and both the Cas9 mRNA and the sgRNAs were purified using MEGAclear kit (Life Technologies, AM1908). The sgRNAs and mRNA encoding Cas9 were co-injected into cytoplasm of fertilized eggs that were prepared by in vitro fertilization with <italic>Runx3</italic>
<sup><italic>tdTomato/tdTomato</italic></sup> sperm and wild-type oocytes. Cas9-mediated double-stranded DNA breaks resolved by non-homologous end joining (NHEJ) ablated the intervening sequences. Founder offspring that had deletion of the target genome region were crossed to wild-type mice, and F1 founders that harbor both deletion mutation and <italic>Runx3</italic>
<sup><italic>tdTomato</italic></sup> allele were selected for establishing mouse line and were analyzed. In order to generate allele harboring double deletions at &#x02212;39&#x02009;kb and &#x02212;21&#x02009;kb regions, sgRNA pair used for generation of <italic>Runx3</italic>
<sup><italic>&#x00394;21E</italic></sup> mutation were injected into eggs obtained by in vitro fertilization between <italic>Runx3</italic>
<sup><italic>tdTomato:&#x00394;39LD/+</italic></sup> sperm and wild-type oocytes. RNA injection was performed by the Animal Facility Group at RIKEN, IMS. All mice were maintained in the specific pathogen free animal facility at the RIKEN IMS, and all animal procedures were in accordance with institutional guidelines for animal care and with the protocol (28-017) approved by the safety section in RIKEN Yokohama Campus.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>DNA pull-down assay</title><p id="Par30">In order to analyze binding of Bcl11b to <italic>Thpok</italic> silencer (<italic>Sth</italic>) core sequences in vitro, nuclear extract was prepared from 10&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>7</sup> total thymocytes and were mixed with 10&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of biotin-labeled synthetic oligo-nucleotides probe (Eurofins Genomics) in 400&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of affinity purification (AP) buffer (20&#x02009;mM HEPES-KOH (pH 7.5), 80&#x02009;mM KCl, 10% Glycerol, 0.1% Triton X, 0.5&#x02009;mM PMSF, 1&#x000d7; cOmplete protease inhibitor Cocktail tablets (Roche)) on ice for 3&#x02009;h, followed by mixture with 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of Dynabeads M-280 Streptavidin (Thermo Fisher Scientific) for additional 3&#x02009;h on ice. After one time wash with AP buffer, beads were incubated with 500&#x02009;pmol of mutant non-labeled oligo-nucleotide for 30&#x02009;min at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, and were washed with AP buffer three times. Captured protein complexes by beads were then released into 50&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of SDS sample buffer and were applied for western blot analyses. Sequences for oligo-nucleotides probes used were as follows:</p><p id="Par31">Wt:5&#x02032;-TGGCAGCCACCGCCTCTTCAGGTGGGTTGGGCGGTCGCGGTAGGGGTTCTGGGGGGCGGCGGGAGGGAGGGGGCTGCGGTCTGAG-3&#x02032;</p><p id="Par32">Mutant:5&#x02032;-TGGCAGCCACCGCCTCTTCAGCACCCATGGGCGCAGGCGGTAGGGGTTCTGGGGGGCGGCGGGAGGGAGGGGGCACGCCACTGAG-3&#x02032;.</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Co-immune precipitation and western blot</title><p id="Par33">Nuclear extract was prepared from 10&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>6</sup> total thymocytes with NE-PER kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific) in the presence of cOmplete protease inhibitor cocktail tablets (Roche), followed by incubation with 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of anti-Bc111b (A300-383A, Bethyl Laboratories) antibody, which was pre-mixed with 50&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of Dynabeads ProteinA, overnight at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C with gentle rotation. Antibody bound proteins were released into 20&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of SDS sample buffer and was loaded onto SDS-PAGE gel. In western blot, anti-Runx1 serum<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup> and antibodies that reacts with N-terminal sequences (A300-383A, Bethyl Laboratories) and C-terminal sequences (A300-385A, Bethyl Laboratories) of Bcl11b were used to detect protein.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Chromatin immunoprecipitation</title><p id="Par34">For ChIP-seq, 3&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>7</sup> thymocytes that were freshly prepared from C57BL/6 mice at 4&#x02212;6 weeks old were washed once with PBS supplemented with 1% FCS, cOmplete protease inhibitor cocktail (Roche) and 1&#x02009;mM 4-(2-Aminoethyl) benzenesulfonyl fluoride hydrochloride (Sigma-Aldrich), and were cross-linked by incubation in a 1% paraformaldehyde solution for 10&#x02009;min with gentle rotation at RT. The reaction was stopped by addition of glycine to 0.15&#x02009;M. Cells were then washed with ice-cold PBS containing 1% FCS for 10&#x02009;min with gentle rotation at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C, and were lysed in Lysis Buffer 1 (50&#x02009;mM HEPES pH 7.5, 140&#x02009;mM NaCl, 1&#x02009;mM EDTA, 10% Glycerol, 0.5% NP-40, 0.25% Triton X-100) supplemented with cOmplete protease inhibitor cocktail tablets (Roche) for 10&#x02009;min at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C with gentle rotation. Nuclei were pelleted and were washed by Lysis Buffer 2 (10&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0, 200&#x02009;mM NaCl, 1&#x02009;mM EDTA and 0.5&#x02009;mM EGTA) supplemented with cOmplete protease inhibitor (Roche). Pelleted chromatin was resuspended in 300&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of Lysis Buffer 3 (10&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0, 100&#x02009;mM NaCl, 1&#x02009;mM EDTA, 0.5&#x02009;mM EGTA, 0.1% Sodium deoxycholate and 0.5% N-laurylsarcosine sodium salt), and was sonicated using a model XL2000 ultrasonic cell disruptor (MICROSON) at output level 6 for 15&#x02009;s for 10 times. After removing debris by centrifugation, 30&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of 10% Triton X-100 (Nacalai tesque) was added to 270&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of supernatant (final 1%) and sonicated chromatin was incubated overnight at 4&#x02009;&#x000b0;C with 5&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of anti-Bcl11b rabbit polyclonal antibody (A300-383A, Bethyl Laboratories) that was pre-conjugated with 50&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of Dynabeads M-280 Sheep anti-Rabbit IgG (Thermo Fisher Scientific). After washing beads with ChIP-RIPA (50&#x02009;mM HEPES (pH 7.6), 500&#x02009;mM LiCl, 1&#x02009;mM EDTA, 1% NP-40, 0.7% sodium deoxycholate) and TE buffer supplemented with 50&#x02009;mM NaCl, immunoprecipitates were eluted from beads into 100&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of elution buffer (50&#x02009;mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0, 10&#x02009;mM EDTA, 1% SDS) by incubation for 15&#x02009;min at 65&#x02009;&#x000b0;C with vigorous shaking. Eluted immunoprecipitates were then incubated at 65&#x02009;&#x000b0;C overnight for reverse-crosslinking. Input DNA and ChIP DNA were treated with RNAse A (Thermo Fisher Scientific) at 37&#x02009;&#x000b0;C for 1&#x02009;h, followed by incubation with Proteinase K (Thermo Fisher Scientific) at 55&#x02009;&#x000b0;C in the presence of 6&#x02009;mM CaCl<sub>2</sub> for one hour. DNA was purified by Phenol/Chloroform extraction for ChIP-seq or ChIP DNA Clean and Concentrator kit (ZYMO RESEARCH) for ChIP-qPCR. For ChIP-seq analysis, purified DNA was subjected to re-sonication with a Covaris S220 to produce DNA fragments with an average size of 200&#x02009;bp, and was used for library construction with NEBNext ChIP-seq Library Prep Master Mix set for Illumina Kit (NEB). Sequencing was performed by the RIKEN IMS sequence facility with Illumina HiSeq 1500 or at Hiroshima University using a GAIIx (illumina). To detect ThPOK binding regions in the murine <italic>Runx3</italic> locus, we performed ChIP-on-chip experiment. Chromatin DNA isolated from 10&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>6</sup> CD4<sup>+</sup> SP thymocytes from FH-ThPOK mice<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup> was immunoprecipitated with anti-Flag (M2; Sigma-Aldrich), and were hybridized against custom microarrays generated by Agilent that tiled through the murine <italic>Runx3</italic> locus up to &#x02009;~&#x02009;565&#x02009;kb upstream and &#x02009;~&#x02009;66&#x02009;kb downstream by means of 60-nucleotide probes. Probe hybridization and scanning of oligo-nucleotide array data were done according to manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol (Agilent). For analytical ChIP, we used 5&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of rabbit anti-Bcl11b antibody (A300-383A, Bethyl Laboratories), 5&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of rabbit anti-ThPOK polyclonal antibody<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup> and 5&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of rabbit anti-SATB1 polyclonal antibody (ab70004, Abcam). Quantitative PCR was performed using the StepOnePlus Real-Time PCR system (Applied Biosystems) with SYBR Green detection system. Primers sequences for quantitative PCR are listed in the Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Flow cytometry analyses</title><p id="Par35">Thymus, spleen, and lymph nodes were removed from mice at 4&#x02212;8 weeks of age, and were mashed through a 70&#x02009;&#x003bc;m cell strainer to make single-cell suspensions. Cells were stained with following antibodies purchased from BD-Bioscience: CD4 (RM4-5), CD8 (53-6.7), CD24 (M1/69), CD25 (PC61), CD154 (MR1), IL1RL1 (DJ8), ScaI (E13-161.7), KLRG1 (2F1), and TCR&#x003b2; (H57-597). Foxp3 staining buffer Set (00-5523-00) and anti-mouse FoxP3 antibody (FJK-16s) from affymetirx eBioscience was used to stain Foxp3. Antibodies were used at a concentration of 2.5&#x02009;&#x003bc;g&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Multi-color flow cytometry analysis was performed using a FACSCANTO II (BD-Bioscience) and data were analyzed using FlowJo (Tree Star) software. Cell subsets were sorted using a FACSAria II (BD Biosciences) by cell sorting facility at RIKEN IMS.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>In vitro T cell culture</title><p id="Par36">Purified T cells were cultured in custom ordered Dulbecco&#x02019;s Modified Eagle Medium (D-MEM, KOHJIN BIO) supplemented with 10% heat inactivated FBS (Hyclone). 1.0&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>6</sup> cells were stimulated in 24-well plates pre-coated with 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>anti-CD3e antibody (553058, BD Bioscience) with 2&#x02009;&#x003bc;g&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> soluble anti-CD28 antibody (553295, BD Bioscience) for two days. For induction of Treg differentiation, 10&#x02009;ng&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> TGF&#x003b2;1 (7666-MB, R&#x00026;D systems), 5&#x02009;&#x003bc;g&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> anti-IL4 (554433, BD Biosciences) and 5&#x02009;&#x003bc;g&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> anti-IFN&#x003b3; (554409, BD Biosciences) were added throughout the culture.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Reconstitution of T cell development in host mice</title><p id="Par37">Total liver cells with either <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>+/+</italic></sup> or <italic>Bcl11b</italic>
<sup><italic>m/m</italic></sup> genotype were prepared from 13.5 to 14.5 dpc embryos, and were suspended in 400&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of D-MEM supplemented with 10% heat inactivated FBS (Hyclone). 200&#x02009;&#x003bc;l of these fetal liver cells were intravenously injected into sub-lethally irradiated (6.5&#x02009;Gy, Gammacell 40 Exactor, MDS Nordion) Rag1-deficeint or I-A&#x003b2; deficient mice that expressing Ly9.1. For ILC2 reconstitution, <italic>Il2rg</italic>
<sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup>:<italic>Rag1</italic>
<sup>&#x02013;/&#x02013;</sup> mice were used as recipients. Host mice were supplied with antibiotics (1&#x02009;mg&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> neomycin and 100&#x02009;unit&#x02009;ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> polymyxin B) containing water for first 2 weeks, and were analyzed 8 weeks after the fetal liver cell injection. In I-A&#x003b2; deficient host mice, donor derived lymphocytes were identified as Ly9.1-negative cells.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>RNA isolation, RT-qPCR and RNA-seq</title><p id="Par38">After total cellular RNA extraction by using Trizol reagent (Thermo Fisher Scientific), samples were incubated with RNase-free DNase I (Thermo Fisher Scientific) before cDNA synthesis with the SuperScriptIII First Strand Synthesis System (Invitrogen). Quantitative RT-PCR was performed using the StepOnePlus Real-Time PCR system (Applied Biosystems) with an internal fluorescent TaqMan probe, Universal ProbeLibrary (Roche) or SYBR Green detection system. Primers sequences and probe sequences for quantitative RT-PCR are listed in the Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">2</xref>. Primer sequence to measure total <italic>Thpok</italic> mRNA was previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. For RNA-seq analyses, purified 1.0&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>6</sup> cells were used to prepare mRNA and 200&#x02212;300&#x02009;ng total RNA were used for the library construction with SureSelect Strand Specific RNA-Seq LibraryPreparation kit (Agilent Technologies) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol. Sequencing was performed by genomics facility at RIKEN IMS with Illumina HiSeq 1500.</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Assay of transposase-accessible chromatin sequencing</title><p id="Par39">Assay of transposase-accessible chromatin sequencing (ATAC-seq) samples were prepared from 25,000 sorted cells. The transposase reactions were carried as previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup> with 12 or 13 total PCR cycles. Amplified DNA fragments were purified with QIAGEN MinElute PCR Purification Kit and size-selected twice with Agencourt AMPure XP. Libraries were quantified with KAPA Library Quantification Kit for Illumina Sequencing Platforms (KAPA Biosystems), and size distribution was checked on a Bioanalyzer (Agilent High Sensitivity DNA chip, Agilent Technologies). Libraries were sequenced on Illumina HiSeq 2500.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Retroviral transduction into T cells and T cell culture</title><p id="Par40">Retroviral vectors encoding Cre recombinase or ThPOK in pMSCV-GFP vector was previously described<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>. Retroviral vectors encoding mutant Bcl11b proteins were generated by insertion of corresponding cDNA into pMSCV-GFP vector after conformation of sequences of PCR amplified fragment. Those vectors were transfected into Plat-E packaging line (a gift from Dr T. Kitamura at the University of Tokyo) by FuGENE6 Reagent (Promega, E2691) and supernatant collected two days after transfection were used for transduction into activated T cells by in vitro TCR stimulation with immobilized anti-CD3 and soluble anti-CD28 by spin infection at 2400&#x02009;r.p.m. for 60&#x02009;min in the presence of 4&#x02009;&#x003bc;g of polybrene (Sigma-Aldrich). Transdcuced T cells were identified according to GFP expression for FACS analyses and RNA extraction.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Data and statistical analyses</title><p id="Par41">Sequences retrieved in ChIP-seq experiments and ATAC-seq were aligned on the mouse genome (mm9) using the bowtie2 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bowtie-bio.sourceforge.net/index.shtml">http://bowtie-bio.sourceforge.net/index.shtml</ext-link>) with default parameters, and accumulated reads were normalized using total mapped reads. RNA-seq reads were mapped using tophat2 (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ccb.jhu.edu/software/tophat/index.shtml">https://ccb.jhu.edu/software/tophat/index.shtml</ext-link>) to the mouse genome and gene expression was estimated with fragments per mapped reads per kilobase (FPKM) values calculated using cufflinks (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cole-trapnell-lab.github.io/cufflinks/">http://cole-trapnell-lab.github.io/cufflinks/</ext-link>) and gene annotation provided by iGenome. Primary component analysis (PCA) was carried out using our in-house program with FPKM values of gene sets whose annotation was provided by Gene Ontology database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://geneontology.org/">http://geneontology.org/</ext-link>). Statistical analysis was performed by F-test and unpaired <italic>t</italic>-test with or without Welch&#x02019;s correction using using GraphPAd Prism6 (Graphpad software). Figures display means and SD.</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Comparative genomics analyses</title><p id="Par42">Homologous sequences of Bcl11 family were searched with human Bcl11b protein sequences as a query against sequences listed at the Ensemble genome browser 85 and Genebank with &#x0201c;TBLASTN&#x0201d; algorithm. As for the Japanese lamprey search, Bcl11 protein sequences for human, mouse, and elephant shark were used as queries to search the Japanese lamprey genome assembly (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://jlampreygenome.imcb.a-star.edu.sg/">http://jlampreygenome.imcb.a-star.edu.sg/</ext-link>) with &#x0201c;TBLASTN&#x0201d; algorithm. Genomic regions that showed high similarity were extracted and searched against the non-redundant protein database at NCBI to confirm their identity. Alignments of C-terminal sequences of Bcl11b orthologue of each species were performed by a computer program Clustal Omega (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.clustal.org/omega/">http://www.clustal.org/omega/</ext-link>) with default options for amino acid sequences using zinc-finger regions obtained proposed by BLASTP algorithm and NCBI conserved domain database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Structure/cdd/wrpsb.cgi">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Structure/cdd/wrpsb.cgi</ext-link>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Data availability</title><p id="Par43">RNA-seq, ChIP-seq and ATAC-seq data that support the findings of this study have been deposited with accession GSE90134, GSE90949, and GSE90989, respectively. All other relevant data are available from the authors.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><sec id="Sec25"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41467_2017_768_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary information</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="41467_2017_768_MOESM2_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Peer Review File</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Electronic supplementary material</bold></p><p>
<bold>Supplementary Information</bold> accompanies this paper at doi:10.1038/s41467-017-00768-1.</p></fn><fn><p>
<bold>Publisher's note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank C. Miyamoto and R. Chihara for mouse genotyping, N. Yoza for cell sorting, T. Ishikura for ES cell aggregation, Y. Iizuka for microinjection of RNA for CRISPR/Cas9 mediated genome editing. We are grateful to Dr Thomas Boehm for helpful suggestion on analyses of lamprey genome and Dr Eugene Oltz for critical reading of the manuscript. This work was supported by JSPS KAKENHI Grant Number JP 21229008 (I.T.), JP 26293109 (I.T.) and JP 22021045 (I.T.), the Uehara Memorial Foundation (I.T.), Takeda Science Foundation (I.T.) the National Institutes of Health grant R01AI 097244-01A1 (T.E.).</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>S.K., H.T., W.S., K.K., Y.N., and I.T. performed experiments for phenotypic characterization of <italic>Bcl11b</italic> mutant mice. M.T. and K.M. performed reconstitution experiments. S.M. isolated ES cell clones. T.A.E. performed statistical and comparative genomics analyses. K.N. made mutant Bcl11b expression vectors. S.K., A.K., and T.I. performed sequencing of ChIP libraries. T.E. provided anti-ThPOK antibody. Y.L. and A.M. performed ATAC-seq. B.V. analyzed Japanese lamprey genome. Y.K. and R.K. provided <italic>Bcl11b</italic> germline KO mice. I.T. designed experiments, interpreted data and wrote the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar1"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par44">The authors declare no competing financial interests.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yui</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothenberg</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Developmental gene networks: a triathlon on the course to T cell identity</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Immunol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>529</fpage><lpage>545</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nri3702</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25060579?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25060579</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeremiah Bell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhandoola</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>T-cell lineage determination</article-title><source>Immunol. Rev.</source><year>2010</year><volume>238</volume><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-065X.2010.00956.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20969581?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20969581</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Leid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rothenberg</surname><given-names>EV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An early T cell lineage commitment checkpoint dependent on the transcription factor Bcl11b</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2010</year><volume>329</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>93</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1188989</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20595614?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20595614</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ikawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>An essential developmental checkpoint for production of the T cell lineage</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2010</year><volume>329</volume><fpage>93</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1188995</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20595615?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20595615</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Reprogramming of T cells to natural killer-like cells upon Bcl11b deletion</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2010</year><volume>329</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>89</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1188063</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20538915?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20538915</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kueh</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Asynchronous combinatorial action of four regulatory factors activates Bcl11b for T cell commitment</article-title><source>Nat. Immunol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>956</fpage><lpage>965</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni.3514</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27376470?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27376470</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Albu</surname><given-names>DI</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcription factor Bcl11b controls selection of invariant natural killer T-cells by regulating glycolipid presentation in double-positive thymocytes</article-title><source>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2011</year><volume>108</volume><fpage>6211</fpage><lpage>6216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1014304108</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21444811?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21444811</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vanvalkenburgh</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Critical role of Bcl11b in suppressor function of T regulatory cells and prevention of inflammatory bowel disease</article-title><source>J. Exp. Med.</source><year>2011</year><volume>208</volume><fpage>2069</fpage><lpage>2081</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20102683</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21875956?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21875956</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Bcl11b is essential for group 2 innate lymphoid cell development</article-title><source>J. Exp. Med.</source><year>2015</year><volume>212</volume><fpage>875</fpage><lpage>882</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20142224</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25964370?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25964370</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The transcription factor Bcl11b is specifically expressed in group 2 innate lymphoid cells and is essential for their development</article-title><source>J. Exp. Med.</source><year>2015</year><volume>212</volume><fpage>865</fpage><lpage>874</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20142318</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25964371?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25964371</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Califano</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcription factor Bcl11b controls identity and function of mature type 2 innate lymphoid cells</article-title><source>Immunity</source><year>2015</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>354</fpage><lpage>368</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2015.07.005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26231117?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26231117</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hogquist</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jameson</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The self-obsession of T cells: how TCR signaling thresholds affect fate &#x02018;decisions&#x02019; and effector function</article-title><source>Nat. Immunol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>815</fpage><lpage>823</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni.2938</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25137456?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25137456</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Adoro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lineage fate and intense debate: myths, models and mechanisms of CD4- versus CD8-lineage choice</article-title><source>Nat. Rev. Immunol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>788</fpage><lpage>801</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nri2416</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18802443?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18802443</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taniuchi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Ellmeier</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional and epigenetic regulation of CD4/CD8 lineage choice</article-title><source>Adv. Immunol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-387663-8.00003-X</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21762816?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21762816</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ellmeier</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Taniuchi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of BTB-zinc finger transcription factors during T cell development and in the regulation of T cell-mediated immunity</article-title><source>Curr. Top Microb. Immunol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>381</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>49</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The zinc finger transcription factor Th-POK regulates CD4 versus CD8 T-cell lineage commitment</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2005</year><volume>433</volume><fpage>826</fpage><lpage>833</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature03338</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15729333?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15729333</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The zinc finger protein cKrox directs CD4 lineage differentiation during intrathymic T cell positive selection</article-title><source>Nat. Immunol.</source><year>2005</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>381</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni1183</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15750595?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15750595</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kappes</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of ThPOK in control of CD4/CD8 lineage commitment</article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Immunol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>295</fpage><lpage>320</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.immunol.25.022106.141715</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20307210?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20307210</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Setoguchi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Repression of the transcription factor Th-POK by Runx complexes in cytotoxic T cell development</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2008</year><volume>319</volume><fpage>822</fpage><lpage>825</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1151844</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18258917?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18258917</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>He</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>CD4-CD8 lineage commitment is regulated by a silencer element at the ThPOK transcription-factor locus</article-title><source>Immunity</source><year>2008</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>346</fpage><lpage>358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2008.02.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18342007?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18342007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muroi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Miyamoto</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Taniuchi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cutting edge: fine-tuning of Thpok gene activation by an enhancer in close proximity to its own silencer</article-title><source>J. Immunol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>190</volume><fpage>1397</fpage><lpage>1401</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.1203006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23315079?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23315079</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Muroi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cascading suppression of transcriptional silencers by ThPOK seals helper T cell fate</article-title><source>Nat. Immunol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1113</fpage><lpage>1121</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni.1650</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18776907?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18776907</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakaguchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The zinc-finger protein MAZR is part of the transcription factor network that controls the CD4 versus CD8 lineage fate of double-positive thymocytes</article-title><source>Nat. Immunol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>442</fpage><lpage>448</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni.1860</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20383150?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20383150</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sakaguchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>MAZR and runx factors synergistically repress ThPOK during CD8+T cell lineage development</article-title><source>J. Immunol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>195</volume><fpage>2879</fpage><lpage>2887</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.1500387</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26254341?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26254341</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Distinct functions for the transcription factors GATA-3 and ThPOK during intrathymic differentiation of CD4&#x02009;+&#x02009;T cells</article-title><source>Nat. Immunol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1122</fpage><lpage>1130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni.1647</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18776904?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18776904</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Steinke</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>TCF-1 and LEF-1 act upstream of Th-POK to promote the CD4<sup>+</sup> T cell fate and interact with Runx3 to silence Cd4 in CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells</article-title><source>Nat. Immunol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>646</fpage><lpage>656</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni.2897</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24836425?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24836425</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Egawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Littman</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ThPOK acts late in specification of the helper T cell lineage and suppresses Runx-mediated commitment to the cytotoxic T cell lineage</article-title><source>Nat. Immunol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1131</fpage><lpage>1139</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni.1652</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18776905?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18776905</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Signaling by intrathymic cytokines, not T cell antigen receptors, specifies CD8 lineage choice and promotes the differentiation of cytotoxic-lineage T cells</article-title><source>Nat. Immunol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>257</fpage><lpage>264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni.1840</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20118929?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20118929</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luckey</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The transcription factor ThPOK suppresses Runx3 and imposes CD4+ lineage fate by inducing the SOCS suppressors of cytokine signaling</article-title><source>Nat. Immunol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>638</fpage><lpage>645</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni.2917</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24880459?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24880459</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taniuchi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Views on helper/cytotoxic lineage choice from a bottom-up approach</article-title><source>Immunol. Rev.</source><year>2016</year><volume>271</volume><fpage>98</fpage><lpage>113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/imr.12401</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27088909?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27088909</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kastner</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Bcl11b represses a mature T-cell gene expression program in immature CD4+CD8+thymocytes</article-title><source>Eur. J. Immunol.</source><year>2010</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>2143</fpage><lpage>2154</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/eji.200940258</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20544728?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20544728</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seo</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Roles of VWRPY motif-mediated gene repression by Runx proteins during T-cell development</article-title><source>Immunol. Cell Biol.</source><year>2012</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>827</fpage><lpage>830</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/icb.2012.6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22370763?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22370763</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PU.1 is a major downstream target of AML1 (RUNX1) in adult mouse hematopoiesis</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><year>2008</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>60</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.2007.7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17994017?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17994017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide identification of Bcl11b gene targets reveals role in brain-derived neurotrophic factor signaling</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>e23691</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0023691</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21912641?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21912641</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Epigenetic Thpok silencing limits the time window to choose CD4+helper-lineage fate in the thymus</article-title><source>EMBO J.</source><year>2013</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>1183</fpage><lpage>1194</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/emboj.2013.47</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23481257?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23481257</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wakabayashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Bcl11b is required for differentiation and survival of alphabeta T lymphocytes</article-title><source>Nat. Immunol.</source><year>2003</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>533</fpage><lpage>539</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni927</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12717433?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12717433</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buenrostro</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Giresi</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaba</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenleaf</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transposition of native chromatin for fast and sensitive epigenomic profiling of open chromatin, DNA-binding proteins and nucleosome position</article-title><source>Nat. Methods</source><year>2013</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1213</fpage><lpage>1218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.2688</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24097267?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24097267</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The zinc finger transcription factor Zbtb7b represses CD8-lineage gene expression in peripheral CD4&#x02009;+&#x02009;T cells</article-title><source>Immunity</source><year>2008</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>876</fpage><lpage>887</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2008.09.019</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19062319?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19062319</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zetsche</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cpf1 is a single RNA-guided endonuclease of a class 2 CRISPR-Cas system</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2015</year><volume>163</volume><fpage>759</fpage><lpage>771</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2015.09.038</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26422227?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26422227</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jenkinson</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Expression of the transcription factor cKrox in peripheral CD8 T cells reveals substantial postthymic plasticity in CD4-CD8 lineage differentiation</article-title><source>J. Exp. Med.</source><year>2007</year><volume>204</volume><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20061982</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17296789?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17296789</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kakugawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Essential roles of SATB1 in specifying T lymphocyte subsets</article-title><source>Cell Rep.</source><year>2017</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1176</fpage><lpage>1188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.celrep.2017.04.038</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28494867?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28494867</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A mechanism for expansion of regulatory T-cell repertoire and its role in self-tolerance</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2015</year><volume>528</volume><fpage>132</fpage><lpage>136</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/528S132a</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26605529?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26605529</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Role of conserved non-coding DNA elements in the Foxp3 gene in regulatory T-cell fate</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2010</year><volume>463</volume><fpage>808</fpage><lpage>812</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature08750</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20072126?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20072126</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kitagawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Guidance of regulatory T cell development by Satb1-dependent super-enhancer establishment</article-title><source>Nat. Immunol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni.3646</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27992401?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27992401</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>HO</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Disregulated expression of the transcription factor ThPOK during T-cell development leads to high incidence of T-cell lymphomas</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2015</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>7773</fpage><lpage>7778</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1424104112</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26056302?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26056302</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kronenberg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudensky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of immunity by self-reactive T cells</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2005</year><volume>435</volume><fpage>598</fpage><lpage>604</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature03725</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15931212?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15931212</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fujita</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fujii</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Direct identification of insulator components by insertional chromatin immunoprecipitation</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2011</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>e26109</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0026109</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22043306?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22043306</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Iuchi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Three classes of C2H2 zinc finger proteins</article-title><source>Cell Mol. Life Sci.</source><year>2001</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>625</fpage><lpage>635</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/PL00000885</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11361095?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11361095</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sankaran</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Developmental and species-divergent globin switching are driven by BCL11A</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2009</year><volume>460</volume><fpage>1093</fpage><lpage>1097</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature08243</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19657335?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19657335</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nishimura</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>VWRPY motif-dependent and -independent roles of AML1/Runx1 transcription factor in murine hematopoietic development</article-title><source>Blood</source><year>2004</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>562</fpage><lpage>570</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2003-06-2109</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 14504086?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14504086</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naoe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Repression of interleukin-4 in T helper type 1 cells by Runx/Cbf beta binding to the Il4 silencer</article-title><source>J. Exp. Med.</source><year>2007</year><volume>204</volume><fpage>1749</fpage><lpage>1755</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20062456</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17646405?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17646405</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mali</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>RNA-guided human genome engineering via Cas9</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2013</year><volume>339</volume><fpage>823</fpage><lpage>826</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1232033</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23287722?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23287722</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>One-step generation of mice carrying mutations in multiple genes by CRISPR/Cas-mediated genome engineering</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>2013</year><volume>153</volume><fpage>910</fpage><lpage>918</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cell.2013.04.025</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23643243?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23643243</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Egawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Tillman</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Naoe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Taniuchi</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Littman</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of the Runx transcription factors in thymocyte differentiation and in homeostasis of naive T cells</article-title><source>J. Exp. Med.</source><year>2007</year><volume>204</volume><fpage>1945</fpage><lpage>1957</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20070133</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17646406?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17646406</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buenrostro</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>HY</given-names></name><name><surname>Greenleaf</surname><given-names>WJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ATAC-seq: a method for assaying chromatin accessibility genome-wide</article-title><source>Curr. Proto. Mol. Biol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>21.29.21</fpage><lpage>29</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mucida</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transcriptional reprogramming of mature CD4<sup>+</sup> helper T cells generates distinct MHC class II-restricted cytotoxic T lymphocytes</article-title><source>Nat. Immunol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>281</fpage><lpage>289</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni.2523</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23334788?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23334788</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>