<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName nlm2jats3.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Immunol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Immunol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Immunol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Immunology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1664-3224</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">8996177</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2022.864031</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Immunology</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>
<italic>Leishmania Major</italic> Centrin Gene-Deleted Parasites Generate Skin Resident Memory T-Cell Immune Response Analogous to Leishmanization</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>Nevien</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/346672"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Karmakar</surname><given-names>Subir</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Bhattacharya</surname><given-names>Parna</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/318654"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sepahpour</surname><given-names>Telly</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Takeda</surname><given-names>Kazuyo</given-names></name><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/994381"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hamano</surname><given-names>Shinjiro</given-names></name><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/32034"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Matlashewski</surname><given-names>Greg</given-names></name><xref rid="aff4" ref-type="aff">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn001" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/814650"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Satoskar</surname><given-names>Abhay R.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff5" ref-type="aff">
<sup>5</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn001" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/46071"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gannavaram</surname><given-names>Sreenivas</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Dey</surname><given-names>Ranadhir</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn001" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/130388"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Nakhasi</surname><given-names>Hira L.</given-names></name><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref rid="fn001" ref-type="author-notes">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref><uri xlink:href="https://loop.frontiersin.org/people/55852"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
<institution>Division of Emerging and Transfusion Transmitted Diseases, Center for Biologics Evaluation and Research (CBER), Food and Drug Administration (FDA)</institution>, <addr-line>Silver Spring, MD</addr-line>, <country>United States</country>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
<institution>Laboratory of Clinical Hematology, Center for Biologics Evaluation and Research (CBER), Food and Drug Administration (FDA)</institution>, <addr-line>Silver Spring, MD</addr-line>, <country>United States</country>
</aff><aff id="aff3">
<sup>3</sup>
<institution>Department of Parasitology, Institute of Tropical Medicine (NEKKEN), Nagasaki University</institution>, <addr-line>Nagasaki</addr-line>, <country>Japan</country>
</aff><aff id="aff4">
<sup>4</sup>
<institution>Department of Microbiology and Immunology, McGill University</institution>, <addr-line>Montreal, QC</addr-line>, <country>Canada</country>
</aff><aff id="aff5">
<sup>5</sup>
<institution>Department of Pathology and Microbiology, Ohio State University</institution>, <addr-line>Columbus, OH</addr-line>, <country>United States</country>
</aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Yasuyuki Goto, The University of Tokyo, Japan</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Malcolm Scott Duthie, HDT Biotech Corporation, United States; Salvador Iborra, Universidad Complutense de Madrid, Spain</p></fn><corresp id="fn001">*Correspondence: Greg Matlashewski, <email xlink:href="mailto:greg.matlashewski@mcgill.ca">greg.matlashewski@mcgill.ca</email>; Abhay R. Satoskar, <email xlink:href="mailto:Abhay.Satoskar@osumc.edu">Abhay.Satoskar@osumc.edu</email>; Ranadhir Dey, <email xlink:href="mailto:ranadhir.dey@fda.hhs.gov">ranadhir.dey@fda.hhs.gov</email>; Hira L. Nakhasi, <email xlink:href="mailto:Hira.Nakhasi@fda.hhs.gov">Hira.Nakhasi@fda.hhs.gov</email>
</corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn002"><p>This article was submitted to Microbial Immunology, a section of the journal Frontiers in Immunology</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>28</day><month>3</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>864031</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>1</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>01</day><month>3</month><year>2022</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2022 Ismail, Karmakar, Bhattacharya, Sepahpour, Takeda, Hamano, Matlashewski, Satoskar, Gannavaram, Dey and Nakhasi</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2022</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Ismail, Karmakar, Bhattacharya, Sepahpour, Takeda, Hamano, Matlashewski, Satoskar, Gannavaram, Dey and Nakhasi</copyright-holder><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Leishmaniasis is a vector-borne parasitic disease transmitted through the bite of a sand fly with no available vaccine for humans. Recently, we have developed a live attenuated <italic>Leishmania major centrin</italic> gene-deleted parasite strain (<italic>LmCen<sup>-/-</sup>
</italic>) that induced protection against homologous and heterologous challenges. We demonstrated that the protection is mediated by IFN (Interferon) &#x003b3;-secreting CD4<sup>+</sup> T-effector cells and multifunctional T cells, which is analogous to leishmanization. In addition, in a leishmanization model, skin tissue-resident memory T (TRM) cells were also shown to be crucial for host protection. In this study, we evaluated the generation and function of skin TRM cells following immunization with <italic>LmCen<sup>-/-</sup>
</italic> parasites and compared those with leishmanization. We show that immunization with <italic>LmCen<sup>-/-</sup>
</italic> generated skin CD4+ TRM cells and is supported by the induction of cytokines and chemokines essential for their production and survival similar to leishmanization. Following challenge with wild-type <italic>L. major</italic>, TRM cells specific to <italic>L. major</italic> were rapidly recruited and proliferated at the site of infection in the immunized mice. Furthermore, upon challenge, CD4<sup>+</sup> TRM cells induce higher levels of IFN&#x003b3; and Granzyme B in the immunized and leishmanized mice than in non-immunized mice. Taken together, our studies demonstrate that the genetically modified live attenuated <italic>LmCen</italic>
<sup>-/-</sup> vaccine generates functional CD4<sup>+</sup> skin TRM cells, similar to leishmanization, that may play a crucial role in host protection along with effector T cells as shown in our previous study.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Leishmania major</kwd><kwd>live attenuated Leishmania vaccine</kwd><kwd>tissue resident memory T cells</kwd><kwd>leishmanization</kwd><kwd>Granzyme B</kwd><kwd>cytokines</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="52"/><page-count count="14"/><word-count count="6600"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Leishmaniasis is a vector-borne neglected tropical disease endemic in tropical and subtropical regions of the world. It is caused by infection with different species of the protozoan parasite <italic>Leishmania</italic> and transmitted by the bites of infected sand fly (<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>). Currently, there is no approved human vaccine against leishmaniasis, and existing treatment options are suboptimal because of the development of drug resistance and coinfections with HIV and other endemic diseases (<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Leishmanization, a process by which a small inoculum of <italic>Leishmania major</italic> parasites is injected into the skin to acquire protection against infection, was previously used in several countries in the Middle East and former Soviet Union (<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). However, the practice has been discontinued because of safety concerns. Recently, using CRISPR (Clustered regularly interspaced short palindromic repeats) gene editing, we have generated a centrin gene-deleted live attenuated <italic>L. major</italic> strain, <italic>LmCen<sup>-/-</sup>
</italic> (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). We demonstrated that <italic>LmCen<sup>-/-</sup>
</italic> parasites do not cause lesions but have the ability to mount an immunological response that is protective against both cutaneous and visceral leishmaniasis in animal models that mimic human disease (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). We have shown that both <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic>immunized and healed mice from primary infection representing leishmanization generated comparable protective immunity against challenge with <italic>LmWT</italic> parasites. The protective immunity was due to multifunctional (IFN&#x003b3;<sup>+</sup> IL2<sup>+</sup> TNF&#x003b1;<sup>+</sup>) CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells as well as IFN-&#x003b3;&#x02212;secreting CD4<sup>+</sup> T-effector cells (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>).</p><p>Recent studies have suggested that memory T cells that accumulate in tissues, termed tissue-resident memory T (TRM) cells, play a crucial role in maintaining long-term protective immunity in skin, lungs, or any other mucosal organs against viral pathogens and allergens (<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). The CD4<sup>+</sup> and CD8<sup>+</sup> TRM cells are identified by the expression of CD69 and CD103 in both mouse and human tissues (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>). It has been shown that skin CD69<sup>+</sup> CD103<sup>+</sup> TRM cells exhibit more effector function compared to CD69<sup>+</sup> CD103<sup>-</sup> (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). TRM cells can also be generated by vaccination, particularly live attenuated viral vaccines appear to be more effective than killed or subunit vaccines for inducing TRM cells (<xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>).</p><p>Previous studies have shown that after the resolution of infection with wild-type <italic>L. major</italic> parasites, i.e., leishmanization, the skin of healed mice harbors CD4<sup>+</sup> TRM cells, and the activity of these cells is important for optimal immunity against reinfection with <italic>Leishmania</italic> (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). The TRM cells persist in the absence of circulating <italic>Leishmania</italic>-specific T cells and rapidly recruit inflammatory monocytes and <italic>Leishmania</italic>-specific T effector cells to the site of infection and contribute to protective immunity (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). In addition, intradermal delivery of a DNA vaccine for <italic>Leishmania</italic> was also found to generate long-lasting skin TRM cells that contributed to protective immunity against <italic>L. major</italic> challenge (<xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>). Therefore, TRM cells are an excellent target for vaccine development (<xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). In this study, we show that intradermal immunization with genetically modified live attenuated <italic>LmCen<sup>-/-</sup>
</italic> parasite vaccine generates CD4<sup>+</sup> TRM cells in the skin of C57BL/6 mice comparable to leishmanization. Generation of CD4<sup>+</sup> TRM cells in the skin by <italic>LmCen<sup>-/-</sup>
</italic> was enabled by the expression of cytokines, chemokine receptors, and transcription factors as shown in previous studies (<xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>). Following challenge with wild-type <italic>L. major</italic>, TRM cells specific to <italic>L. major</italic> were rapidly recruited and proliferated at the site of infection in the immunized mice and induced higher levels of IFN-&#x003b3; and Granzyme B in the immunized and leishmanized mice than non-immunized mice. Therefore, the protection induced by <italic>LmCen<sup>-/-</sup>
</italic> against infection with virulent <italic>L. major</italic> parasites might be, in part, due to rapid recruitment, proliferation, and induction of Th1 response and cytotoxic response (Granzyme B) by CD4<sup>+</sup> TRM cells at the site of infection in addition to the IFN&#x003b3;-secreting CD4+ T effector cells and multifunctional T cells (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). These observations suggest that intradermal immunization with <italic>LmCen<sup>-/-</sup>
</italic> induces a protective response similar to leishmanization albeit a safer alternative to leishmanization.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s2_1"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>The animal protocol for this study has been approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee at the Center for Biologics Evaluation and Research, US Food and Drug Administration (FDA) (ASP 1995#26). In addition, the animal protocol is in full accordance with &#x0201c;The guide for the care and use of animals as described in the US Public Health Service policy on Humane Care and Use of Laboratory Animals 2015.&#x0201d;</p></sec><sec id="s2_2"><title>
<italic>Leishmania</italic> Strains and Culture Medium</title><p>
<italic>L. major</italic> Friedlin (FV9) used in this study were routinely passaged into the footpads of BALB/c mice. Amastigotes isolated from infected lesions were grown in M199 medium, and promastigotes were cultured at 27&#x000b0;C in M199 medium (pH 7.4) supplemented with 10% heat-inactivated fetal bovine serum, 40 mM HEPES ((4-(2-hydroxyethyl)-1-piperazineethanesulfonic acid) (pH 7.4), 0.1 mM adenine, 5 mg L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> hemin, 1 mg L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> biotin, 1 mg L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> biopterin, 50 U ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> penicillin, and 50 &#x003bc;g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> streptomycin. Cultures were passaged in fresh medium at a 40-fold dilution once a week. The wild-type <italic>L. major centrin</italic> gene-deleted <italic>LmCen</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup> (Friedlin strain) promastigotes were cultured as previously described (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s2_3"><title>Mouse Infection and Immunization</title><p>Female 6- to 8-week-old C57BL/6 (Jackson labs) or IFN&#x003b3;/Thy1.1 knock-in mice (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>) were immunized or infected, in the upper right flank, with 2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> total stationary phase promastigotes of <italic>LmCen<sup>&#x02212;/&#x02212;</sup>
</italic> or <italic>LmWT</italic> parasites, by intradermal needle injection, in 10 &#x003bc;l PBS. IFN&#x003b3;/Thy1.1 knock-in mice were provided by C. Weaver (University of Alabama, Birmingham, AL, USA). After 15 weeks of infection/immunization, healed and immunized mice were challenged in the distal flank skin with 2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> total stationary phase <italic>LmWT</italic> promastigotes intradermally by needle inoculation.</p></sec><sec id="s2_4"><title>Flow Cytometric Analysis</title><p>T cells were isolated from the skin using the following protocol: after euthanasia, flanks were shaved and 1 cm<sup>2</sup> of the flank skin was collected, then chopped and incubated in collagenase P (2&#x02009;mg/ml; Roche Diagnostics) and DNAase in 10% FBS complete RPMI media at 37&#x000b0;C for 120&#x02009;min. Tissue was then homogenized in MACS C tubes using gentleMACS Dissociator (Miltenyi Biotec) for 1 min. To obtain a single-cell suspension, tissue homogenate was strained through 100-&#x000b5;m and 70-&#x000b5;m nylon strains (Miltenyi Biotec). Cells were stained with antibodies, and their expression of phenotypic markers was determined by flow cytometry using BD LSR Fortessa (BD Biosciences) and analyzed with FlowJo (Treestar). We used the following antibodies: anti-mouse CD3 (17A2), CD44 (IM7), Thy-1.1 (HIS51), and Granzyme B (NGZB) from Thermo Fisher Scientific; anti-mouse CD4 (RM4-5), CD8a (53-6.7), CD62L (MEL-14), CD69 (H1.2F3), CD103 (2E7); anti-BrdU (B24) from BD Biosciences. Live cells were discriminated with a fixable LIVE/DEAD fixable blue dead cell stain (Thermo Fisher Scientific). Cell number, when indicated, was calculated as an absolute number per 10<sup>6</sup> total acquired cells.</p></sec><sec id="s2_5"><title>Quantification of Gene Expression by qPCR</title><p>Cytokine expression from mouse skin tissues was determined by real-time PCR at the indicated time points. Briefly, total RNA was extracted from flank skin using PureLink RNA Mini kit (Ambion). Aliquots (300 ng) of total RNA were reverse transcribed into cDNA by using random hexamers from a high-capacity cDNA reverse transcription kit (Applied Biosystems). TaqMan gene expression Master Mix (Applied Biosystem) was used to determine the cytokine (<xref rid="SM2" ref-type="supplementary-material">
<bold>Table S1</bold>
</xref>) expression levels in a CFX96 Touch Real-Time System (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA). The data were analyzed with CFX Manager Software. The expression levels of genes of interest were determined by the 2<sup>-&#x00394;&#x00394;Ct</sup> method; samples were normalized to GAPDH expression and determined relative to expression values from naive animals.</p></sec><sec id="s2_6"><title>Histological and Immunohistochemical Staining</title><p>Mouse flanks were shaved before tissue harvesting. Flank skin was fixed in fixative solutions (10% buffered formalin phosphate solution). Paraffin-embedded sections were stained with H&#x00026;E. Immune staining was also done using an Anti-Granzyme B Ab (EPR22645-206) from Abcam. All the histochemical and immunohistochemical staining was done by Histoserv (Gaithersburg, MD, USA). Stained sections were analyzed under a Keyence digital microscope (Keyence Corporation of America). For immunofluorescence, unfixed mouse skins were embedded in OCT compound embedding medium (Tissue-Tek) and cut into 10-&#x000b5;m sections for immunohistochemistry. Frozen sections were fixed with cold methanol for 5 min. Sections were blocked with 10% normal donkey serum and incubated with anti-CD3 (EPR20752), anti-CD69 (H1.2F3), and CD103 (AP-MAB0828) antibodies, from Abcam, overnight at 4&#x000b0;C. After washing with PBS, anti-rat, anti-rabbit, and anti-hamster secondary antibodies conjugated with Alexa Fluor 488, 594, and 647 (Jackson ImmunoResearch), respectively, were applied for 1 h at room temperature, washed and followed with Hoechst 33258 nuclear counterstaining, and mounted with Fluoromount-G. These slides were examined with a Leica SP8 confocal microscope.</p></sec><sec id="s2_7"><title>
<italic>In Vivo</italic> Bromodeoxyuridine Treatment</title><p>Mice were injected intraperitoneally with 2&#x02009;mg of BrdU per day, for 3 days, with treatment starting on the day of challenge with <italic>LmWT</italic> parasites. BrdU incorporation was measured with a BrdU flow kit (BD Biosciences), and the proportion of BrdU<sup>+</sup> cells was measured by flow cytometry and analyzed by FlowJo software as indicated in <xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">
<bold>Supplementary Figure S4</bold>
</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s2_8"><title>Adoptive Transfer of T Cells</title><p>For cell recruitment studies, T cells from spleens of 4 weeks <italic>LmCen<sup>-/-</sup>
</italic> immunized mice were isolated using mouse Pan T cell isolation kit (Miltenyi Biotec) according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol. The cells were then stained with Invitrogen CellTrace Far Red Cell Proliferation Kit (Fisher Scientific). The stained cells (30 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup>/mouse) were transferred intravenously (i.v.) into naive recipient mice. After 24 h, recipient mice were then challenged in the flank skin with <italic>L. major WT</italic> parasite (2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup>/mouse). Skin from challenged flanks was collected at 48 h post-challenge and prepared for flow cytometry analysis.</p></sec><sec id="s2_9"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>Statistical analysis of differences between means of groups was determined using a two-tail unpaired t test. All proportional numerical values provided in the text and figure legends were written as the mean&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;SEM. All statistical analyses were done in Prism 7.0 (GraphPad). All experiments were performed at least two times, with similar results obtained each time.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3_1"><title>Immunization With <italic>LmCen</italic>
<sup>-/-</sup> Generates CD4<sup>+</sup> TRM Cells in the Skin</title><p>Previous studies of the leishmanization model have shown that resolution of acute infection with <italic>LmWT</italic> parasites (12&#x02013;20 weeks post-infection) is accompanied by the formation of CD4<sup>+</sup> TRM cells that contribute to protective immunity against virulent challenge (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). To investigate if immunization with <italic>LmCen<sup>-/-</sup>
</italic> parasites would similarly lead to the formation of TRM cells, we injected C57BL/6 mice intradermally in the flank skin with 2 &#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> stationary phase of either <italic>LmCen<sup>-/-</sup>
</italic> or <italic>LmWT</italic> parasites and monitored TRM populations in both groups (<xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figure&#x000a0;1A</bold>
</xref>). Next, we evaluated both CD4<sup>+</sup>CD69<sup>+</sup> as well as CD4<sup>+</sup>CD69<sup>+</sup>CD103<sup>+</sup> TRM cell populations in the injected and distal flanks at both 6 and 15 weeks post-infection/immunization (<xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figures&#x000a0;1B&#x02013;E</bold>
</xref>). We identified TRM population as CD3<sup>+</sup>CD4<sup>+</sup>CD44<sup>+</sup>CD62L<sup>-</sup>CD69<sup>+</sup> and CD3<sup>+</sup>CD4<sup>+</sup>CD44<sup>+</sup>CD62L<sup>-</sup>CD69<sup>+</sup>CD103<sup>+</sup> (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">
<bold>Supplementary Figure S1</bold>
</xref>). We observed that most of the TRM cells expressing CD69 are also expressing CD103 (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">
<bold>Supplementary Figure S1</bold>
</xref>). The purpose of evaluating the generation of TRMs at 6 weeks was to establish a baseline for the response observed at the 15-week time point. There were very few CD4<sup>+</sup>CD69<sup>+</sup> as well as CD4<sup>+</sup>CD69<sup>+</sup>CD103<sup>+</sup> TRM cells in the injected flank at 6 weeks PI in both <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic> and <italic>LmWT</italic>-infected mice (<xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figures&#x000a0;1B, C</bold>
</xref>
<bold>)</bold>. However, in both <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic>immunized mice and <italic>LmWT</italic>-infected mice (healed mice), we observed significantly higher numbers of both CD4<sup>+</sup>CD69<sup>+</sup> and CD4<sup>+</sup>CD69<sup>+</sup>CD103<sup>+</sup> TRM in the injected flank at 15 weeks compared to 6 weeks PI or compared to non-immunized mice (<xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figures&#x000a0;1B, C</bold>
</xref>
<bold>)</bold>. Our data indicate that, in the injected flank, at 15 weeks of PI, there was no significant difference between <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic>immunized mice and <italic>LmWT</italic>-infected mice (<xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figures&#x000a0;1B, C</bold>
</xref>
<bold>)</bold>. However, at the distal flank, there was a significant increase of both CD4+CD69+ and CD4+CD69+CD103+ TRM cells in <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic>immunized group compared to <italic>LmWT</italic> healed group at 15 weeks of PI (<xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figures&#x000a0;1D, E</bold>
</xref>
<bold>)</bold>. We also noted that the frequencies of CD4<sup>+</sup> TRM cells in the injected and distal flanks are comparable (<xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figures&#x000a0;1B&#x02013;E</bold>
</xref>), indicating that the TRM cells were present in more or less uniform density throughout the skin of immunized animals. Taken together, these data indicate that immunization with <italic>LmCen<sup>-/-</sup>
</italic> parasites generates CD4<sup>+</sup> TRM cells in the injected as well as distal sites of the skin of mice.</p><fig position="float" id="f1"><label>Figure&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Immunization with <italic>LmCen</italic>
<sup>-/-</sup> generates CD4<sup>+</sup> TRM cells in the skin. Mice were injected, intradermally, with either <italic>LmCen<sup>-/-</sup>
</italic> or <italic>L. major</italic> wild-type (<italic>LmWT)</italic> parasites in the right flank, and TRM cell population was assessed at 6 and 15 weeks post-injection by flow cytometry from both right (injected flank) and left flank (distal flank) marked by the red box. Baseline TRM population was measured in flank skin of non-immunized mice. <bold>(A)</bold> Schematic plan of injection site and experimental time points. <bold>(B, C)</bold> TRM cell population in the injected flank. <bold>(B)</bold> CD4<sup>+</sup>CD69<sup>+</sup> TRM cells and <bold>(C)</bold> CD4<sup>+</sup>CD69<sup>+</sup>CD103<sup>+</sup>
<bold>. (D, E)</bold> TRM cell population in the distal flank. <bold>(D)</bold> CD4<sup>+</sup>CD69<sup>+</sup> TRM cells and <bold>(E)</bold> CD4<sup>+</sup>CD69<sup>+</sup>CD103<sup>+</sup> collected from <italic>LmWT</italic> and <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic>injected mice at 6 and 15 weeks post-injection. The Y axis represents the number of TRM cells per 10e6 total cells acquired. Results are representative of one of two independent experiments with n = 3&#x02013;4 mice per group. Bars represent the means with SEM in each group. Statistical analysis was performed by unpaired two-tailed t-test (**<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.009, *<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05, ns, not significant).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fimmu-13-864031-g001" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3_2"><title>Expression Profile of Cytokines and Chemokine Receptors Supporting Tissue-Resident Memory T Cell Generation at the Injected and Distal Flank Skin</title><p>To investigate the immunological milieu that supports TRM cells, we determined the expression of several cytokines and chemokine receptors (AHR, IL15, IL33, CXCR3, CCR8, and TGF&#x003b2;) known to support the formation, survival, and homeostasis of TRM cells (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). RNA was isolated from the injected flank skin of the <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic> or <italic>LmWT</italic>-injected mice, and the indicated analytes were assayed by q-PCR (<xref rid="f2" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figure&#x000a0;2A</bold>
</xref>). In the injected flank of <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic>immunized mice, the expression of AHR, IL33, CXCR3, CCR8, and TGFB was significantly upregulated at 15 weeks PI compared to 6 weeks PI (<xref rid="f2" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figures&#x000a0;2B, D&#x02013;G</bold>
</xref>). Our data indicate that the expression of AHR, IL15, IL33, CXCR3, and CCR8 was significantly higher in the <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic>immunized mice compared to <italic>LmWT</italic> healed mice at 15 weeks PI (<xref rid="f2" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figures&#x000a0;2B&#x02013;F</bold>
</xref>). In the <italic>LmWT</italic> healed group, only AHR, CXCR3, and TGFB were significantly upregulated at 15 weeks (<xref rid="f2" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figures&#x000a0;2B, E, G</bold>
</xref>
<bold>)</bold>. Since we observed increased population of CD4+ TRM cells in the distal flank (<xref rid="f1" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figures&#x000a0;1D, E</bold>
</xref>
<bold>)</bold>, we wanted to investigate if such increase in TRM cell population was supported by differential expression of cytokines or chemokine receptors in the distal flank as well. In the distal flank, of both <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic>immunized mice and <italic>LmWT</italic> healed mice, the expression of AHR, IL33, and CXCR3 was significantly upregulated at 15 weeks PI compared to 6 weeks PI (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">
<bold>Supplementary Figures S2A, B, D, E</bold>
</xref>). However, there was no difference in the expression of IL15 at 15 weeks PI compared to 6 weeks PI in both immunized and <italic>LmWT</italic> healed mice (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">
<bold>Supplementary Figure S2C</bold>
</xref>).</p><fig position="float" id="f2"><label>Figure&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Expression profile of cytokines and chemokine receptors supporting TRM cell generation at the injected flank skin. Mice were injected with <italic>LmCen<sup>-/-</sup>
</italic> or <italic>LmWT</italic>, intradermally, in the right flank. The expression profile of indicated genes from the injected flank skin was assessed at 6 and 15 weeks (6w and 15w) post-injection by qPCR. <bold>(A)</bold> Schematic plan of the experimental time points and injection site. <bold>(B&#x02013;G)</bold> Expression of different transcripts, <bold>(B)</bold> AHR<bold>, (C)</bold> IL15, <bold>(D)</bold> IL33<bold>, (E)</bold> CXCR3, <bold>(F)</bold> CCR8, and <bold>(G)</bold> TGFB, at indicated time points. To determine the fold expression of each gene, 2<sup>-&#x00394;&#x00394;CT</sup> method was employed. The data were normalized to GAPDH expression and shown as the fold change relative to age-matched naive mice. Results are representative of one of two independent experiments, with total 4 mice per group. Bars represent the means with SEM in each group. Statistical analysis was performed by unpaired two-tailed t test (*<italic>p</italic>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05, **<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.009, ***<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.0005).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fimmu-13-864031-g002" position="float"/></fig><p>Overall, these results suggest that the cytokine milieu in the skin of <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic>immunized mice is conducive to support the formation, survival, and homeostasis of TRM cells at both injected and distal sites. Furthermore, our results suggest that immunization with <italic>LmCen<sup>-/-</sup>
</italic> parasites results in slightly higher cytokine milieu in the skin compared to leishmanization.</p></sec><sec id="s3_3"><title>
<italic>LmWT</italic> Challenge Leads to Rapid Accumulation of Tissue-Resident Memory T Cells in the Skin of Immunized or Healed Mice</title><p>To study <italic>Leishmania</italic>-specific TRM cell recall response in the skin, non-immunized, <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic>immunized, or healed mice were challenged with <italic>LmWT</italic> parasites 15 weeks PI at a site different from the initial immunization or infection site (<xref rid="f3" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figure&#x000a0;3A</bold>
</xref>). At 48 and 72 h post-challenge, skin from the challenge site was collected for histology and immunohistochemistry (<xref rid="f3" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figure&#x000a0;3A</bold>
</xref>). The challenged flank skin stained with H&#x00026;E clearly revealed a robust accumulation of cells in both <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic>immunized mice and healed mice compared to non-immunized mice at 48 h post-challenge (<xref rid="f3" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figure&#x000a0;3B</bold>
</xref>). Furthermore, TRM cells before (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">
<bold>Supplementary Figure S3A</bold>
</xref>) and after 48 and 72 h post-challenge were identified by staining for CD3, CD69, and CD103 <bold>(</bold>
<xref rid="f3" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figure&#x000a0;3C</bold>
</xref>
<bold>).</bold> Before challenge, we observed a few CD69+CD103+ cells in the skin of immunized or healed mice (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">
<bold>Supplementary Figure S3B</bold>
</xref>). In the immunized mice after challenge with <italic>LmWT</italic> parasites, immunohistochemistry-stained section of the challenged site showed a rapid increase of CD103+ cells within 48 h compared to non-immunized or healed mice that persisted until 72 h (<xref rid="f3" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figure&#x000a0;3C</bold>
</xref>). This increase was also observed in CD3<sup>+</sup>CD103<sup>+</sup> cells, as revealed in the overlay of red (CD3<sup>+</sup>) and green (CD103<sup>+</sup>) fluorescence images (<xref rid="f3" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figure&#x000a0;3C</bold>
</xref>
<bold>, inset</bold>). In healed mice, the accumulation of TRM cells (CD3<sup>+</sup> CD103<sup>+</sup>) after challenge with <italic>LmWT</italic> parasites was distinct from non-immunized mice only at 72 h post-challenge (<xref rid="f3" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figure&#x000a0;3C</bold>
</xref>). Non-immunized challenged mice showed little accumulation of TRM cells at the site of challenge that indicates that the rapid accumulation of TRM cells at the site of challenge is a recall response to <italic>LmWT</italic> challenge infection.</p><fig position="float" id="f3"><label>Figure&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>
<italic>LmWT</italic> challenge leads to rapid accumulation of TRM cells in the skin of immunized or healed mice. Fifteen-week (15w) immunized and healed mice and non-immunized control mice were challenged in the flank skin with <italic>LmWT</italic> virulent parasite. Skin from the site of challenge was collected at 48 and 72 hours (48h and 72h) post-challenge. Tissue infiltration and TRM cells were analyzed by immunofluorescence and H&#x00026;E staining. <bold>(A)</bold> Schematic plan of the experimental time points. <bold>(B)</bold> H&#x00026;E staining of skin tissue at the site of challenge 48 h post-challenge. Black arrow indicates cellular infiltration at the challenge site. <bold>(C)</bold> Expression of CD3 (red), CD69 (blue), and CD103 (green) in the flank skin of non-immunized control, healed, and immunized mice, at the site of challenge, following 48 and 72 h post-challenge. Scale bar is 25 &#x000b5;m. Results are representative of one independent experiment, repeated 3 times, with 3 mice per group.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fimmu-13-864031-g003" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3_4"><title>Tissue-Resident Memory T Cells From <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic>Immunized Mice Proliferate Locally Following Challenge With Virulent <italic>LmWT</italic> Parasites</title><p>It was shown that TRM cells proliferate <italic>in situ</italic> after an antiviral recall response (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). To assess the proliferative capacity of TRM cells in response to <italic>LmWT</italic> challenge, immunized, healed, or non-immunized mice were treated with bromodeoxyuridine (BrdU) for three consecutive days starting on the day of challenge (<xref rid="f4" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figure&#x000a0;4A</bold>
</xref>). Seven days post-challenge, cells were isolated from the challenged flank skin to detect the proliferating TRM cells (identified by incorporated BrdU, i.e., BrdU<sup>+</sup> cells). We excluded central memory T cells by gating on CD3<sup>+</sup>CD62L<sup>low</sup> cells (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">
<bold>Supplementary Figure S4</bold>
</xref>). We observed that both immunized and healed mice had significantly higher proportion of CD3<sup>+</sup>CD69<sup>+</sup>BrdU<sup>+</sup> (<xref rid="f4" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figures&#x000a0;4B, C</bold>
</xref>
<bold>)</bold> and CD3<sup>+</sup>CD69<sup>+</sup>CD103<sup>+</sup>BrdU<sup>+</sup> (<xref rid="f4" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figures&#x000a0;4B, D</bold>
</xref>
<bold>)</bold> T cells compared to the non-immunized challenged group. The proportion of both CD3<sup>+</sup>CD69<sup>+</sup>BrdU<sup>+</sup> and CD3<sup>+</sup>CD69<sup>+</sup>CD103<sup>+</sup>BrdU<sup>+</sup> T cells from immunized challenged mice was similar to that observed in the healed challenged group (<xref rid="f4" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figures&#x000a0;4C, D</bold>
</xref>
<bold>)</bold>. These results indicate that <italic>LmCen<sup>-/-</sup>
</italic> immunization generates skin TRM cells that proliferate, <italic>in situ</italic>, in response to challenge with virulent <italic>L. major</italic> parasite.</p><fig position="float" id="f4"><label>Figure&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>TRM cells from <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic>immunized mice proliferate locally following challenge with virulent <italic>LmWT</italic> parasites. Fifteen<bold>-</bold>week (15w) immunized and healed mice were challenged with <italic>LmWT</italic> parasites and injected with BrdU, as described in the <italic>Materials and Methods</italic>. Mice were euthanized, and flank skins were collected 7 days post-challenge and analyzed for BrdU-positive cells. <bold>(A)</bold> Schematic plan of the experiment. <bold>(B)</bold> Representative BrdU staining on skin CD69<sup>+</sup> (single positive) and CD69<sup>+</sup>CD103<sup>+</sup> (double positive) TRM cells 7 days post-<italic>LmWT</italic> challenge. The numbers represent the percentage of gated population as a ratio of total parent population (CD69<sup>+</sup> or CD69<sup>+</sup>CD103<sup>+</sup>, <bold>C, D</bold>, respectively). Panels <bold>(C, D)</bold> show the proportion of skin CD69<sup>+</sup> and CD69<sup>+</sup>CD103<sup>+</sup> TRM cells, respectively, with incorporated BrdU in the Non-immunized, Healed, and Immunized mice 7 days post-<italic>LmWT</italic> challenge. <italic>*p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.02, <italic>**p</italic> = 0.005, ns = not significant. Data shown are combined results from two independent experiments, n = 5&#x02013;6. Results are mean &#x000b1; SEM; statistical analysis was performed by two-tailed unpaired t-test. D, Days; Chal, Challenged; inj, Injection.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fimmu-13-864031-g004" position="float"/></fig><p>It has been shown in the leishmanization model that TRM cells enhance T-cell recruitment to the site of challenge (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). In the current study, we wanted to investigate if TRM cells generated by <italic>LmCen<sup>-/-</sup>
</italic> immunization have any role in the recruitment of <italic>Leishmania</italic>-specific T cells from circulation to the site of challenge. The T cells were collected from the spleens of <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic>immunized mice and stained by CellTrace and injected intravenously (i.v.) into non-immunized, healed, or <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic>immunized mice. The recipient mice were then challenged in the flank skin with <italic>LmWT</italic> parasites (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">
<bold>Supplementary Figure S5A</bold>
</xref>). To assess T-cell recruitment to the site of challenge, we assessed the percentage of CellTrace-positive T cells isolated from the challenged flank 48 h post-challenge (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">
<bold>Supplementary Figure S5B</bold>
</xref>
<bold>).</bold> We observed that upon challenge, the skin of <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic>immunized mice and healed mice had significantly higher proportion of CellTrace-positive T cells compared to non-immunized challenged mice that lack <italic>L. major</italic>-specific skin TRM cells (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">
<bold>Supplementary Figure S5C</bold>
</xref>). There was no difference in CellTrace-positive T-cell recruitment between <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic>immunized and healed mice (<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">
<bold>Supplementary Figure S5C</bold>
</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s3_5"><title>Skin Tissue-Resident Memory T Cells From <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic>Immunized Mice Produce IFN&#x003b3; in Response to Challenge</title><p>We wanted to evaluate if TRM cells are capable of producing IFN&#x003b3; upon challenge. To increase the sensitivity of detection of IFN&#x003b3;, we used <italic>IFN&#x003b3;/Thy1.1</italic> knock-in mice, where IFN&#x003b3;-expressing cells could be identified by the surface expression of Thy1.1 (<xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>). Non-immunized, immunized, and healed <italic>IFN&#x003b3;/Thy1.1</italic> knock-in mice were challenged with virulent <italic>LmWT</italic> parasites in the lower flank skin (<xref rid="f5" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figure&#x000a0;5A</bold>
</xref>). Five days post-challenge, cells were isolated from the challenged site skin, and the expression of IFN&#x003b3; on TRM cells was measured by flow cytometry without any <italic>ex vivo</italic> antigen restimulation and compared among the groups (<xref rid="f5" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figures&#x000a0;5A, B</bold>
</xref>
<bold>;</bold>
<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">
<bold>Supplementary Figure S6</bold>
</xref>). We observed that both CD4<sup>+</sup>CD69<sup>+</sup> and CD4<sup>+</sup>CD69<sup>+</sup>CD103<sup>+</sup> TRM cells from immunized and healed mice showed significantly higher expression of IFN&#x003b3; (represented by Thy1.1 expression) compared to that of non-immunized mice following challenge (<xref rid="f5" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figures&#x000a0;5C, D</bold>
</xref>
<bold>)</bold>. Importantly, IFN&#x003b3; expression by TRM cells was comparable between healed and immunized mice (<xref rid="f5" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figures&#x000a0;5C, D</bold>
</xref>
<bold>)</bold>. Taken together these, data indicate that <italic>Leishmania</italic>-specific skin TRM cells, generated after immunization with <italic>LmCen<sup>-/-</sup>
</italic> parasites, can mount a Th1 response upon challenge with virulent parasite.</p><fig position="float" id="f5"><label>Figure&#x000a0;5</label><caption><p>Skin TRM cells from <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic>immunized mice produce IFN&#x003b3; in response to challenge. Non-immunized, healed, and immunized IFN&#x003b3;/Thy1.1 mice were challenged with <italic>LmWT</italic> parasite in the flank skin. T cells from challenged skin were isolated 5 days post-challenge, and cytokine production was assessed with flow cytometry analysis. <bold>(A)</bold> Schematic representation of the experiment. <bold>(B)</bold> Graph is representative of Thy1.1 staining on skin CD4<sup>+</sup> TRM cells (CD3<sup>+</sup>CD4<sup>+</sup>CD44<sup>+</sup>CD62L<sup>-</sup>CD69<sup>+</sup> and CD3<sup>+</sup>CD4<sup>+</sup>CD44<sup>+</sup>CD62L<sup>-</sup>CD69<sup>+</sup>CD103<sup>+</sup>). <bold>(C, D)</bold> Expression of Thy1.1 surface marker, representing IFN&#x003b3; expression, was measured on <bold>(C)</bold> CD4<sup>+</sup>CD69<sup>+</sup> and <bold>(D)</bold> CD4<sup>+</sup>CD69<sup>+</sup>CD103<sup>+</sup> TRM cells. Y axis represents a portion of skin CD4<sup>+</sup> TRM cells expressing IFN&#x003b3; as a percentage of CD4<sup>+</sup>CD69<sup>+</sup> TRM population. Data shown are combined results from two independent experiments with n = 6&#x02013;8 mice per group. Bars represent the means with SEM in each group. Statistical analysis was performed by unpaired two-tailed t-test (**<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.007, *<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.02). Chal, Challenged; w, week.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fimmu-13-864031-g005" position="float"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3_6"><title>Tissue-Resident Memory T Cells From <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic>Immunized Mice Exhibit Cytotoxic Function by Expressing Granzyme B</title><p>To investigate if the <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic>induced TRM cells exhibit cytotoxic function following virulent infection, we challenged non-immunized, immunized, and healed mice in the flank skin with <italic>LmWT</italic> parasites (<xref rid="f6" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figure&#x000a0;6A</bold>
</xref>). We collected the flank skin 48 h post-challenge and stained the tissue with anti-granzyme B antibodies (<xref rid="f6" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figure&#x000a0;6A</bold>
</xref>). Immunohistochemistry staining showed that granzyme B expression is higher in the tissue of <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic>immunized mice compared to healed and non-immunized mice following challenge (<xref rid="f6" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figure&#x000a0;6B</bold>
</xref>). The expression of granzyme B in non-immunized mice was minimal (<xref rid="f6" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figure&#x000a0;6B</bold>
</xref>). Next, we wanted to investigate if the cells producing granzyme B are indeed TRM cells. Non-immunized, immunized, and healed mice were challenged with <italic>LmWT</italic> parasites, and granzyme B production by TRM cells was assessed by flow cytometry. We found that a significant proportion of CD4<sup>+</sup>CD69<sup>+</sup> TRM cells from the skin of <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic>immunized mice produced granzyme B post-challenge, which was significantly higher compared to healed or non-immunized mice (<xref rid="f6" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figure&#x000a0;6C</bold>
</xref>). The proportion of granzyme B-producing CD4<sup>+</sup>CD69<sup>+</sup>CD103<sup>+</sup> TRM cells was also significantly higher in the <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic>immunized mice compared to healed and non-immunized mice following challenge (<xref rid="f6" ref-type="fig">
<bold>Figure&#x000a0;6D</bold>
</xref>). Taken together, these results indicate that <italic>LmCen<sup>-/-</sup>
</italic> immunization induces CD4<sup>+</sup> TRM cells with a cytotoxic response after challenge, and such response is equivalent to healed infection.</p><fig position="float" id="f6"><label>Figure&#x000a0;6</label><caption><p>TRM cells from <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic>immunized mice exhibit cytotoxic function by expressing granzyme B (GzmB). Fifteen-week 15w immunized and healed mice and non-immunized control mice were challenged in the flank skin with <italic>LmWT</italic> virulent parasites. <bold>(A)</bold> Schematic diagram of the site of injections. <bold>(B)</bold> Immunohistochemistry of the flank skin, at the challenge site, from 48 h challenged mice, stained with anti-granzyme B antibodies. <bold>(C, D)</bold> T cells from challenged skin were isolated 5 days post-challenge, and granzyme B production was assessed with flow cytometry analysis. <bold>(C)</bold> Portion of CD4 TRM cells, single positive (CD4<sup>+</sup>CD69<sup>+</sup>), expressing granzyme B <bold>(D)</bold> Portion of CD4 TRM cells, double positive (CD4<sup>+</sup>CD69<sup>+</sup>CD103<sup>+</sup>), expressing granzyme B Results are representative of one of two independent experiments with total 2&#x02013;4 mice per group. Bars represent the means with SEM in each group. Statistical analysis was performed by unpaired two-tailed t-test (**<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.004, *<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.03). h, hours.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fimmu-13-864031-g006" position="float"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Skin is the first line of defense against infection with vector-borne pathogens like <italic>Leishmania</italic> parasites. In addition to its physical, chemical, and microbiological barriers against pathogens, human skin harbors innate immune cells as well as a combination of resident and recirculating memory T cells with potent effector functions (<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>). Upon infection, these cells induce a robust immune response against invading pathogens. In recent years, a T-cell lineage termed TRM cells has been identified as the first line of defense against viral infections entering the body at barrier sites, like the skin (<xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>). Similarly, these cells have also shown to play an important role in host immunity against parasitic infections such as leishmaniasis and malaria (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>). Specifically, it has been demonstrated that protection upon challenge with <italic>L. major</italic> parasites in healed (i.e., leishmanization) is mediated by the TRM cells that help recruit heterogenous cell populations including CD4<sup>+</sup> T-effector cells and inflammatory monocytes to the site of infection and mediate parasite control (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). Prior studies in leishmanization models also showed the critical role of IFN&#x003b3;-secreting CD4<sup>+</sup>CD44<sup>+</sup>Ly6C<sup>+</sup> T effector cells in protection against challenge by virtue of their capacity to mount microbicidal activities immediately after challenge (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>, <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>). However, since the presence of &#x0201c;ready-to-act&#x0201d; CD4<sup>+</sup>CD44<sup>+</sup>Ly6C<sup>+</sup> T-effector cells requires a persistent infection of <italic>Leishmania</italic> parasites, achieving durable protection through safer vaccination methods makes TRM populations more desirable to target. Such vaccination may be achieved through live attenuated <italic>Leishmania</italic> strains that can persist at low levels in the immunized host yet lack virulence (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>). Moreover, such vaccines may circumvent the unresolved issues associated with persistent infection of <italic>Leishmania</italic> observed in leishmanization models such as 1) indefinite maintenance of T-effector populations in the presence of concomitant immunity and 2) potential for T-cell exhaustion due to continuous exposure to persisting antigens as discussed previously (<xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>). However, little is known about the role of TRM cells in vaccine immunity in general and particularly in genetically modified live attenuated vaccine candidates including <italic>Leishmania.</italic>
</p><p>Recently, we have reported on using CRISPR-Cas9 technology to develop <italic>centrin</italic> gene-deleted <italic>L. major</italic> parasites (<italic>LmCen<sup>-/-</sup>
</italic>). <italic>LmCen<sup>-/-</sup>
</italic> parasites showed limited survival in the host and induced protective immunity comparable to leishmanization against both needle and sand fly challenge with a wild-type <italic>L. major</italic> as well as <italic>L. donovani</italic> infection (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>). We also demonstrated that upon challenge with <italic>LmWT</italic> parasites, both <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic>immunized and healed mice generated a comparable CD4<sup>+</sup>Ly6C<sup>+</sup>IFN&#x003b3;<sup>+</sup> effector T-cell response (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>), which has been shown to play a role in parasite killing upon reinfection (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>). Since, in addition to CD4<sup>+</sup> effector T cells, it was reported that skin resident CD4<sup>+</sup> TRM cells are generated in response to <italic>L. major</italic> infection, after lesions are healed, and that they play an important role in protection against reinfection along with circulating memory T cells (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>). In this study, we evaluated the generation and function of skin TRM cells following immunization with <italic>LmCen<sup>-/-</sup>
</italic> parasites in mice and compared the response with mice that were healed after a primary <italic>LmWT</italic> infection. It is important to distinguish various T memory cell populations in characterizing the vaccine immunity. Since CD62L is a marker specific for central memory T cells, we have excluded this population while analyzing TRM cells. In this study, TRM cells were identified by the expression of both CD69 and CD103 (<xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>), as it was previously shown that expression of both markers is necessary for the optimal formation and survival of TRM cells in the skin (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>). The skin of immunized and healed mice sampled at 15 weeks of post-infection time point showed a significantly higher population of TRM cells compared to naive control group, similar to previous studies (<xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>, <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>). It has been shown that TRM cells are not restricted to the original site of infection but have the capacity to disseminate throughout the skin (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>, <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>). Interestingly, in the <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic>immunized group, we found that CD4<sup>+</sup> TRM cells were significantly higher in numbers in the distal sites compared to healed mice, suggesting that <italic>LmCen</italic>
<sup>-/-</sup> immunization is efficacious at inducing TRM cell populations. Previously, it has been shown that a population of skin resident CD4+ regulatory T cells (CD4+CD25+Foxp3+) also express CD103 (<xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>, <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>) and that CD103+ T regulatory (T Reg) cells play a crucial role in <italic>Leishmania</italic> infection-induced pathology (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). Since CD69+CD103+ T cells were observed at 15 weeks post-<italic>LmCen<sup>-/-</sup>
</italic> immunization at which point we could not recover any viable parasites, it is unlikely that these cells are CD4+ T Reg cells that require the presence of persistent infection (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>). Additionally, the residency of T Reg cells in the non-lymphoid organs in the absence of persistent infection is not fully understood (<xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>, <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>). Future studies will delineate the roles of T Reg and TRM cells in <italic>LmCen<sup>-/-</sup>
</italic> vaccine-induced immunity.</p><p>The role of chemokine receptors in the formation and survival of skin TRM cells has been previously documented (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>). It has been shown that aryl hydrocarbon receptor (AHR) is required for long-term persistence of skin TRM cells (<xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>, <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>). We observed that <italic>LmCen<sup>-/-</sup>
</italic> immunization induced significantly higher expression of AHR compared to healed mice. Similarly, IL15, IL33, and TGF&#x003b2; are shown to be required for the development and maintenance of TRM cells in the skin following viral (Herpes Simplex Virus) infection (<xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>, <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>). In our study, we observed significantly higher expression of these cytokines in the <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic>immunized group as well as healed animals compared to non-immunized animals, suggesting that immunization with <italic>LmCen</italic>
<sup>-/-</sup> induces an immune milieu that enables the generation of TRM cells, similar to leishmanization. Future studies will need to address the mechanisms by which these cytokines will help in the maintenance of long-term TRM cells in the skin of <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic>immunized mice.</p><p>In localized infections, TRM cells are highly protective and modulate host immune response by 1) killing the pathogen-infected cells through direct lysis, 2) release cytokines that further enhance local recruitment of other innate and adaptive immune cells, and 3) proliferate <italic>in situ</italic> to maintain a stable population of protective TRM cells (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>). We investigated each of these functions in both immunized and healed mice in response to virulent <italic>LmWT</italic> challenge. Similar to studies in humans, where activated memory CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells, termed CD4<sup>+</sup> CTL cells, secreted a similar amount of granzyme B compared to memory CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>), CD4<sup>+</sup> TRM cells from the skin of <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic>immunized mice produced granzyme B very early on upon challenge. These cells are mainly localized in peripheral tissue like the skin and were found to play an important role in antiviral immunity as studied by others (<xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>, <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). Parasite-specific granzyme B production by human peripheral blood mononuclear cells (PBMCs) was found to be a good correlate of protection against <italic>Leishmania</italic> infection and could be a biomarker of vaccine-induced protection against human leishmaniasis (<xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). Our study is the first to show granzyme B production by activated CD4<sup>+</sup> TRM cells in response to <italic>Leishmania</italic> challenge in a mouse model illustrating the direct antimicrobicidal activities of CD4<sup>+</sup> TRM cells in protection.</p><p>Toward characterizing the effector function from TRM populations, we analyzed cytokine responses in the skin following challenge. We observed pro-inflammatory cytokine, IFN&#x003b3;, to be specifically expressed by TRM cells upon challenge with <italic>LmWT</italic> parasites. In addition, as early as 48 h post-challenge, we observed an abundant number of immune cells at the site of infection compared to non-immunized challenged mice. These cells included CD69<sup>+</sup>CD103<sup>+</sup> TRM cells that progressively increased in number from 48 to 72 h post-challenge. As shown in previous studies, this increase could be due to the proliferation or recruitment from adjacent sites or from circulation to the site of infection (<xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>). Accordingly, we have found that <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic>specific TRM cells proliferate <italic>in situ</italic> and might play a role in recruiting <italic>Leishmania</italic> antigen-specific T cells from circulation in response to <italic>LmWT</italic> challenge. Consistent with the cytokine milieu that enables the production and maintenance of TRM population observed in <italic>LmCen<sup>-/-</sup>
</italic> immunization, an equivalent TRM response between immunization and healed infection suggests that immunization with <italic>LmCen<sup>-/-</sup>
</italic> is potent at inducing this population without causing pathology. A formal demonstration of the role of TRMs induced by <italic>LmCen<sup>-/-</sup>
</italic> immunization in the recruitment of heterogeneous cell populations or local proliferation at the site of challenge will require further studies.</p><p>TRM cells have been shown to mediate effector functions similar to circulating T memory populations that have been studied extensively in various infection models. As TRM cells are located in the peripheral tissues, early activation and gaining of antimicrobial function are some of the crucial characteristics of these cells. Due to their effector activity, the TRM cells have been shown to control viral infections in various preclinical studies in mice in addition to the circulating memory cells (<xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>, <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>). Similarly, in non-human primates, the presence of TRM cells against Simian Immunodeficiency virus (SIVs) or Ebola virus was essential to control the viral load (<xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>, <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>). In <italic>Leishmania</italic>, where the rapidity of response is essential for protection against sand fly bite transmission, the presence of skin TRM cells along with effector cells can be the first line of defense keeping the parasites in check until the activation of central memory T cells takes place (<xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>, <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>). In the current study, we observed that within 48 h post-challenge, CD69<sup>+</sup>CD103<sup>+</sup> TRM cells accumulated in the challenged site in <italic>LmCen<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>
</italic>immunized mice, and these cells remained abundant at 72 h in the infected site. Consistent with previous studies, the TRM cells secreted IFN&#x003b3; and granzyme B, indicating that their cytotoxic activities may be important in the protection observed in <italic>LmCen</italic>
<sup>-/&#x02013;</sup>induced immunity.</p><p>Overall, our results establish that <italic>LmCen<sup>-/-</sup>
</italic> immunization generates CD4<sup>+</sup> TRM cells in the skin of immunized animals. Moreover, <italic>LmCen<sup>-/-</sup>
</italic> immunization-induced immunity is comparable to that of healed mice as previously measured by effector T cell response (<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>) and in the current study by TRM cell-mediated response. Since <italic>LmCen<sup>-/-</sup>
</italic> parasites do not induce any pathology, it could serve as a safer alternative to leishmanization. Therefore, immunization with <italic>LmCen</italic>
<sup>-/-</sup> parasites may represent a more practical vaccination strategy with a realistic possibility of gaining approval for clinical use than leishmanization. In conclusion, this preclinical study in an animal model further confirms that <italic>LmCen<sup>-/-</sup>
</italic> parasites should be explored as a potential <italic>Leishmania</italic> vaccine in future clinical trials.</p></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Author&#x02019;s Note</title><p>The findings of this study are an informal communication and represent the authors&#x02019; own best judgments. These comments do not bind or obligate the Food and Drug Administration.</p></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s6"><title>Data Availability Statement</title><p>The original contributions presented in the study are included in the article/<xref rid="SM1" ref-type="supplementary-material">
<bold>Supplementary Material</bold>
</xref>. Further inquiries can be directed to the corresponding authors.</p></sec><sec sec-type="ethics-statement" id="s7"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>The animal protocol for this study has been approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee at the Center for Biologics Evaluation and Research, US FDA (ASP 1995#26). In addition, the animal protocol is in full accordance with &#x0201c;The guide for the care and use of animals as described in the US Public Health Service policy on Humane Care and Use of Laboratory Animals 2015.&#x0201d;</p></sec><sec sec-type="author-contributions" id="s8"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>NI, SK, PB, TS, and KT conducted the experiments and analyzed the data. NI, RD, and HLN designed the experiments. NI, SH, AS, GM, SG, RD, and HLN helped to write the article. All authors contributed to the article and approved the submitted version.</p></sec><sec sec-type="funding-information" id="s9"><title>Funding</title><p>This research was supported by the Global Health Innovative Technology Fund and CBER Intramural Research Program, FDA.</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement" id="s10"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>The FDA is currently a co-owner of two US patents that claim attenuated <italic>Leishmania</italic> species with the Centrin gene deletion (US7,887,812 and US 8,877,213).</p><p>The remaining authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec><sec sec-type="disclaimer" id="s11"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p>All claims expressed in this article are solely those of the authors and do not necessarily represent those of their affiliated organizations, or those of the publisher, the editors and the reviewers. Any product that may be evaluated in this article, or claim that may be made by its manufacturer, is not guaranteed or endorsed by the publisher.</p></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s12"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fimmu.2022.864031/full#supplementary-material" ext-link-type="uri">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fimmu.2022.864031/full#supplementary-material</ext-link>
</p><supplementary-material id="SM1" position="float" content-type="local-data"><media xlink:href="Presentation_1.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="SM2" position="float" content-type="local-data"><media xlink:href="Table_1.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Valenzuela</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Belkaid</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Garfield</surname><given-names>MK</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamhawi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Rowton</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Toward a Defined Anti-Leishmania Vaccine Targeting Vector Antigens: Characterization of a Protective Salivary Protein</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source> (<year>2001</year>) <volume>194</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<page-range>331&#x02013;42</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.194.3.331</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Naouar</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Boussoffara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben Ahmed</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Belhaj Hmida</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Gharbi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gritli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Involvement of Different CD4(+) T Cell Subsets Producing Granzyme B in the Immune Response to Leishmania Major Antigens</article-title>. <source>Mediat Inflamm</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>2014</volume>:<fpage>636039</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2014/636039</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Torres-Guerrero</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Quintanilla-Cedillo</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruiz-Esmenjaud</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Arenas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Leishmaniasis: A Review</article-title>. <source>F1000Res</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>6</volume>:<fpage>750</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12688/f1000research.11120.1</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28649370</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alvar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Velez</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name><name><surname>Bern</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Herrero</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Desjeux</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cano</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Leishmaniasis Worldwide and Global Estimates of its Incidence</article-title>. <source>PloS One</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>7</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>e35671</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0035671</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22693548</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Piscopo</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name><name><surname>Mallia Azzopardi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Leishmaniasis</article-title>. <source>Postgrad Med J</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>83</volume>(<issue>976</issue>):<page-range>649&#x02013;57</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/pgmj.2006.047340corr1</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matlashewski</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Arana</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kroeger</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Be-Nazir</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mondal</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Nabi</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Research Priorities for Elimination of Visceral Leishmaniasis</article-title>. <source>Lancet Glob Health</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>2</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<page-range>e683&#x02013;4</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S2214-109X(14)70318-3</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khamesipour</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dowlati</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Asilian</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hashemi-Fesharki</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Javadi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Noazin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Leishmanization: Use of an Old Method for Evaluation of Candidate Vaccines Against Leishmaniasis</article-title>. <source>Vaccine</source> (<year>2005</year>) <volume>23</volume>(<issue>28</issue>):<page-range>3642&#x02013;8</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.vaccine.2005.02.015</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Karmakar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gannavaram</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dey</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lypaczewski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>A Second Generation Leishmanization Vaccine With a Markerless Attenuated Leishmania Major Strain Using CRISPR Gene Editing</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>11</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>3461</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-020-17154-z</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32651371</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karmakar</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ismail</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Oristian</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>WW</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaviraj</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Preclinical Validation of a Live Attenuated Dermotropic Leishmania Vaccine Against Vector Transmitted Fatal Visceral Leishmaniasis</article-title>. <source>Commun Biol</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>4</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>929</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s42003-021-02446-x</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34330999</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mueller</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackay</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Tissue-Resident Memory T Cells: Local Specialists in Immune Defence</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Immunol</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>16</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>79</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>89</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nri.2015.3</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26688350</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sathaliyawala</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubota</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yudanin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Camp</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Thome</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Distribution and Compartmentalization of Human Circulating and Tissue-Resident Memory T Cell Subsets</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>38</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<page-range>187&#x02013;97</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2012.09.020</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laidlaw</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>HD</given-names></name><name><surname>Staron</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>CD4+ T Cell Help Guides Formation of CD103+ Lung-Resident Memory CD8+ T Cells During Influenza Viral Infection</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>41</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<page-range>633&#x02013;45</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2014.09.007</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turner</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldklang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cvetkovski</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Paik</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Trischler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Barahona</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Biased Generation and <italic>In Situ</italic> Activation of Lung Tissue-Resident Memory CD4 T Cells in the Pathogenesis of Allergic Asthma</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>200</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<page-range>1561&#x02013;9</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.1700257</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watanabe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gehad</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><name><surname>Teague</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlapbach</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Human Skin Is Protected by Four Functionally and Phenotypically Discrete Populations of Resident and Recirculating Memory T Cells</article-title>. <source>Sci Transl Med</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>7</volume>(<issue>279</issue>):<fpage>279ra39</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/scitranslmed.3010302</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Szabo</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Miron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Farber</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Location, Location, Location: Tissue Resident Memory T Cells in Mice and Humans</article-title>. <source>Sci Immunol</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>4</volume>(<issue>34</issue>). doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciimmunol.aas9673</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zens</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Farber</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Vaccine-Generated Lung Tissue-Resident Memory T Cells Provide Heterosubtypic Protection to Influenza Infection</article-title>. <source>JCI Insight</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>1</volume>(<issue>10</issue>). doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/jci.insight.85832</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mangalam</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name><name><surname>Channappanavar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Fett</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyerholz</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Airway Memory CD4(+) T Cells Mediate Protective Immunity Against Emerging Respiratory Coronaviruses</article-title>. <source>Immunity</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>44</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<page-range>1379&#x02013;91</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.immuni.2016.05.006</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Suwanto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Okabe</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nochi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Imai</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Vaginal Memory T Cells Induced by Intranasal Vaccination are Critical for Protective T Cell Recruitment and Prevention of Genital HSV-2 Disease</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>88</volume>(<issue>23</issue>):<page-range>13699&#x02013;708</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.02279-14</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glennie</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeramilli</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Beiting</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><name><surname>Volk</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Skin-Resident Memory CD4+ T Cells Enhance Protection Against Leishmania Major Infection</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>212</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<page-range>1405&#x02013;14</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20142101</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glennie</surname><given-names>ND</given-names></name><name><surname>Volk</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Skin-Resident CD4+ T Cells Protect Against Leishmania Major by Recruiting and Activating Inflammatory Monocytes</article-title>. <source>PloS Pathog</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>13</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>e1006349</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1006349</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28419151</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Louis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wise</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Glennie</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Broderick</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Intradermal Synthetic DNA Vaccination Generates Leishmania-Specific T Cells in the Skin and Protection Against Leishmania Major</article-title>. <source>Infect Immun</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>87</volume>(<issue>8</issue>). doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/IAI.00227-19</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Long-Lived Skin-Resident Memory T Cells Contribute to Concomitant Immunity in Cutaneous Leishmaniasis</article-title>. <source>Cold Spring Harb Perspect Biol</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>12</volume>(<issue>10</issue>). doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/cshperspect.a038059</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strutt</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhume</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Finn</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hwang</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Castonguay</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Swain</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>IL-15 Supports the Generation of Protective Lung-Resident Memory CD4 T Cells</article-title>. <source>Mucosal Immunol</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>11</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<page-range>668&#x02013;80</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/mi.2017.101</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harrington</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Janowski</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliver</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Zajac</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Memory CD4 T Cells Emerge From Effector T-Cell Progenitors</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> (<year>2008</year>) <volume>452</volume>(<issue>7185</issue>):<page-range>356&#x02013;60</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature06672</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaid</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hor</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Christo</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Prier</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Local Proliferation Maintains a Stable Pool of Tissue-Resident Memory T Cells After Antiviral Recall Responses</article-title>. <source>Nat Immunol</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>19</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<page-range>183&#x02013;91</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41590-017-0027-5</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nguyen</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name><name><surname>Soulika</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The Dynamics of the Skin&#x02019;s Immune System</article-title>. <source>Int J Mol Sci</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>20</volume>(<issue>8</issue>). doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijms20081811</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosato</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Beura</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Masopust</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Tissue Resident Memory T Cells and Viral Immunity</article-title>. <source>Curr Opin Virol</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>22</volume>:<fpage>44</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>50</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.coviro.2016.11.011</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27987416</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hohman</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>CD4(+) T Cell-Mediated Immunity Against the Phagosomal Pathogen Leishmania: Implications for Vaccination</article-title>. <source>Trends Parasitol</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>35</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<page-range>423&#x02013;35</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pt.2019.04.002</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hohman</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mou</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Carneiro</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferland</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kratofil</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubes</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Protective CD4+ Th1 Cell-Mediated Immunity Is Reliant Upon Execution of Effector Function Prior to the Establishment of the Pathogen Niche</article-title>. <source>PloS Pathog</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>17</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>e1009944</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1009944</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34543348</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peters</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimblin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Secundino</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kamhawi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lawyer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sacks</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Vector Transmission of Leishmania Abrogates Vaccine-Induced Protective Immunity</article-title>. <source>PloS Pathog</source> (<year>2009</year>) <volume>5</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>e1000484</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.1000484</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19543375</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mackay</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahimpour</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Stock</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Hafon</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>The Developmental Pathway for CD103(+)CD8+ Tissue-Resident Memory T Cells of Skin</article-title>. <source>Nat Immunol</source> (<year>2013</year>) <volume>14</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<page-range>1294&#x02013;301</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ni.2744</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shenoy</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyon De Ana</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Arafa</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name><name><surname>Salwig</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Korkmaz</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Antigen Presentation by Lung Epithelial Cells Directs CD4(+) TRM Cell Function and Regulates Barrier Immunity</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>5834</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-021-26045-w</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34611166</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagers</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuhlbrigge</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name><name><surname>Kupper</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Skin Infection Generates non-Migratory Memory CD8+ T(RM) Cells Providing Global Skin Immunity</article-title>. <source>Nature</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>483</volume>(<issue>7388</issue>):<page-range>227&#x02013;31</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature10851</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Prier</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gebhardt</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Carbone</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackay</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cutting Edge: Tissue-Resident Memory T Cells Generated by Multiple Immunizations or Localized Deposition Provide Enhanced Immunity</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>198</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<page-range>2233&#x02013;7</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.1601367</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sather</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Treuting</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Perdue</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Miazgowicz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fontenot</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudensky</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Altering the Distribution of Foxp3(+) Regulatory T Cells Results in Tissue-Specific Inflammatory Disease</article-title>. <source>J Exp Med</source> (<year>2007</year>) <volume>204</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<page-range>1335&#x02013;47</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1084/jem.20070081</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Suffia</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Reckling</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Salay</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Belkaid</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>A Role for CD103 in the Retention of CD4+CD25+ Treg and Control of Leishmania Major Infection</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source> (<year>2005</year>) <volume>174</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<page-range>5444&#x02013;55</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.174.9.5444</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barros</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Veldhoen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>The Fellowship of Regulatory and Tissue-Resident Memory Cells</article-title>. <source>Mucosal Immunol</source> (<year>2022</year>) <volume>15</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>64</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41385-021-00456-w</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34608235</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Piconese</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Campello</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Natalini</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Recirculation and Residency of T Cells and Tregs: Lessons Learnt in Anacapri</article-title>. <source>Front Immunol</source> (<year>2020</year>) <volume>11</volume>:<elocation-id>682</elocation-id>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2020.00682</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32431695</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zaid</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hor</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Christo</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Groom</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Heath</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackay</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Chemokine Receptor-Dependent Control of Skin Tissue-Resident Memory T Cell Formation</article-title>. <source>J Immunol</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>199</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<page-range>2451&#x02013;9</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4049/jimmunol.1700571</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Griffith</surname><given-names>JW</given-names></name><name><surname>Sokol</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Luster</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Chemokines and Chemokine Receptors: Positioning Cells for Host Defense and Immunity</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Immunol</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>32</volume>:<fpage>659</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>702</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-immunol-032713-120145</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24655300</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zaid</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Mackay</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahimpour</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Braun</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Veldhoen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Carbone</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Persistence of Skin-Resident Memory T Cells Within an Epidermal Niche</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>111</volume>(<issue>14</issue>):<page-range>5307&#x02013;12</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1322292111</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Tissue-Specific Control of Tissue-Resident Memory T Cells</article-title>. <source>Crit Rev Immunol</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>38</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>79</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>103</lpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1615/CritRevImmunol.2018025653</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29953389</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christo</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Evrard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gandolfo</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Burn</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name><name><surname>Fonseca</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Discrete Tissue Microenvironments Instruct Diversity in Resident Memory T Cell Function and Plasticity</article-title>. <source>Nat Immunol</source> (<year>2021</year>) <volume>22</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<page-range>1140&#x02013;51</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41590-021-01004-1</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ariotti</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Haanen</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Schumacher</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Behavior and Function of Tissue-Resident Memory T Cells</article-title>. <source>Adv Immunol</source> (<year>2012</year>) <volume>114</volume>:<page-range>203&#x02013;16</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-396548-6.00008-1</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Couturier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Medina</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kozinetz</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Granzyme B Secretion by Human Memory CD4 T Cells is Less Strictly Regulated Compared to Memory CD8 T Cells</article-title>. <source>BMC Immunol</source> (<year>2014</year>) <volume>15</volume>:<fpage>36</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12865-014-0036-1</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25245659</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Juno</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>van Bockel</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kent</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelleher</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaunders</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Munier</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cytotoxic CD4 T Cells-Friend or Foe During Viral Infection</article-title>? <source>Front Immunol</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<elocation-id>19</elocation-id>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fimmu.2017.00019</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28167943</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boussoffara</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chelif</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben Ahmed</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Mokni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben Salah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dellagi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Immunity Against Leishmania Major Infection: Parasite-Specific Granzyme B Induction as a Correlate of Protection</article-title>. <source>Front Cell Infect Microbiol</source> (<year>2018</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<elocation-id>397</elocation-id>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fcimb.2018.00397</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30483482</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nizard</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Roussel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Diniz</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Karaki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Tran</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Voron</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Induction of Resident Memory T Cells Enhances the Efficacy of Cancer Vaccine</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source> (<year>2017</year>) <volume>8</volume>:<fpage>15221</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncomms15221</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28537262</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rosato</surname><given-names>PC</given-names></name><name><surname>Wijeyesinghe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stolley</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Manlove</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Virus-Specific Memory T Cells Populate Tumors and can be Repurposed for Tumor Immunotherapy</article-title>. <source>Nat Commun</source> (<year>2019</year>) <volume>10</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>567</fpage>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41467-019-08534-1</pub-id>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30718505</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Garron</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Lubaki</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mire</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Fenton</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Klages</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Aerosolized Ebola Vaccine Protects Primates and Elicits Lung-Resident T Cell Responses</article-title>. <source>J Clin Invest</source> (<year>2015</year>) <volume>125</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<page-range>3241&#x02013;55</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI81532</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Belyakov</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuznetsov</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelsall</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Klinman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Moniuszko</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. <article-title>Impact of Vaccine-Induced Mucosal High-Avidity CD8+ CTLs in Delay of AIDS Viral Dissemination From Mucosa</article-title>. <source>Blood</source> (<year>2006</year>) <volume>107</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<page-range>3258&#x02013;64</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1182/blood-2005-11-4374</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Novais</surname><given-names>FO</given-names></name></person-group>. <article-title>Cutaneous Leishmaniasis: Immune Responses in Protection and Pathogenesis</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Immunol</source> (<year>2016</year>) <volume>16</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<page-range>581&#x02013;92</page-range>. doi: <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nri.2016.72</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>