<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.6.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art560.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.6.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_JACCAO404 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEmain pdf ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?FILEgr2 jpg ?><?FILEgr3 jpg ?><?FILEgr4 jpg ?><?FILEgr5 jpg ?><?FILEfx1 jpg ?><?FILEmmc1 docx ?><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">JACC CardioOncol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">JACC CardioOncol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>JACC: CardioOncology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2666-0873</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">9830219</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2666-0873(22)00456-2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaccao.2022.09.005</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>LAG3 Regulates T Cell Activation and Plaque Infiltration in Atherosclerotic Mice</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au1"><name><surname>Mulholland</surname><given-names>Megan</given-names></name><degrees>MSc</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">&#x02217;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au2"><name><surname>Kritikou</surname><given-names>Eva</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref><xref rid="fn1" ref-type="fn">&#x02217;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au3"><name><surname>Katra</surname><given-names>Pernilla</given-names></name><degrees>MSc</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au4"><name><surname>Nilsson</surname><given-names>Jan</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au5"><name><surname>Bj&#x000f6;rkbacka</surname><given-names>Harry</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au6"><name><surname>Lichtman</surname><given-names>Andrew H.</given-names></name><degrees>MD, PhD</degrees><xref rid="aff2" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au7"><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>Annabelle</given-names></name><degrees>MD</degrees><email>rodriguezoquendo@uchc.edu</email><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://twitter.com/HDLHeart">@HDLHeart</ext-link><xref rid="aff3" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="cor2" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;&#x02217;</xref><xref rid="fn2" ref-type="fn">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au8"><name><surname>Engelbertsen</surname><given-names>Daniel</given-names></name><degrees>PhD</degrees><email>daniel.engelbertsen@med.lu.se</email><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://twitter.com/EngelbertsenLab">@EngelbertsenLab</ext-link><xref rid="aff1" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor1" ref-type="corresp">&#x02217;</xref><xref rid="fn2" ref-type="fn">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>a</label>Department of Clinical Sciences, Malm&#x000f6;, Cardiovascular Research - Cellular Metabolism and Inflammation, Lund University, Malm&#x000f6;, Sweden</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>b</label>Department of Pathology, Brigham and Women&#x02019;s Hospital, Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts, USA</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>c</label>Center for Vascular Biology, University of Connecticut Health, Farmington, Connecticut, USA</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>&#x02217;</label><bold>Address for correspondence:</bold> Dr Daniel Engelbertsen, Jan Waldenstr&#x000f6;ms Gata 35, Experimental Cardiovascular Research, CRC 91:12, Box 50 332, 202 13 Malm&#x000f6;, Sweden. <email>daniel.engelbertsen@med.lu.se</email><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://twitter.com/EngelbertsenLab">@EngelbertsenLab</ext-link></corresp><corresp id="cor2"><label>&#x02217;&#x02217;</label>Dr Annabelle Rodriguez, University of Connecticut Health, 263 Farmington Avenue, Farmington, Connecticut 06030, USA. <email>rodriguezoquendo@uchc.edu</email><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://twitter.com/HDLHeart">@HDLHeart</ext-link></corresp><fn id="fn1"><label>&#x02217;</label><p id="ntpara0010">Ms Mulholland and Dr Kritikou contributed equally to this work as joint first authors.</p></fn><fn id="fn2"><label>&#x02020;</label><p id="ntpara0015">Drs Rodriguez and Engelbertsen contributed equally to this work as joint last authors.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>20</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>12</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>12</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>635</fpage><lpage>645</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>5</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>27</day><month>9</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>9</month><year>2022</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2022 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2022</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="abs0010"><sec><title>Background</title><p>The immune checkpoint receptor lymphocyte-activation gene 3 (LAG3) is a new target for immune checkpoint blockade (ICB), but the effects of LAG3 on atherosclerosis are not known.</p></sec><sec><title>Objectives</title><p>The aim of the study was to evaluate the role of LAG3 on plaque inflammation using murine hypercholesterolemic models of atherosclerosis.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>To study the role of LAG3 in atherosclerosis, we investigated both bone marrow chimeras lacking LAG3 in hematopoietic cells as well as global <italic>Lag3</italic><sup><italic>-/-</italic></sup> knockout mice. Effects of anti-LAG3 monoclonal antibody monotherapy and combination therapy with anti-programmed cell death protein 1 (PD-1) were tested in hypercholesterolemic low-density lipoprotein receptor knockout (<italic>Ldlr</italic><sup><italic>-/-</italic></sup>) mice and evaluated by histology and flow cytometry.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>LAG3-deficiency or treatment with blocking anti-LAG3 monoclonal antibodies led to increased levels of both interferon gamma&#x02013;producing T helper 1 cells and effector/memory T cells, balanced by increased levels of regulatory T&#x000a0;cells. Plaque size was affected by neither LAG3 deficiency nor LAG3 blockade, although density of T cells in plaques was 2-fold increased by loss of LAG3. Combination therapy of anti-PD-1 and anti-LAG3 had an additive effect on T cell activation and cytokine production and promoted plaque infiltration of T cells.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p>Loss of LAG3 function promoted T cell activation and accumulation in plaques while not affecting plaque burden. Our report supports further clinical studies investigating cardiovascular risk in patients treated with anti-LAG3 ICB.</p></sec></abstract><abstract abstract-type="graphical" id="abs0015"><title>Central Illustration</title><fig id="undfig1" position="anchor"><graphic xlink:href="fx1"/></fig></abstract><kwd-group id="kwrds0010"><title>Key Words</title><kwd>atherosclerosis</kwd><kwd>cardiovascular disease</kwd><kwd>immune checkpoint blockade</kwd><kwd>inflammation</kwd><kwd>T cells</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group id="kwrds0015"><title>Abbreviations and Acronyms</title><kwd>CTLA-4, cytotoxic T lymphocyte associated protein 4</kwd><kwd>HCD, high-cholesterol diet</kwd><kwd>ICB, immune checkpoint blockade</kwd><kwd>IFN, interferon</kwd><kwd>IL, interleukin</kwd><kwd>LAG3, lymphocyte-activation gene 3</kwd><kwd>PD-1, programmed cell death protein-1</kwd><kwd>PD-L1, programmed death-ligand 1</kwd><kwd>TNF, tumor necrosis factor</kwd><kwd>Treg, regulatory T cell</kwd><kwd>WT, wild-type</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p id="p0010">Immune checkpoint blockade (ICB) targeting T&#x000a0;cell&#x02013;inhibitory pathways (cytotoxic T lymphocyte associated protein 4 [CTLA-4], programmed cell death protein 1 [PD-1] and programmed death-ligand 1 [PD-L1]) has proven successful as treatment for several types of tumors. The mechanisms of action of ICB are not completely understood, and likely varies between ICB targets, but converges on alleviating T cell inhibition in the tumor to allow for efficient antitumor responses.<xref rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> Immune checkpoint molecules serve an important physiological role in regulating adaptive immune response, and ICB treatment has been shown to induce autoimmunity and tissue inflammation.<xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>, <xref rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></p><p id="p0015">Atherosclerosis is a chronic disease with involvement of both innate and adaptive immunity.<xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref> Previous work in hypercholesterolemic mice has shown that genetic loss of PD-1 or PD-L1 aggravates atherosclerosis and promotes vascular inflammation as indicated by increased vascular T cell accumulation.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Treatment with a combination of anti-PD-1 and anti-CTLA-4 antibodies likewise led to increased T cell accumulation in atherosclerotic plaques<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> and ICB treatment in cancer patients was associated with a 3-fold increased risk of cardiovascular disease.<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref></p><p id="p0020">A new target for ICB in cancer is lymphocyte-activation gene 3 (LAG3) that is expressed on several leukocyte subsets, including T cells.<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref> LAG3 is upregulated upon activation of T cells but proteolytically cleaved by ADAMT10/17 proteases,<xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr"><sup>12</sup></xref> and expressed at higher levels on exhausted T cells.<xref rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr"><sup>13</sup></xref> LAG3 interacts with several receptors including major histocompatibility complex II and galectin-3 and negatively modulates T cell activation and proliferation.<xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr"><sup>11</sup></xref></p><p id="p0025">Demonstrating an important immunoregulatory role of LAG3 in&#x000a0;vivo, genetic knockdown of LAG3 in mice results in increased susceptibility to autoimmune diseases such as type 1 diabetes.<xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr"><sup>14</sup></xref> Recently, the RELATIVITY-047 (Study of relatlimab plus nivolumab versus nivolumab alone in participants with advanced melanoma) trial demonstrated that treatment with a monoclonal antibody against LAG3 (relatimab) in combination with anti-PD-1 (nivolumab) was superior to nivolumab monotherapy in patients with untreated advanced melanoma,<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> and the combination therapy of anti-LAG3/anti-PD-1 (Opdualag) is now approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration for clinical use. Given previous reports of ICB-induced vascular inflammation, a key outstanding question is what role LAG3 plays in regulating cardiovascular inflammation. In this report, we investigated the role of LAG3 in atherosclerosis and potential synergistic effects of dual LAG3/PD-1 blockade utilizing complementary mouse models of atherosclerosis.</p><sec id="sec1"><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec1.1"><title>Mice</title><p id="p0030">Mice in this study were bred and housed in the pathogen-free facility at the New Research Building (Harvard Medical School, Boston, Massachusetts, USA) or Lund University (Malm&#x000f6;, Sweden). All vertebrate animal related procedures were approved and were carried out in accordance with the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee or approved by local government agencies in Sweden. Ethical permits were obtained before conducting any experiments. <italic>Lag3</italic><sup><italic>-/-</italic></sup> mice originally derived by Miyazaki et&#x000a0;al,<xref rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr"><sup>16</sup></xref> were generously provided by Dr Dario Vignali (University of Pittsburgh). Studies were conducted using both male and female mice.</p></sec><sec id="sec1.2"><title>Bone marrow transplantation</title><p id="p0035">Eleven-week-old male and female <italic>Ldlr</italic><sup><italic>-/-</italic></sup> mice were subjected to 950&#x000a0;rad of total body irradiation and reconstituted with 1&#x000a0;&#x000d7; 10<sup>6</sup> bone marrow cells from <italic>Lag3</italic><sup><italic>-/-</italic></sup> or wild-type (WT) mice. Bone marrow recipients received sulfamethoxazole/trimethoprim (Sulfatrim) treatment in drinking water for 1&#x000a0;week prior to and 4&#x000a0;weeks following bone marrow transplantation. All animals were allowed to recover on a chow diet for 4&#x000a0;weeks after bone marrow transplantation and then fed a high-cholesterol diet (HCD) containing 1.25% cholesterol (catalog no. D1218C; Research Diets) for 10&#x000a0;weeks until the end of the experiment.</p></sec><sec id="sec1.3"><title>Adeno-associated viral administration of murine&#x000a0;proprotein convertase subtilisin/kexin type 9</title><p id="p0040">AAV-PCSK9 <sup>D374Y</sup> was administered as previously described.<xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr"><sup>17</sup></xref> In brief, 9-week-old female and male WT (C57BL/6) or <italic>Lag3</italic><sup><italic>-/-</italic></sup> (C57BL/6 background) mice were given a single dose of AAV-PCSK9 <sup>D374Y</sup> (5&#x02009;&#x000d7;&#x02009;10<sup>11</sup> genome copies/injection) and fed an HCD for 10&#x000a0;weeks.</p></sec><sec id="sec1.4"><title>Immune checkpoint blockade</title><p id="p0045">For studies investigating the effect of anti-LAG3 monotherapy on atherosclerosis, 9-week-old <italic>Ldlr</italic><sup><italic>-/-</italic></sup> mice were fed an HCD for a total of 10&#x000a0;weeks, and anti-LAG3 (clone: C9B7W; BioXCell) or control immunoglobulin G1 (IgG1) (clone: HRPN; BioXCell) were administered (0.2&#x000a0;mg/dose) twice a week for the last 4&#x000a0;weeks. In an additional experiment, 8- to 12-week-old apolipoprotein E&#x02013;deficient (<italic>Apoe</italic><sup><italic>-/-</italic></sup> mice) were fed an HCD for 5&#x000a0;weeks and treated for the last 3&#x000a0;weeks with anti-LAG3 (clone: C9B7W; BioXCell) or control IgG1 (clone: HRPN; BioXCell) (0.2&#x000a0;mg/dose) twice a week. For studies investigating the effect of anti-LAG3/anti-PD-1 therapy, 7- to 9-week-old <italic>Ldlr</italic><sup><italic>-/-</italic></sup> mice were fed an HCD for a total of 6&#x000a0;weeks, and 0.2&#x000a0;mg anti-PD-1 (clone: 29F.1A12; BioXCell), 0.2&#x000a0;mg anti-PD-1 and 0.2 anti-LAG3, or combined isotype control 0.2&#x000a0;mg IgG1/0.2&#x000a0;mg IgG2a (clones: HRPN and 2A3) were administered twice a week for the last 4&#x000a0;weeks.</p></sec><sec id="sec1.5"><title>Histology</title><p id="p0050">Oil Red O (Sigma-Aldrich) staining with&#x000a0;hematoxylin counterstained was performed to visualize neutral lipids and allow for quantification of atherosclerotic lesions. Van Gieson staining kit (Sigma-Aldrich) was utilized to stain plaque collagen. To quantify CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells and macrophages in lesions, sections were stained using anti-CD4 as primary antibody (Cat. No. 550280; BD Pharmingen) or anti-Mac-3 (M3/84, Cat. No. 550292; BD Pharmingen), respectively, and biotinylated rabbit anti-rat IgG (Cat. No. BA-4001; Vector Laboratories) as the secondary antibody. Sections were incubated with streptavidin-HRP (Cat. No. K0675; DAKO), and the reaction was visualized using AEC Substrate Chromogen (Cat. No. K3464; DAKO). To visualize the nuclei, sections were counterstained using Gill&#x02019;s hematoxylin. CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells were quantified by manually counting the stained cells. Adventitial tissue was identified as the area extending outward from the external elastic lamina not including myocardium. Assessment of plaque morphology was performed blinded using the Virmani classification.<xref rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr"><sup>18</sup></xref></p></sec><sec id="sec1.6"><title>Flow cytometry</title><p id="p0055">Single-cell suspensions were analyzed by flow cytometry using the following antibodies: CD3 (17A2), CD4 (RM4-4), CD8 (53&#x02013;6.7), CD44 (IM7), CD62L (MEL14) and CD25 (PC61), and PD-1 (29F.1A12). Zombie Aqua fixable viability dye (Cat. No. 423102) was used to remove dead cells. Anti-CD16/CD32 was added to antibody mix to block nonspecific monoclonal antibody binding. Fluorescence activated cell sorting buffer containing 0.5% bovine serum albumin and 0.02% sodium azide in phosphate-buffered saline without Ca<sup>2+</sup> and Mg<sup>2+</sup> was used for all the washing steps. To measure intracellular cytokines or other intracellular proteins, splenocytes or cells obtained from aortic digestion were stimulated with cell activation cocktail containing phorbol myristate acetate, ionomycin, and Brefeldin A (Cat No. 423303; BioLegend). Cells were fixed and permeabilized using a fixation and permeabilization kit (Cat. No. 88-8824-00; eBioscience) and subsequently stained with anti-interferon (IFN)-&#x003b3; (XMG1.2), anti-interleukin (IL)-2 (JES6-5H4), and anti-tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-&#x003b1; (MP6-XT22). For T&#x000a0;regulatory cell (Treg) and Ki67 proliferation analysis, unstimulated cells were fixed and permeabilized followed by Ki67 (16A8) and FoxP3 (FJK-16S) staining. Fluorescence activated cell sorting analysis was performed on a DxP11 or Gallios flow cytometer, and the data were analyzed using FlowJo software (FlowJo v10.8.0, LLC).</p></sec><sec id="sec1.7"><title>Statistics</title><p id="p0060">Data were tested for normal distribution using Kolmogorov-Smirnov normality test. Data comparing 2 groups were analyzed with unpaired 2-tailed Student&#x02019;s <italic>t</italic> test or Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test. Data comparing 3 groups were analyzed with analysis of variance and Tukey&#x02019;s multiple comparison test or Kruskal-Wallis test and Dunn&#x02019;s multiple comparison tests. A <italic>P</italic> value of&#x000a0;&#x0003c;0.05 was determined as significant. Statistical analysis was performed using GraphPad Prism v7 software (GraphPad Software). Dots represent individual mice and bars denote median in all graphs.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec2"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec2.1"><title>LAG3 regulates T cell activation and accumulation of plaque T cells but does not affect plaque burden</title><p id="p0065">To evaluate the role of LAG3 in atherosclerosis, we performed several complementary models of experimental atherosclerosis. First, <italic>Ldlr</italic><sup><italic>-/-</italic></sup> recipient mice were irradiated and reconstituted with bone marrow from WT C57BL/6 (WT) or <italic>Lag3</italic><sup><italic>-/-</italic></sup> donors to generate bone marrow chimeras (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;14/group). After 10&#x000a0;weeks of HCD feeding, mice were terminated and the cardiovascular and immunological phenotype investigated (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1A</xref>). As compared with recipient mice reconstituted with WT donor bone marrow cells, recipient mice reconstituted with <italic>Lag3</italic><sup><italic>-/-</italic></sup> donor cells showed increased levels of CD44<sup>hi</sup>CD62L<sup>-</sup> CD4<sup>+</sup> and CD8<sup>+</sup> T effector cells, as well as increased levels of CD25<sup>+</sup>FoxP3<sup>+</sup> Tregs (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figures 1B to 1D</xref>). Similarly, levels of circulating CD44<sup>hi</sup>CD62L<sup>-</sup> CD4<sup>+</sup> and CD8<sup>+</sup> T effector cells were also increased in recipient mice reconstituted with <italic>Lag3</italic><sup><italic>-/-</italic></sup> donor cells compared with WT donor cells (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplemental Figures&#x000a0;1A</xref> and <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">1B</xref>). Weight, total cholesterol, low-density lipoprotein and high-density lipoprotein levels were not affected by LAG3 deficiency (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplemental Figures&#x000a0;1C to 1F</xref>). Analysis of subvalvular and descending aortic atherosclerotic plaques revealed no difference in plaque burden (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figures&#x000a0;1E</xref> and <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1F</xref>), and we observed no change in collagen (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1G</xref>) or macrophage content (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplemental Figure&#x000a0;1G</xref>). Categorization of plaque morphology (intimal thickening, intimal xanthoma, pathological intimal thickening, and fibrous cap atheroma) did not reveal any differences between groups (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplemental Figure&#x000a0;1H</xref>). However, levels of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cell accumulation in aortic plaques and vascular adventitia were 2-fold (<italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c; 0.05) increased in <italic>Lag3</italic><sup><italic>-/-</italic></sup> bone marrow recipients compared with WT control mice (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figures&#x000a0;1H</xref> and <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1I</xref>). To validate our findings using a complementary model of atherosclerosis, WT or <italic>Lag3</italic><sup><italic>-/-</italic></sup> mice were injected with adeno-associated virus encoding a gain-of-function variant of proprotein convertase subtilisin/kexin type 9 (AAV-PSCK9<sup>DY</sup>)<xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr"><sup>19</sup></xref> to induce hypercholesterolemia upon HCD feeding (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figures&#x000a0;1J</xref> and <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">1K</xref>). Similarly, in the context of AAV-PSCK9<sup>DY</sup>&#x02013;induced hypercholesterolemia, T cell activation was increased in <italic>Lag3</italic><sup><italic>-/-</italic></sup> compared with WT mice, but plaque burden and plaque morphology remained unchanged (<xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figures&#x000a0;1L and 1M</xref>, <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplemental Figures&#x000a0;1I</xref> and <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">1J</xref>).<fig id="fig1"><label>Figure&#x000a0;1</label><caption><p>Impact of LAG3 Deficiency on T Cell Activation and Atherosclerosis</p><p><bold>(A)</bold> Irradiated low-density lipoprotein knockout mice (<italic>Ldlr</italic><sup><italic>-/-</italic></sup><italic>)</italic> mice received wild-type (WT) (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;14) or lymphocyte-activation gene 3 (LAG3) knockout (<italic>Lag3</italic><sup><italic>-/-</italic></sup>) (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;14) bone marrow transplantation (BMT) and were fed a high-cholesterol diet (HCD) for 10&#x000a0;weeks to study atherosclerosis. <bold>(B-D)</bold> Levels of CD4<sup>+</sup> and CD8<sup>+</sup> CD44<sup>hi</sup>CD62L<sup>-</sup> T effector cells and CD25<sup>+</sup>FoxP3<sup>+</sup> regulatory T cells in spleen. <bold>(E)</bold> Histological quantification of subvalvular plaque area and representative Oil Red O&#x02013;stained images. Scale bar&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m. <bold>(F)</bold> En face analysis of descending aorta and representative images. <bold>(G)</bold> Van Gieson collagen staining and representative images. Scale&#x000a0;bar&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m. <bold>(H, I)</bold> Immunohistochemical staining for CD4 and quantification of lesional and adventitial CD4<sup>+</sup> cells per mm<sup>2</sup>. Scale bar =50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m. <bold>(J)</bold> Adeno-associated viral administration of murine proprotein convertase subtilisin/kexin type 9 (AAV-mPCSK9<sup>D374Y</sup>) to WT or <italic>Lag3</italic><sup><italic>-/-</italic></sup> mice followed by 10&#x000a0;weeks of HCD. <bold>(K)</bold> Cholesterol levels in plasma. <bold>(L)</bold> Levels of CD4<sup>+</sup> CD44<sup>+</sup>CD62L<sup>-</sup> T effector cells in spleen. <bold>(M)</bold> Histological quantification of subvalvular plaque area and representative Oil Red O&#x02013;stained images. Scale bar =100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m. An unpaired <italic>t</italic> test was used to analyze normally distributed data and a Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test was used for non-normally distributed data. &#x02217;<italic>P&#x000a0;&#x0003c;</italic> 0.05, &#x02217;&#x02217;<italic>P&#x000a0;&#x0003c;</italic> 0.01, &#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;<italic>P&#x000a0;&#x0003c;</italic> 0.001.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec2.2"><title>LAG3 blockade promotes T cell activation and promotes PD-1 expression</title><p id="p0070">To test cardiovascular and immunoregulatory effects of LAG3 blockade, <italic>Ldlr</italic><sup><italic>-/-</italic></sup> mice were injected with anti-LAG3 monoclonal antibodies for the last 4&#x000a0;weeks of a total 10&#x000a0;weeks on an HCD (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;12/group) (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;2A</xref>). Similar as to what was observed in <italic>Lag3</italic><sup><italic>-/-</italic></sup> mice, LAG3 blockade led to increased fractions of CD44<sup>hi</sup>CD62L<sup>-</sup> CD4<sup>+</sup> T effector cells and elevated levels of FoxP3<sup>+</sup> Tregs (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figures&#x000a0;2B</xref> and <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2C</xref>) in spleen and aorta-draining lymph nodes, as well as increased levels of CD44<sup>hi</sup>CD62L<sup>-</sup> CD8<sup>+</sup> T effector cells in spleen but not in aorta-draining lymph nodes (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplemental Figure&#x000a0;2A</xref>). Similarly, both conventional T cells (FoxP3<sup>-</sup>) and Tregs (FoxP3<sup>+</sup>) displayed increased fractions of Ki67<sup>+</sup> cells in anti-LAG3 treated mice (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;2D</xref>, <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplemental Figure&#x000a0;2B</xref>). Furthermore, LAG3 blockade resulted in increased levels of IFN-&#x003b3;&#x02013;producing T helper 1 cells (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;2E</xref>). Analysis of atherosclerotic plaque burden revealed no change in plaque burden or plaque morphology after anti-LAG3 treatment (<xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;2F</xref>, <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplemental Figure&#x000a0;2C</xref>).<fig id="fig2"><label>Figure&#x000a0;2</label><caption><p>Anti-LAG3 Treatment Expands T Helper 1 Cells and Regulatory T Cells</p><p><bold>(A)</bold> Low-density lipoprotein knockout mice (<italic>Ldlr</italic><sup><italic>-/-</italic></sup>) were fed an HCD for 10&#x000a0;weeks and injected with 0.2&#x000a0;mg isotype control (ctrl) immunoglobulin G (IgG) (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;12) or anti-LAG3 (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;12) twice a week for 4&#x000a0;weeks. <bold>(B, C)</bold> CD4<sup>+</sup> CD44<sup>hi</sup>CD62L<sup>-</sup> effector cells or CD4<sup>+</sup>CD25<sup>+</sup>FoxP3<sup>+</sup> regulatory T cells (Tregs) were quantified in spleen (SPL) or aortic lymph nodes (aLN). <bold>(D)</bold> Levels of the proliferation marker Ki67 were measured in CD4<sup>+</sup> conventional T cells (FoxP3<sup>-</sup> T<sub>conv</sub>) or Tregs (FoxP3<sup>+</sup> Tregs) in SPL. <bold>(E)</bold>&#x000a0;Levels of interferon (IFN)-&#x003b3;&#x02013;producing T helper 1 (Th1) cells in SPL. <bold>(F)</bold> Histological quantification of subvalvular plaque area and representative Oil Red O&#x02013;stained images. Scale bar&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;100&#x000a0;&#x003bc;m. An unpaired <italic>t</italic> test was used to analyze normally distributed data and a Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test was used for non-normally distributed data. &#x02217;<italic>P&#x000a0;&#x0003c;</italic> 0.05, &#x02217;&#x02217;<italic>P&#x000a0;&#x0003c;</italic> 0.01, &#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;<italic>P&#x000a0;&#x0003c;</italic> 0.001. Abbreviations as in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p><p id="p0075">LAG3 has been demonstrated to be expressed on exhausted PD-1&#x02013;expressing T cells in the context of cancer and chronic infections.<xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr"><sup>20</sup></xref> In a separate experiment to evaluate if LAG3 blockade in atherosclerotic mice impacts expression of immunoregulatory PD-1, apolipoprotein E&#x02013;deficient (<italic>Apoe</italic><sup><italic>-/-</italic></sup>) mice were fed HCD for 6&#x000a0;weeks and treated with anti-LAG3 for the last 3&#x000a0;weeks (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;7/group). Notably, LAG3 blockade expanded a population of CD44<sup>+</sup>PD-1<sup>int</sup> (intermediate) T cells of both CD4<sup>+</sup> and CD8<sup>+</sup> subsets (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figures&#x000a0;3A&#x000a0;to 3C</xref>). ICB treatment (eg, anti-PD-1) has been shown to expand IFN-&#x003b3;&#x02013;producing CD8<sup>+</sup> T cell subsets that retain capacity to produce multiple other cytokines besides IFN-&#x003b3;.<xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr"><sup>21</sup></xref> Suggesting a similar immunostimulatory function of anti-LAG3 antibodies, we observed increased levels of IL-2/TNF-&#x003b1; coproduction by IFN-&#x003b3;&#x02013;producing CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells after anti-LAG3 treatment (<xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">Figures&#x000a0;3D</xref> and <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3E</xref>). Analyzing IL-2 and TNF-&#x003b1; separately, IL-2 production by IFN-&#x003b3;&#x02013;producing CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells was upregulated, whereas TNF-&#x003b1; production was not affected (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplemental Figure&#x000a0;3A</xref>). We did not observe any change in the ability of T helper 1 cells to produce IL-2 or TNF-&#x003b1; after anti-LAG3 blockade (<xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplemental Figures&#x000a0;3B to 3D</xref>).<fig id="fig3"><label>Figure&#x000a0;3</label><caption><p>Anti-LAG3 Treatment Promotes PD-1 Expression and IL-2 Production</p><p>Apolipoprotein E&#x02013;deficient mice (<italic>Apoe</italic><sup><italic>-/-</italic></sup>) fed an HCD for 6&#x000a0;weeks and injected with 0.2&#x000a0;mg isotype ctrl IgG (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;12) or anti-LAG3 (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;12) twice a week for 3&#x000a0;weeks and SPLs were analyzed. <bold>(A)</bold> Representative flow cytometry plots of CD4<sup>+</sup><bold>(top)</bold> and CD8<sup>+</sup><bold>(bottom)</bold> T cells analyzed for CD44 and programmed cell death protein 1 (PD-1). <bold>(B, C)</bold> Quantification of CD4<sup>+</sup>- and CD8<sup>+</sup>-naive (CD44<sup>-</sup>PD1<sup>-</sup>), CD44<sup>+</sup>PD-1<sup>-</sup>, CD44<sup>hi</sup>PD-1<sup>int</sup> (intermediate), and CD44<sup>+</sup>PD-1<sup>hi</sup> (high) populations. <bold>(D)</bold> Representative flow cytometry plots of interleukin (IL)-2 and tumor necrosis factor (TNF)-&#x003b1; gated on IFN-&#x003b3;<sup>+</sup> CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells. <bold>(E)</bold> Quantification of IL-2 and TNF-&#x003b1; production of IFN-&#x003b3;<sup>+</sup>CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells. An unpaired <italic>t</italic> test was used to analyze normally distributed data and a Mann-Whitney <italic>U</italic> test was used for non-normally distributed data. &#x02217;<italic>P&#x000a0;&#x0003c;</italic> 0.05, &#x02217;&#x02217;<italic>P&#x000a0;&#x0003c;</italic> 0.01, &#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;<italic>P&#x000a0;&#x0003c;</italic> 0.001. Abbreviations as in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figures&#x000a0;1</xref> and <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr3"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="sec2.3"><title>Additive effect of LAG3 and PD-1 blockade in activating T cells in atherosclerotic mice</title><p id="p0080">Of relevance to the recently approved anti-LAG3/anti-PD-1 combination therapy in patients with melanoma,<xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr"><sup>15</sup></xref> we tested the immunological and cardiovascular outcomes of combination therapy in atherosclerotic mice. <italic>Ldlr</italic><sup><italic>-/-</italic></sup> mice were fed HCD for 6&#x000a0;weeks and treated with control IgG, anti-PD-1 monotherapy, or anti-PD-1/anti-LAG3 combination therapy for the last 4&#x000a0;weeks (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;7-9/group) (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;4A</xref>). Results showed a striking additive effect of anti-LAG3 combined with anti-PD-1 for promoting CD44<sup>hi</sup>CD62L<sup>-</sup> T effector cell expansion and IFN-&#x003b3; production of both CD4<sup>+</sup> and CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figures&#x000a0;4B to 4F</xref>, <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplemental Figure&#x000a0;4A</xref>), compared with anti-PD-1 monotherapy or control IgG. Levels of Tregs were also expanded by anti-PD-1/anti-LAG3 combination therapy (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;4G</xref>). Cholesterol levels were not affected by ICB treatment (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;4H</xref>). Analyzing the atherosclerotic plaques, neither anti-PD-1 monotherapy nor anti-PD-1/anti-LAG3 combination therapy influenced plaque burden or plaque morphology (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figure&#x000a0;4I</xref>, <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplemental Figure&#x000a0;4B</xref>). However, accumulation of lesional and adventitial CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells were increased by anti-LAG3/anti-PD-1 combination therapy (<xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">Figures&#x000a0;4J</xref> and <xref rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">4K</xref>, <xref rid="mmc1" ref-type="supplementary-material">Supplemental Figure&#x000a0;4C</xref>).<fig id="fig4"><label>Figure&#x000a0;4</label><caption><p>Additive Effects of Anti-LAG3/Anti-PD-1 Combination Therapy on Immune Activation in Atherosclerotic Mice</p><p><bold>(A)</bold> Low-density lipoprotein knockout mice (<italic>Ldlr</italic><sup><italic>-/-</italic></sup>) were fed an HCD for 6&#x000a0;weeks and injected with 0.2&#x000a0;mg isotype ctrl IgG (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;7), anti-PD-1 (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9) or anti-PD-1&#x000a0;+ anti-LAG3 (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9) twice a week for 4&#x000a0;weeks. <bold>(B, C)</bold> Representative flow cytometry plots and quantification of splenic CD4<sup>+</sup> CD44<sup>hi</sup>CD62L<sup>-</sup> effector cells. <bold>(D)</bold> Levels of CD8<sup>+</sup> CD44<sup>hi</sup>CD62L<sup>-</sup> effector cells. <bold>(E, F)</bold> Quantification of IFN-&#x003b3;&#x02013;producing CD4<sup>+</sup> and CD8<sup>+</sup> T cells. <bold>(G)</bold> Levels of CD4<sup>+</sup>CD25<sup>+</sup>FoxP3<sup>+</sup> Tregs. <bold>(H)</bold> Levels of plasma cholesterol. <bold>(I)</bold> Quantification of subvalvular plaque area. <bold>(J, K)</bold> Quantification of CD4<sup>+</sup> T cells in lesions and adventitia. Analysis of variance and Tukey&#x02019;s multiple comparison test or Kruskal-Wallis test and Dunn&#x02019;s multiple comparison tests. &#x02217;<italic>P&#x000a0;&#x0003c;</italic> 0.05, &#x02217;&#x02217;<italic>P&#x000a0;&#x0003c;</italic> 0.01, &#x02217;&#x02217;&#x02217;<italic>P&#x000a0;&#x0003c;</italic> 0.001. Abbreviations as in <xref rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">Figures&#x000a0;1</xref>, <xref rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, and <xref rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr4"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec3"><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0085">ICB has been shown to promote cardiovascular disease and aggravate atherosclerosis in patients.<xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr"><sup>10</sup></xref> Recently, combination therapy of PD-1&#x02013; and LAG3-blocking antibodies has been approved for use in patients with unresectable or metastatic melanoma. Our study demonstrates that LAG3 regulates T cell activation in atherosclerotic mice and that loss of LAG3 function promotes T cell infiltration in atherosclerotic plaques and surrounding vascular adventitia (see <xref rid="undfig2" ref-type="fig">Central Illustration</xref>).<fig id="undfig2"><label>Central Illustration</label><caption><p>LAG3 Regulates T Cell Activation and Plaque Infiltration in Atherosclerotic Mice</p><p>Genetic loss of lymphocyte-activation gene 3 (LAG3) or LAG3 blockade in combination with programmed cell death protein-1 (PD-1) blockade in atherosclerotic mice promotes T cell activation and accumulation of T cells in plaques and adventitia. mAb&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;monoclonal antibody.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="gr5"/></fig></p><p id="p0090">The effects of loss of LAG3 on immune function and atherosclerosis observed in our study is in line with that observed for studies of other immune checkpoint molecules. Similar to atherosclerotic <italic>Lag3</italic><sup><italic>-/-</italic></sup> mice, both PD-1 and PD-L1 deficiency promoted influx of T cells to atherosclerotic lesions and increased levels of T cell activation and cytokine production.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>, <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref> Antibody-mediated blockade of the PD-1 pathway promoted accumulation of T cells in lesions without any effect on plaque size.<xref rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr"><sup>6</sup></xref> However, atherosclerotic mice lacking PD-1 or PD-L1 displayed increased lesion size. A recent study investigating PD-1/CTLA-4 combination therapy observed a similar phenotype of increased T cell accumulation in lesions without changes in plaque size, although demonstrating an increase in plaque necrotic core area.<xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr"><sup>9</sup></xref> In our study, we observed an additive effect of PD-1 and LAG3 blockade on T cell activation and cytokine production. However, we did not observe any difference in plaque T cell infiltration comparing anti-PD-1 monotherapy and anti-PD-1/anti-LAG3 combination therapy, although the anti-PD-1/anti-LAG3 combination therapy treatment group displayed levels significantly above the control group. This suggests that treatment with LAG3-blocking antibodies in patients may promote infiltration of highly inflammatory T cells to the atherosclerotic lesions and potentially promote plaque destabilization leading to cardiovascular events. Long-term follow-up studies are needed to evaluate whether combined PD-1 and LAG3 blockade has cardiovascular side effects and whether increased cardiovascular monitoring in these patients is warranted. Notably, in the MESA (Multi-Ethnic Study of Atherosclerosis) study, levels of soluble LAG3 were inversely associated with risk of coronary heart disease.<xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr"><sup>22</sup></xref> Our findings suggest potential cardiovascular implications in individuals with deficiencies in LAG3 production.</p><p id="p0095">One consistent finding in both LAG3-deficient mice and anti-LAG3&#x02013;treated mice is expansion of both conventional effector T cells and Tregs. It has previously been demonstrated that loss of LAG3 promotes Treg expansion and function.<xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr"><sup>23</sup></xref> Similarly, studies have shown that PD-1 blockade promotes Treg function, and that Tregs may promote progression of cancer in a subset of cancer patients that respond to anti-PD-1 therapy by expansion of Tregs.<xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr"><sup>24</sup></xref> It is possible that in our model, proatherogenic effects of loss of LAG3 leading to activated cytokine-producing T cells are partially countered by antiatherogenic Treg expansion, leading to a net-zero effect on plaque size. We propose that the observed increased accumulation of T cells in plaques of LAG3 deficient mice or after LAG3/PD-1 blockade is due to a combination of factors including increased generation of tissue-homing effector T cells as well as possibly augmented autoimmune responses against putative self-antigens such as apolipoprotein B. Further studies are required to evaluate expansion of autoreactive T cells after ICB treatment.</p><sec id="sec3.1"><title>Study limitations</title><p id="p0100">First, we cannot rule out differences in functionality between the anti-LAG3 antibody used in our study compared with human antibodies used for blocking LAG3 (eg, relatimab). Second, it is possible that the age of mice used for our studies may have affected the impact of LAG3 blockade, as expression of markers of exhaustion are known to increase in aged mice.<xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr"><sup>25</sup></xref> A similar limitation is that we were only able to treat mice with anti-PD-1 or anti-LAG3 antibodies for 4&#x000a0;weeks because these were rat antibodies, which can induce a mouse&#x02013;anti-rat immunoglobulin response that would impair the blocking function. If a longer period of effective treatment were possible, it may have further aggravated plaque inflammation or plaque burden. In addition, further studies are needed to evaluate if plaque inflammation is reversed is upon cessation of ICB treatment. Third, the mechanisms underlying T&#x000a0;cell activation and plaque accumulation after LAG3 deficiency or blockade are beyond the scope of this study. However, recent work suggests that LAG3 exerts its immunoregulatory effects by reducing T cell receptor signaling, and that T cells lacking LAG3 have a lower threshold for proliferation.<xref rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr"><sup>26</sup></xref> This is consistent with our results demonstrating increased proliferation of T cells in LAG3-deficient mice or mice given LAG3-blocking antibodies. We have also recently reported that bone marrow&#x02013;derived dendritic cells lacking LAG3 showed enhanced antigen-induced CD4<sup>+</sup> T cell activation and proliferation, strongly suggesting that LAG3 in non&#x02013;T cells significantly influences T cell function.<xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr"><sup>27</sup></xref></p></sec></sec><sec id="sec4"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="p0105">We demonstrate that LAG3 deficiency promotes activation and recruitment of proatherogenic T cells to atherosclerotic plaques and that LAG3 and PD-1 blockade have an additive effect on T cell activation. Although atherosclerotic lesion size was not affected by either LAG3 deficiency or blockade, increased T cell activation and lesional infiltration of T cells suggests risk of plaque inflammation and destabilization. These findings encourage follow-up studies of cardiovascular events in patients treated with LAG3/PD-1&#x02013;blocking antibodies.<boxed-text id="dtbox1"><label>Perspectives</label><p id="p0110"><bold>COMPETENCY IN MEDICAL KNOWLEDGE:</bold> LAG3, a novel target for next-generation ICB, regulates T cell activation and infiltration of T cells in atherosclerotic plaques in a mouse model of atherosclerosis.</p><p id="p0115"><bold>TRANSLATIONAL OUTLOOK:</bold> This study adds to the growing evidence of ICB therapies promoting plaque inflammation. Clinical studies are required to evaluate potential adverse effects of novel anti-LAG3 therapeutics on cardiovascular disease.</p></boxed-text></p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Funding Support and Author Disclosures</title><p id="p0120">Dr Engelbertsen was supported by the Swedish Heart-Lung Foundation (#20200522, #20190449), Dr Rodriguez was supported by National Institutes of Health HL131862 and the Linda and David Roth Chair for Cardiovascular Research; is an inventor of issued patents related to LAG3; and is the founder of Lipid Genomics. Dr Lichtman was supported by National Institutes of Health HL131862. All other authors have reported that they have no relationships relevant to the contents of this paper to disclose.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="cebib0010"><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref1"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pardoll</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The blockade of immune checkpoints in cancer immunotherapy</article-title><source>Nat Rev Cancer</source><volume>12</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>252</fpage><lpage>264</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22437870</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moslehi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lichtman</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharpe</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Galluzzi</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitsis</surname><given-names>R.N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immune checkpoint inhibitor-associated myocarditis: manifestations and mechanisms</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Clin Invest</source><volume>131</volume><year>2021</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e145186</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref3"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Postow</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sidlow</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellmann</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immune-related adverse events associated with immune checkpoint blockade</article-title><source>N&#x000a0;Engl J Med</source><volume>378</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>158</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29320654</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref4"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>D.Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salem</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>J.V.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Fatal toxic effects associated with immune checkpoint inhibitors: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title><source>JAMA Oncol</source><volume>4</volume><year>2018</year><fpage>1721</fpage><lpage>1728</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30242316</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref5"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Witztum</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lichtman</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The influence of innate and adaptive immune responses on atherosclerosis</article-title><source>Annu Rev Pathol</source><volume>9</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>73</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23937439</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref6"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bu</surname><given-names>D.X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarrio</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maganto-Garcia</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impairment of the programmed cell death-1 pathway increases atherosclerotic lesion development and inflammation</article-title><source>Arterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol</source><volume>31</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>1100</fpage><lpage>1107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21393583</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref7"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gotsman</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grabie</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dacosta</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sukhova</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharpe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lichtman</surname><given-names>A.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proatherogenic immune responses are regulated by the PD-1/PD-L pathway in mice</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Clin Invest</source><volume>117</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>2974</fpage><lpage>2982</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17853943</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref8"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cochain</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaudhari</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wiendl</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckstein</surname><given-names>H.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zernecke</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Programmed cell death-1 deficiency exacerbates T cell activation and atherogenesis despite expansion of regulatory T cells in atherosclerosis-prone mice</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>9</volume><year>2014</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e93280</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref9"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poels</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Leent</surname><given-names>M.M.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boutros</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Immune checkpoint inhibitor therapy aggravates T cell-driven plaque inflammation in atherosclerosis</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Am Coll Cardiol CardioOnc</source><volume>2</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>599</fpage><lpage>610</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref10"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drobni</surname><given-names>Z.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvi</surname><given-names>R.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Taron</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Association between immune checkpoint inhibitors with cardiovascular events and atherosclerotic plaque</article-title><source>Circulation</source><volume>142</volume><year>2020</year><fpage>2299</fpage><lpage>2311</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">33003973</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref11"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>L.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marciscano</surname><given-names>A.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Drake</surname><given-names>C.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vignali</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>LAG3 (CD223) as a cancer immunotherapy target</article-title><source>Immunol Rev</source><volume>276</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>80</fpage><lpage>96</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28258692</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref12"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Metalloproteases regulate T-cell proliferation and effector function via LAG-3</article-title><source>EMBO J</source><volume>26</volume><year>2007</year><fpage>494</fpage><lpage>504</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17245433</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref13"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giles</surname><given-names>J.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>TOX transcriptionally and epigenetically programs CD8(+) T cell exhaustion</article-title><source>Nature</source><volume>571</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>211</fpage><lpage>218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31207603</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref14"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bettini</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Szymczak-Workman</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Cutting edge: accelerated autoimmune diabetes in the absence of LAG-3</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Immunol</source><volume>187</volume><year>2011</year><fpage>3493</fpage><lpage>3498</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21873518</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref15"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tawbi</surname><given-names>H.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schadendorf</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipson</surname><given-names>E.J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Relatlimab and nivolumab versus nivolumab in untreated advanced melanoma</article-title><source>N&#x000a0;Engl J Med</source><volume>386</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>34</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34986285</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref16"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miyazaki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dierich</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Benoist</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathis</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Independent modes of natural killing distinguished in mice lacking Lag3</article-title><source>Science</source><volume>272</volume><year>1996</year><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8602528</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref17"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Engelbertsen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Autio</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verwilligen</surname><given-names>R.A.F.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Increased lymphocyte activation and atherosclerosis in CD47-deficient mice</article-title><source>Sci Rep</source><volume>9</volume><year>2019</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10608</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref18"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Virmani</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolodgie</surname><given-names>F.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farb</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lessons from sudden coronary death: a comprehensive morphological classification scheme for atherosclerotic lesions</article-title><source>Arterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol</source><volume>20</volume><year>2000</year><fpage>1262</fpage><lpage>1275</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10807742</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref19"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bjorklund</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hollensen</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hagensen</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Induction of atherosclerosis in mice and hamsters without germline genetic engineering</article-title><source>Circ Res</source><volume>114</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>1684</fpage><lpage>1689</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24677271</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref20"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maruhashi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugiura</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okazaki</surname><given-names>I.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okazaki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>LAG-3: from molecular functions to clinical applications</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Immunother Cancer</source><volume>8</volume><year>2020</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e001014</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref21"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>B.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sen</surname><given-names>D.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Al Abosy</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Subsets of exhausted CD8(+) T cells differentially mediate tumor control and respond to checkpoint blockade</article-title><source>Nat Immunol</source><volume>20</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>326</fpage><lpage>336</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30778252</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref22"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Golden</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kolmakova</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sura</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Lymphocyte activation gene 3 and coronary artery disease</article-title><source>JCI Insight</source><volume>1</volume><year>2016</year><object-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e88628</object-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref23"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chikina</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Szymczak-Workman</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>LAG3 limits regulatory T cell proliferation and function in autoimmune diabetes</article-title><source>Sci Immunol</source><volume>2</volume><year>2017</year><fpage>eaah4569</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28783703</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref24"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamada</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Togashi</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tay</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>PD-1(+) regulatory T cells amplified by PD-1 blockade promote hyperprogression of cancer</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source><volume>116</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>9999</fpage><lpage>10008</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31028147</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref25"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Decman</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Laidlaw</surname><given-names>B.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Doering</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Defective CD8&#x000a0;T cell responses in aged mice are due to quantitative and qualitative changes in virus-specific precursors</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Immunol</source><volume>188</volume><year>2012</year><fpage>1933</fpage><lpage>1941</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22246631</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref26"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guy</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitrea</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chou</surname><given-names>P.C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>LAG3 associates with TCR-CD3 complexes and suppresses signaling by driving co-receptor-Lck dissociation</article-title><source>Nat Immunol</source><volume>23</volume><year>2022</year><fpage>757</fpage><lpage>767</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35437325</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="sref27"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garcia Cruz</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giri</surname><given-names>R.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gamiotea Turro</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balsbaugh</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adler</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lymphocyte activation gene-3 regulates dendritic cell metabolic programing and T cell priming function</article-title><source>J&#x000a0;Immunol</source><volume>207</volume><year>2021</year><fpage>2374</fpage><lpage>2384</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">34588222</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec id="appsec1"><title>Appendix</title><p id="p0125">
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="mmc1"><caption><title>Supplemental Figures&#x000a0;1&#x02013;4</title></caption><media xlink:href="mmc1.docx"/></supplementary-material>
</p></sec><fn-group><fn id="d35e418"><p id="ntpara0015aa">The authors attest they are in compliance with human studies committees and animal welfare regulations of the authors&#x02019; institutions and Food and Drug Administration guidelines, including patient consent where appropriate. For more information, visit the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.jacc.org/author-center" id="interref1">Author Center</ext-link>.</p></fn><fn id="appsec2"><p>Appendix</p><p id="p0130">For supplemental figures, please see the online version of this paper.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>